All right, and welcome.
Welcome everyone.
This is our second public town hall on the open source AI definition.
The process that the open source initiative has started more than a year ago now.
So a little ground rules before we start, we have these community agreements and I love
to have your comments on these one person at a time.
Meaning make space for others.
If you have the tendency to speak a lot, try yourself.
Think about being quiet and allow others to speak up.
And if you're the kind of person who usually doesn't speak, I highly encourage you to raise
your hand, write down your comments on the chat or take the mic.
We want to hear your voice.
We want to hear your comments.
Everyone is welcome.
Be nice.
I don't think that we need to be talking too much about this.
We expect everyone to go through this hard work without being hard themselves.
And another couple of points, like we need to keep moving.
And this means that if we face an obstacle during our conversations and as we are drafting
the open source AI definition, we may want to face recognize that we have an obstacle
or something hard to deal with.
But during the meetings, we try to keep on moving.
And we'll get back to the hard part later.
So then we go towards the destination.
And focus on solutions.
That means this is pioneer work.
It's a multi-stakeholder process.
And we know that there are a lot of things that don't work that can be done better.
But we need to focus on what works and keep marching towards the end goal.
And the end goal is to have the open source AI definition version 1 by the end of the
year.
By ideally October.
We started more than a year ago.
And we need to have a shared understanding among multiple experts in various disciplines
around the world.
This definition is not coming from a sacred text given by a genius or a saint or some
other form of venerable entity.
It needs to be built by us.
And we need to build an understanding together as we move forward before we can call this
version 1.0.
And I said we started some time ago now.
And this is what we have achieved so far.
We have a document that we're calling this definition.
And it's made of a few parts.
There is a definition of AI system at the beginning which is the same as the definition
used by the organization for economic cooperation and development.
OECD.
And there's a preamble that contains the basic principles of why we need open source AI.
And also mention of what is out of scope.
Meaning the things that we're not covering in the definition.
Then for freedoms which is the shortest possible answer to the question what is open source
AI and followed by a checklist to evaluate legal documents, not just licenses that are
used to grant the four freedoms to the components and elements of an AI system.
So we have done quite a bit of work on the part above the checklist.
And that's what we're missing.
We're missing the checklist.
That's what we're focusing on.
That's what we focused on the last couple of weeks.
Since our last meeting.
So what is open source AI in terms of the four freedoms?
This is the text that we have now in draft four.
And after a few reviews with a few experts, I don't think that this is up for discussion.
But I don't think that there are a lot of controversies or controversial statements
in here.
I think it should be quite fairly understood and fairly well supported.
Now what we need to do in terms of question that we need to find an answer for, the next
big thing is to understand what is the preferred form to make modifications to an AI system.
Because if you those of you who are familiar with the open source definition and the free
software definition, the preferred form to make modification is quite crucial to understand
how you can make how you can exercise your freedom on software.
To exercise your freedoms on software, for example, the freedom to study or the freedom
to modify the software, you need access to the source code of that program.
And we need to find an equivalent of source code of the program for the AI system.
And the proposed path towards getting there is to use this multiple steps.
First start from the concept of AI system.
Now AI system as defined by the OECD means to simplify a system, a digital system that
is capable given an input to generate an output with various degrees of independence from
human interactions.
So input, magic collaboration, output.
Now for the first step that we're working on now is to find the list of components that
are necessary to use, study, modify, share an AI system.
And depending on the component, then from the list of components, we're going to look
at each of these components to see if in which in each legal, which legal framework, legal
regimes they operate under.
So if it's, for example, the inference code or the training code that is software, it's
under the what we already know that is covered by software.
So it's going to be what people refer to as usually intellectual property or things like
that.
If it's data, then we have different regime.
And this is also going to be an exercise where we're going to be identifying potential gaps.
But we already know, for example, that large language models, the weights, for example,
are not clearly, are not yet clearly labeled either as data or software, and they may fall
into some other regime.
So there's going to be conversations around there.
And then we're going to look at existing frameworks.
I mean, for each component, we're going to look at the legal documents that go with them
and see if there is any gaps.
And reading them and analyzing them, identify common traits.
And finally, we should have, after repeating this exercise for many different AI systems,
we're going to have something that looks like a valuable checklist that we can use for many
years probably, hopefully.
So last week I said the past weeks we have started working to analyze Lama 2 as an AI
system as an example.
And this is what we discovered in the meetings and online conversations that we had last
week.
We assembled a working group made of these people from different organizations, different
expertise, all of them participating in the personal capacity.
This is one of the -- none of them is authorized to speak for the company, but they are working
-- they're collaborating with us.
And the -- so the purpose of the meeting is -- I mean, we show the purpose of the meeting.
It's part of the -- part of a track of work that is testing the system to discover the
components that are available, like the -- and so make that list and identify which ones
of them are absolutely necessary for -- to exercise each of the individual freedoms.
Like the study -- use, study, modify, and share.
And so we have reviewed the table of components that we have -- that we have borrowed.
We've been following the work of the Linux Foundation, AI and data foundation, and data
group, they've been working on a document on their own.
And that contains a pretty long, pretty detailed list of components.
And we've used that as a conversation starter for our exercise.
We have -- so this is what we've done.
We have separated the list of components into four main blocks.
Well, three main blocks and one smaller block.
One for things that we call code.
That is software.
And we have, for example, looking at the code, list of components that we call code.
And apply to the exercise -- I mean, the function of using an AI system.
So getting an output from an AI system.
Asked the group to write down if that component was necessary, strictly necessary or not.
For running or using the system.
And this is the first result for the code.
And then the next question is looking at the data.
Separated into many -- you see many different types of datasets in here.
And we asked what is necessary to use Llama2 in terms of data.
And as you can see, most of the answers are in the not necessary.
And we also captured in the document the comments on nuanced approaches.
It's not necessarily it would be nice to have.
And this is something that we want to debate further.
I'm gonna ask a question to you afterwards.
And finally, on the model itself, so the model weights, parameters, architecture, model card,
et cetera, we asked people here to describe what is needed to use.
I gotta say there was a little bit of a lot of actually a lot of conversations during
the meeting around the meaning of these words.
And there was a major misunderstanding on the word model parameters.
Because in the intention of the paper from the LFAI data, which is a very early draft,
so it's not really meant to be quoted yet, model parameters contains both model weights
and model biases and parameters, hyperparameters and other elements.
So there was a little bit of confusion.
But there was -- you know, the group seemed to agree that, of course, you need the model
weights to run, to use Llama2.
And other components like model card, some people interpreted the definition of model
card as something that is necessary for use.
And then finally, the last group of elements or components is on the documentation, the
supporting documentation.
Like, the availability of a thorough research paper for the execution, you know, for running
Llama2 is nice to have.
I guess, you know, you can understand a lot of things.
But it's actually not strictly -- what is strictly or much more necessary is have documentation
on the usage.
And this is the current status.
We didn't get through -- we didn't get through the first meeting, during the first meeting
through the other freedoms, Modify and others.
But we're gonna keep on iterating with the others.
So yeah.
This is what we need to do next.
It's to ask these questions on what you need to study.
So understand how the Llama2 was built, fine-tuned, how it can be fine-tuned, what biases are
in the dataset.
And things like that.
Explain its performance.
And on the Modify questions are more on the -- what are the tools, techniques that we
can use to fine-tune, optimize, get a different output from -- or faster outputs from the
model or more accurate.
And finally, in order to share it, what are we gonna do?
You know, what is necessary, what is needed?
So for us, the next steps are continuing on this process of running these meetings and
starting new AI systems.
We've already -- I've already asked a few people who volunteered to analyze Pythia.
But we need to start parallel the process for Bloom and Mistral.
And also we want to look at AI systems that are not generative AI, that are not large
language models.
And like inside OpenCV, the Open Computer Vision Project, there are a lot of neural
networks and other kind of AI that are not generative AI.
So they pose a slightly different -- slightly different questions if we want to look into
those.
So if you know anyone in those areas, point them our way.
And I'll give you also more information about how to engage later.
And we also need to validate this list of components.
As I mentioned, we worked with the AI and data from Linux Foundation.
But we know that the -- that their paper is not peer-reviewed.
And their working paper, they're still working on it.
So we need to provide feedback to them.
But also we need to see whether that list of components is enough or if we need to keep
on improving it.
So to reiterate our timeline, it still looks like this.
We want to have a new draft of the definition in February.
And then a regular cadence every month.
Have a new draft of the definition.
Refining at every step.
And most importantly, the most important part is as we refine this step, we also have more
publicity to it, more people supporting it, endorsing it.
And we need it to -- we want to get to a point in between the end of May, early June, where
we have enough support and enough endorsements collected from a variety of different stakeholders
to be able to call the definition feature complete and issue a release candidate, first
release candidate.
Then between June and October, we want to get into a series of conferences, a series
of meetings around the world with me and other volunteers who have participated in the drafting
process.
Maybe some of the original endorsers that participated to release candidate work.
And push it through a big exposure and a round of larger feedback.
And by October, gain like double the amount of endorsers and be able to call it version
1.0.
And because version 1.0 will be basically feature complete license that enough organizations
from a variety of interests will be supporting it and be able to endorse it.
And say we're going to be using it.
But then after version 1, we know that there's going to be more work to be done.
So in terms of stakeholders that we want to have in the rooms to work with us on the definition,
we need to find a way to engage with policymakers.
That is we have some contacts and we need to have a little bit more of conversations
with people who are working in the government space, in the policymaking space.
Even though of course regulators will not be giving comments to us.
People who write the legislation.
And we will not engage with people who write legislation directly because we cannot as
an American.
But we want to hear from the people who are in this space.
Because we notice that there is legislators are concerned about abuse of AI.
And there is already starting to emerge a vision that open source AI or open AI widely
available models and AI are capable of influencing elections or creating havoc in the society
in general.
So we need to make sure that whatever definition comes out of this process is not seen as a
threat to society by regulators.
That's something we need to be very careful about.
And we need to explain this as we go.
Understanding the problematics and solve them as soon as possible.
And we need also to engage a lot with end users.
So people who are like interacting with a bot at a bank.
Or subjects.
These are people who don't know that they're talking to an AI and they are affected by
the automatic decisions, for example.
We need to engage with them.
So how a reminder, this is doesn't end with 1.0.
We already started to define to think about what's going to be the future of 1.0.
Like the open source initiative and its board has set up is setting up a new committee to
brainstorm to think about the maintenance of this definition that is coming very quickly
in a space that is evolving even faster, even more rapidly.
So we need to prepare to catch up and to have a process to maintain the definition to keep
it valid over time.
And so what we're launching today is a new forum.
We'll keep on doing these biweekly town halls and we'll keep on adding opportunities to
volunteer to help out.
We're working on a new version of the landing page to have the information all about this
process all in one place.
And we've done that.
We're working on this.
And as I said, setting up the board for managing the future.
So as a big announcement for you is to the opening of the forums to have this conversation
publicly online in order to join the forum.
The forum uses the single sign on with other OSIs website.
So you can you need to become a member of OSI.
That is a free member.
We have three tiers.
There is a free membership.
So you don't have to worry about having to pay.
Or if this is an opportunity for you to support this work, which is very important, you can
become a full member and donate to us from $50 a year and up.
And on the forums you will find the links to the latest drafts.
We will keep on asking questions on the forums.
We'll keep on having the conversations we're having here constantly on the forums.
And with that, I will I see that there are some questions on the chat.
If you prefer, I can unmute all of you.
You can also take the mic and speak.
So I'll answer the question from Dirk.
What licenses are required for the data and software components in the AI system?
So we'll be talking about it.
From the software components, it's I think that the answer is going to be quite easy.
Anything that is recognizably software, we need to use licenses that have been approved
by the open source definition.
For the data component, it's we'll have to have conversations around that.
I think we are working with organizations like Creative Commons and I mentioned the
Linux Foundation AI Data.
They have their licenses.
There are different licenses that qualify as open data.
The open data world has a different culture than the open source movement and the open
source world.
The data people, I mean, the people who have been dealing with open data that I met, I'm
not sure how much they have been thinking about the fact that their data is actionable.
We need to understand with them, we need to work with them to understand exactly what
they think of their space once the space of open data, once it becomes actionable just
like software.
In other words, to make a pretty simple example, not many data sets out there are maintained
in a way that they can be modified and fixed.
One of the latest examples that I noticed is that in an open data set that has been
used to train a lot of the large language models had reported, I mean, someone analyzed
it years ago and found that it contained a lot of images that were illegal in many parts
of the world and absolutely abhorrent, including child porn and atrocious material.
Now the project that the people, the group that maintains this data set, which is open,
never received a public issue.
This is on GitHub, this data set.
It's a GitHub project and there was no issue filed, but there was a paper, a research paper
filed that described the bad material in the data set.
So I think that there is work that needs to be done into this community because they're
completely different and they're probably inside a similar conundrum that we as open
source groups are when it comes to AI.
Our world is being disrupted, let's say, modified.
I don't know if that explains it.
Any other questions?
Curiosities?
Thanks, Kellen.
Yeah, glad to see you.
And I hope that we can, yeah, we can work together soon.
Any other concerns, questions?
I'll give you time to start playing with the forums and maybe if you have any technical
issues, you can, we can do, play with it.
All right.
No more questions.
I'm going to stop the recording.
Thanks.
Bye.