Yeah, let's go with it.
All right.
Okay, welcome everyone.
So you are attending the online public town hall for the open source AI definition on
March 8th, 2024.
My name is Mare Joyce.
My pronouns are she and her, and I'm the process facilitator for creating this definition as
a multi-stakeholder co-design process.
Okay, so these are community agreements.
Some of you have already seen them.
I'll go over them briefly.
So one mic, one speaker, allowing one person to speak at a time, no interrupting.
Take space, make space if you tend to speak up.
Allow space for others to speak.
If you tend not to speak, we do invite you to share.
Kindness, just remembering that the work is hard, but we don't have to be, and to just
be gentle with each other and curious.
And of course, hate speech and insults are not permitted in the spaces that we host.
Forward motion just means that we focus on what's possible and that we note obstacles
and then we route around them and move forward and come back when needed, but that we don't
let complexity stop our project from moving forward.
Solution seeking is connected to that.
So we just, we know that suggesting new ideas and options is vulnerable, but it is crucial.
And this is how we resolve those complexities that we just mentioned.
And are there any other norms that you would like to see in this meeting?
If you have any, you can type them in the chat.
I also realized that there's a transparency norm that we should add here, just to say
that this will be posted publicly, this video will be posted publicly.
Okay.
Looks like we don't have any other comments.
I will continue.
So yes, our objective for 2024 is to release version 1.0 of the open source AI definition.
And this is what the definition looks like.
We define AI system.
There is a preamble that basically makes an argument for why this definition is necessary.
There are certain out of scope issues.
The URL is up at the top.
If you'd like to see the document.
And there are the four freedoms, which I will go into in greater detail.
And then there's this license checklist, which is looking at specifically which components
of an AI system must be open in order for the system to be called open according to
this definition.
These are the freedoms.
These were coming from earlier documents in the open source movement, but were verified
and drafted specifically for this purpose by co-design workshops at the end of 2023.
So using the system for any purpose without having to ask for permission, studying how
the system works and inspecting its components, modifying the system to change its recommendations
and predictions and to adapt it to your needs and sharing the system with or without modification
for any purpose are the overarching requirements of an open source AI system.
And now what we're going to talk about is the most recent work we've been doing, which
is recommendations of working groups that have been looking at AI systems to develop
this list of required components.
So this is what we're up to with systems review, which is also called track one of our project.
We're not going too deeply into different tracks, but for those of you who have that
context, this is track one of three.
So what we have completed is that we analyzed a sample of AI systems to identify precisely
required components for study, use, modification and sharing.
And what we are going to do next is for each component of these systems, check their availability
and the conditions for use and distribution.
So legal documents and licenses, because that is the mechanism by which OSI verifies a piece
of technology is open source or not is through licenses and legal documents.
Then we will generalize the findings and complete a checklist for OSI license committee, get
endorsement from major stakeholders.
And that will be called that's release candidate one, which will proceed version 1.0, which
of course we will refine and rough dates are RC1 is June and then version 1.0 is October.
And anything to add to the slide, Stefano?
No, this to me looks complete.
It's more about if anyone has any comments so far, I mean, you can use the chat and keep
on adding comments.
Yeah.
Okay.
Sounds good.
So these are the four systems that we developed work groups around and this is why we chose
them.
We wanted to have a diversity of approaches.
So we looked at Pythia, an open science project with a permissive license, Bloom, another
open science project with lots of details with release, but with a restrictive license.
And I'm sure all these descriptions could be, might be different for different people,
but this is how we were looking at the systems.
Lama2, obviously a commercial project with a restrictive license, OpenCV, an open source
project with ML components, but let's have generative AI.
And so these were the work group members having public membership as part of the transparency
commitment we have just so that you know, who are the people that are making these recommendations?
Cause these are particularly empowered stakeholders in determining what the components of the
definition will be.
And we did additional outreach to have a better, particularly racial and geographic representation.
So you can take a look at that later, I guess.
We do have posted on the forum, all these, this information as well.
And what the, what the members of the working groups did, this might be information that
some of you have already heard, but I'll go through it for those who are new, is that
they voted on, we took a list of components from a forthcoming paper.
Can we, can we name the paper yet Stefano?
Cause it is forthcoming.
We can name it.
Yes.
Okay.
Excellent.
So it's called the Model Openness Framework.
It's being, it was written primarily by researchers connected to the Linux Foundation, although
with other collaborators as well, it's going to be released on ArchiveX, I think imminently,
maybe even today or tomorrow.
Anyway, they came up with this really nice generalized list of AI system components.
And so we use their list and then we created this voting system.
Do you think this component is necessary to use, study, modify, share, and then members
of the working groups with their initials.
So again, there's transparency who's saying that what is required voted.
And this is just a screenshot of a slide from the LAMA working group.
And yeah, if you have any questions, just put them in the chat.
And if I don't see them, Stefano will see them.
And then we compiled all the votes across all the working groups.
And I developed a rubric for basically picking a vote total and turning it into a recommendation
for a requirement.
And I think, do I have a zoom in on that?
I do not have a zoom in on that.
So if you look at the upper, I don't know which corner it is, upper left or right, but
you see this part of the slide, for me, it's the upper right, which says legend.
And it's basically based on the mean number of votes, something that was more than two
times the mean was an automatic yes, this is required on down to likely yes, maybe lean
no and then no for less than, okay, between I think 0.5 and zero or zero less than 0.5
and zero.
Yeah.
So you can kind of see through this color coding how each component ranked, you can
see there's a few here that are yeses, like training validation and testing code and inference
code.
And then many lean no's, for example, data set.
And then we looked at multiple different data sets.
So that was different from the model openness framework.
They just had data set, but we thought that's such an important part of the system that
we broke it out into multiple different types of data set to really get as much input as
possible on whether that should be required.
And then this is the result of the voting of that applying the rubric to the votes was
that the required elements were and are training validation and testing code, inference code,
model architecture, model parameters, which includes weights, supporting libraries and
tools which includes things like tokenizers and hyperparameter search if used.
And then down through a likely required data processing code, maybe the data sets as you
saw not likely elements like the model card, not required data card, sample model, technical
report.
And then what is new from I think some of you have been in previous meetings is that
we have for version 6.0 made this distinction.
So the required components, we took everything that was required plus likely required.
So the data pre-processing code and those are the required components.
And then everything else is optional.
So there's nothing that we're saying don't include this, but everything else is listed
as appreciated, but not required.
And I think let's see what's next.
I feel like this might be a good place to pause.
Maybe we do this.
Do you want to pause here for questions, Stefano, or do you want to go into this greater detail
about version 6.0 and then pause?
Yeah, let's wait and see if anyone has any questions so far.
We can definitely take a break.
Yeah.
So any kind of questions or thoughts on how we got here and where we are?
Okay.
Thank you.
I'm muted basically, everyone.
If anyone wants to jump, they can use voice or if you feel more comfortable, you can type.
Yeah.
And there's a raise hand function at the bottom like in Zoom as well.
Yep.
I don't see many questions.
Maybe we can just...
Obastium has a question.
Go ahead.
Yeah.
Hi.
Thanks for the summary.
I was just wondering if you had any priority in each column, like is data processing code
more important than training validation?
I guess on the left, everything is at the same level, but maybe on the right, some things
are more optional than others or is it something that has not been discussed?
Hasn't been discussed, frankly.
And yes, they're all required.
It's a yes or no.
Yeah, it's a yes or no.
Yeah, we can have a conversation about that.
Yeah.
Because...
Oh, let me just before those double questions, let me get another question from the next
person, Bastien, and come back to you.
Unless...
Is that okay?
Sure.
No problem.
Yes.
Okay.
Thanks.
All right.
Jacob?
Yeah.
You guys can hear me, right?
Correct.
Yep.
Okay, cool.
Yeah, sure.
So I guess one question I had is if some of the reasoning around decisions that were made
within these groups is available.
I'd just be curious, particularly on the datasets portion.
I guess my intuition is that if something is open source, we should be able to verify
its legality completely.
And without access to the datasets or in some way, then that may be a lot more difficult.
I'm not saying complete access to the datasets.
But some access may be worthwhile.
Go ahead, Stef.
Yeah.
I can give an argument.
So the question of legality may not be appropriate for the open source definition.
It's a separate conversation.
But I do believe, and there were conversations inside the group about that understanding
of the datasets.
And in fact, one of the reasons why you see there the required components, the data pre-processing
code is that many of the groups had debated about which of the -- what's necessary, what
level of understanding do you need to have in order to be able to feel safe about using
a model or have enough information, the transparency requirements that look like they're going
to be mandated by law anyway, at least in Europe, and other information about provenance
and assessing risk in deployments, bias calculation, and all of those things.
So the conversation went -- this is the -- it's the torn issue, access to the datasets, what
is necessary, what is required, what level of depth do you need to have access to it.
And it's something that we're probably going to keep continuing debating.
What seemed clear to me is that the original dataset, having access to it completely and
fully in a way that you can download it, et cetera, and retrain with the purpose of retraining
or rebuilding from scratch a model that you have received, it's a requirement that is
not strictly necessary.
At least there was pretty much -- pretty good agreement on that front.
>> Thank you.
And I see you have a raised hand again, Jacob.
I'm just going to go to another question, and we can come back to you.
So Shala asks -- yeah, exactly.
No, thank you.
So Shala asks, did any of the systems reviewed meet the required components?
So let me go back to the -- yeah.
So it wasn't that we were trying to evaluate whether any system had all of its components
required.
It was more of a comparison.
And no, there was no system where all the components were considered to be required.
But the ones that are required are simply the ones on this list under the lime green
required title.
And those are the ones that then we moved into this binary distinction of required and
not, which will appear in definition 0.0.6.
And feel free to raise your hand or ask a follow-up question in case I didn't ask.
Okay.
Bastien needs to go.
Thank you for coming, Bastien.
I see -- Jacob, did you want to ask another question?
>> I want to complete the answer.
I want to add something else for Shala.
This analysis, this -- you know, the response also will come after the next phase.
We're going to be reviewing the systems and see if they have available the required components
and what conditions they're available.
What can we do with those components?
>> Okay.
Yeah, I see what you're asking, Shala.
Thank you for clarifying that, Stefano.
I see Justin is typing.
But Jacob already has his hand up.
So yes, ask your question, Jacob.
>> I should have written it down.
I apologize.
I had a thought.
It's gone now.
I'll bring it up if I remember it.
>> No problem.
No problem.
I'm going to -- let's move on to the next slide.
Because that one adds this extra information about requirements around the training method.
And then we can continue to take questions.
What do you think, Stefano?
So I think this is where you will start presenting, I think.
>> I was looking at the -- we can answer Justin.
>> Okay.
Let's do that.
>> He admitted -- no, no.
He admitted that it's outside of this.
>> Okay.
Great.
>> So this is the text that is now in the draft of -- in the draft version 6.
006.
Which is going to go live on Monday.
So it's basically completed.
And the narrative in here is to have a piece of text inside the definition of that section
of what is open source AI.
Where we describe what we actually need in order to exercise those four freedoms.
To use study, share, modify.
And that's where the text that I was talking about before, the sufficiently detailed information
of how the system was trained, and the components basically that the groups have said that they
require.
Here they are described in a more verbose way, more of a narrative rather than bullet
points talking about quoting, mentioning specifically components that are referenced in a separate
paper by -- or maintained by another organization.
So this is more about describing in a more -- in a fairly precise fashion the list of
components that require components that came out of the working group.
And here you can see, like, you need to have detailed information of how the system was
trained.
Providence of the data, the scope and characteristics.
Some of these wording also comes from the EU AI Act in terms of requirements of transparency.
So I tried to use the words included in that legislation so that thinking that it's sufficiently
-- it's been reviewed.
It's been debated.
It's been agreed upon by the -- at least by the European regulators.
And negotiated heavily.
So I'm assuming it's quite fine-tuned to represent transparency requirements in a fairly
detailed way.
So at least it's a good way to start the conversation for us.
And then in terms of code, pieces that are about the preprocessing data, the code used
for the training validation, and the supporting libraries.
And the model parameters, the weights, which should also include the checkpoints for the
intermediate stages of the training.
As well as the finalized one.
So this is what's in -- you will see on Monday on draft six as it gets published.
You want to go on to the next one?
Because this is the other thing that will be clear.
Spelled out.
Like the precondition that we need to focus on, like a very, very high-level necessary
thing, necessary feature that needs to be made available is to have the preferred form
to make modifications to the system.
And that, for machine learning, the examples that we have studied, they give us the list
of components.
This sentence here is a form to make the open source AI definition a little bit more flexible
and adaptable to other technologies should they change next year or two years from now.
At least in the short term.
Give us a little bit more flexibility.
And that's what we're going to do.
So the next step is -- the very immediate next step is to finalize the -- hit the release
button and go live with version six of the draft on Monday.
And then we're going to start the second step in track one, which is to review each of the
systems that we have already analyzed.
Maybe add some more.
I'm not against adding more at this stage.
Because we need to look at the required components that we think are necessary.
The working groups have identified as necessary.
Make a list.
And for each of the components, put the URLs, you know, where can I get them?
Where can I get it?
If it's not available, then mark it as unavailable.
And if we can get them, under what conditions?
So we're going to find out -- I can already say we know.
For Lama 2, we know that in order to download the model weights, you will have to -- you
will have to sign up on a website.
You need to give in your details.
You need to ask for permission.
And you need to sign an agreement by doing so.
And that agreement has specifications of what you can and cannot do.
And we'll log all of that information in a place.
And we'll analyze them in step three.
PTR will have different things, et cetera, et cetera.
Oh, in fact, yes.
I put together -- there is a slide with -- go ahead.
Go to the next one.
Yes.
That's the -- that's what the next table, the next working groups will do.
It's basically go through the list of required components, put the URL, and match the legal
framework.
Now, you will see that here we're talking mostly about code.
And there is one line.
So for the code parts, it's going to be easy to say that all the code made available needs
to be formally using an OSI-approved license.
And I don't think it's going to be that complicated, that part.
The model parameters instead.
That part is most likely going to raise a conversation around what legal frameworks
go around the parameters.
Those are -- there is still some, from what I hear from the legal communities, the lawyers
have diverging opinions whether parameters are copyrightable.
And if they're not copyrightable, what kind of other -- if there is any other exclusive
in property regimes or not.
And therefore, what kind of contracts -- the validity of the contracts or terms of use
and other legal tools.
Whether -- you know, which ones are better or valid, et cetera.
So it's going to spin off an interesting legal conversation.
>> Sorry.
I clicked early.
I didn't want to raise my hand before you were done.
>> No, you're good.
Go.
>> Okay.
So the first question I have, which is what I meant to ask earlier, was what constitutes
data preprocessing versus a new dataset?
Like is it -- if it's done internally to the company that is making the model, that's when
it's data preprocessing?
Or -- yeah, I guess basically how are we differentiating between those?
>> No, let me look at the paper.
The paper, it will go live later today.
And definitely on Monday.
But my memory serves me right.
The data preprocessing is the tooling that is used to do things like cleaning up, formatting
the data, and tokenizing, you know, doing the -- all the preparation work that goes
into prepare the data to be fed into -- for data ingestion, for example.
>> Right.
>> Feature engineering, you know, data, yeah, all of that code.
Oh, I guess there's a follow-up.
But I'll pause if you want to go to someone else.
>> What do you mean?
There's overlap?
>> Sorry, Mer, I couldn't hear you.
>> Yeah, you can -- yeah, let's -- yeah, good facilitation practice.
Let me go to Mo and then we can come back to this.
Mo says model architecture is defined in the code.
It overlaps with the training and validation and testing code.
Is model architecture really an independent component that can be analyzed individually?
Do you want to -- >> Once we can -- yeah, I think that once
we can point at the paper that so far we've been using generously through pre-preview,
we can have a better understanding of these technical overlaps, et cetera.
>> Yeah, the delineation between different components.
So yeah, part of this paper is that there's often multi-paragraph definitions of each
of these components.
So yeah, I think that's the best place to go for that.
Jacob, did you want to ask a follow-up?
>> Yeah.
So I guess then at least how I'm thinking about this data pre-processing and I will
be like be open -- I'm coming at this from an adversarial perspective intentionally because
I feel like that will be done, I guess.
And so basically my thought is if we don't have to know -- like if a third party can
do the pre-processing, not in terms of tokenization necessarily, but more of like sifting the
data and can create a new dataset that is proprietary and then you use that, that's
a way to obfuscate your data usage.
And so maybe that's not relevant here.
Maybe that goes too much into legality, but that's just sort of how I'm thinking about
it and I'm curious to hear what your response is.
>> It seems like it's covered by the first bullet.
Isn't a lot of that concern covered by the first bullet?
There's just so much documentation about data that's required?
Or what do you think, Stefano?
>> If I understand correctly, the question or the concern, it's about replicating the
dataset with different setups, different things in it.
Or different way of reorganizing, reshuffling the same -- using the pre-processing code
means that you have a way to rebuild -- it doesn't mean that you have access to the original
data.
You can -- you have a way to extrapolate, you have those transparency requirements that
make you -- that give you some sort of better understanding for how you would have to build
your own dataset for your own training if you want to do -- if you want to rebuild from
scratch or if you want to build from -- not rebuild from scratch, build from scratch something
else that looks or behaves similar to what you have received.
In other words, I don't think that the scenario that you're describing is a scenario that
necessarily is part of this conversation.
>> Gotcha.
Okay.
Let's go on and see what else comes up.
>> Yeah, because I think some of these questions can be -- yeah, can be described also in what
we're doing.
Another thing -- another of the things that we're doing next and partially I can talk
about here the roadshow that now it's not detailed here, but you can see on the timeline
we have these three tracks, the green, the white, and the light blue that we're following
in parallel.
And in June we're going to have the release candidate.
Once that release candidate happens, we'll have meetings in different parts of the world
and we're organizing them to show the release candidate to gain more visibility across different
communities and different practitioners, different stakeholders in order to get to release candidate
to version 1 in October.
During these meetings, we're going to spin off a conversation about data because there
is a strong requirement for good quality data sets and an increased amount of awareness
in the practice of building data sets that are valid, respectful, trustworthy, you know,
they are clean, they're transparent, they're fair in how -- what they represent, et cetera.
And there is very few of these.
There are very few data sets that are large enough, that are good enough -- that are good
in that term.
And what's becoming more clear to me also is that the data community hasn't been -- needs
to also -- to have these conversations.
So we're going to be partnering with organizations that are more into that data space and we're
going to be helping supporting conversations around data in parallel or, you know, as a
spin off of this project.
>> Jacob, go ahead.
>> Yeah, sorry.
Last one.
You touched on this just now, but I guess one thing that I've been thinking about a
lot is how do we -- or I guess OSI maybe -- take back the term?
Because I feel like it's been falsely attributed to systems that are pretty clearly not open
source by this definition.
And like you said, you're going to go and, you know, talk with more people and have those
meetings.
But, yeah, just curious what your thoughts are about that.
>> Yeah, this is a known issue, unfortunately.
Yes, exactly.
Having a definition helps to take back the term.
And having people, enough people who support it and are willing to say we're going to use
it.
This is what we mean when we say open source AI.
And they're going to be multiplying the idea.
You know, they're going to go -- so I'll tell you an anecdote.
I was in -- I was at a meeting last week with a lot of friends of open in general.
And there was a lot of pushback.
Common shared pushback against Meta's use of the open source AI name to identify, to
talk about Lama.
Lama2 specifically.
So it's -- many others will be joining in our effort to clarify the public what that
means.
And it's a little bit the same work that -- the same way that it happens with the open source
software.
Like lots of -- there is people -- some people still complain and say, well, but I mean something
else.
But there is always a very large pushback of supporters of the open source definition who
say, no, it's -- you may have all the opinions you want, but open source is defined by the
open source initiative.
And it's maintained by the open source initiative.
And that brings the cloud up.
Yeah, so that's a big thing.
This doesn't end with version 1.
We know that we will have -- most likely it's going to be -- it's going to have to be maintained
and improved and reviewed.
So the board of the OSI is already at work to think about the -- how we're going to be
maintaining -- we're going to be maintaining this definition.
Which is very different from what the open source definition for software is.
Right?
We're trying to have -- so someone was asking before I saw the meetings and -- oh, it was
Justin.
Yeah, we're talking about meetings, et cetera.
And how to participate.
So we're trying to have everything public.
So that no one gets surprised when at the end we come up with the definition.
We're having this sequence of town halls every two weeks at different times so that we can
accommodate multiple time zones.
We have discussions on the forums.
We do publish on the blog every week a summary of what's happening on the forums.
So there are multiple ways to get involved.
To stay aware and to give comments during this process.
We'll publish the roadshow.
Also the roadshow meetings are going to be in different parts of the world.
We have partnered with existing conferences.
In order to gather people who are already being at a place.
Already going to that place.
So we're going to be in -- at the -- well, we'll publish it next week.
Or the week after.
But I can say that we're going to touch every continent starting from June.
Starting from June until October.
So we're going to be in Africa in June.
We're going to be in September.
We're going to be in Hong Kong.
Europe, Paris, North America, Mexico.
I don't remember when.
So there's many, many opportunities to meet in person.
And we're raising also funds and disclosing this.
By the hope is that we're going to have also travel grants for people who want to participate.
And they can apply and get to some of these meetings.
So hopefully we'll be able to have a very good roadshow.
And gather a lot of support.
And if not, we're going to keep on going next year also.
Multiple opportunities.
>> Thank you, Sam, for offering to host us in Toronto.
Okay.
Yes.
And thank you for your comment, Jacob.
Okay.
Let's see what else we have in the deck.
Oh!
Q&A.
>> I haven't really started.
So yeah.
That's the end of our deck.
So we do have more time in the meeting.
If anyone else has a question.
And this would be a great time if you're someone who often doesn't ask a question in a meeting.
Please do.
We really invite you to.
And if you prefer to put it in the chat rather than to speak publicly, then that is also
most available to you.
>> All right.
Jacob, thank you for sharing the information.
You're welcome to join the forums if you're not already.
They're easy to use.
And should be smooth.
And once you're a you can become a free member of the OSI to join the forums.
It's very easy.
>> Yes.
I joined earlier this week.
I had some troubles with logging in.
But I got that fixed.
So...
>> Cheers.
>> Thank you, guys.
>> Thank you.
>> Bye.
>> See.
Just in typing.
But I'll wait.
But I can stop the recording at this point.
I think.
Okay.
So...
I'm going to stop the recording.