All right, here I am.
Let's start the recording and welcome everyone.
Maybe we can wait a couple of minutes and give a little bit of time for others to join.
Okay.
All right.
Let's get it started so we can use most of the time and we can also collect feedback.
So I'll try to get enough time for people to ask me questions and I'm here available.
Let's get started with some very quick community agreements.
Let's make sure that we have give time for people to speak and if you're the kind of
person who usually stays quiet, speak up, feel free to really grab time and write down.
Use the hand button if you want to get attention or write down your comment, but please, we
want to be able to, we want to hear from you.
Be nice and don't have to remind people that this is a safe space and we don't have to
we have to be gentle and we need to keep on moving.
Also if we face obstacles, we move around and we will get back to it and we want to
focus on solutions.
This is a process that is complicated and it's also quite pioneer if you want.
We don't have that history outside the organization of running this co-design process with multiple
stakeholders across the world and there are a lot of things that we know don't work and
can be done better, but we also need to keep on working because time is on us.
Is there anything else that you think we need to cover in this agreement?
All right.
Okay.
So give a recap to the people who have just started following this work.
We started a discussion to define the definition of open source AI and this is a definition
that is coming from a wide conversation with stakeholders from different sides of society
for a very wide different groups and the objective that we have is to talk to multiple experts
in various fields and disciplines around the world.
We will not be able to have some genius coming out of the basement with a definition.
It's unlikely for this to happen, so this needs to be a global conversation and we're
helping.
We hear as the open source initiative as facilitator, convener of conversations for an open source
AI definition to come out of consensus from different stakeholders and the document that
we're trying to draft looks is made of three parts.
My computer is getting really slow.
Okay.
It's made of three parts.
There is a definition of AI system and a preamble at the top and the preamble contains the basic
principles of why we need open source AI.
And there is a section also with issues that are out of scope to clarify what's not covered
in this AI definition.
Then we have the shortest possible answer to the question, what is open source AI?
And they look a lot like the four freedoms for software that many of us have been accustomed
to see.
And then the rest of it is a checklist to evaluate legal documents that are used to
grant the four freedoms above to the AI system.
And we got to the point where we had plenty of conversation in the second half of last
year, 2023, with a variety of people to have the bones, the bare bones of the definition
of AI systems, the preamble, the out of scope and the four freedoms.
And we're missing this checklist of legal documents at the end.
Yes, I will explain the checklist in more details.
So probably it's worth having a very quick overview of how we are proceeding.
We're basically retracing the history of open source, compressing those 25, 30 years of
history in a few months so that we can get to the open source AI definition.
We're tracing the steps following this sequence.
We're going from a software when it came out, there was a legal framework that was applied
to it.
And a community established itself around the principles of the GNU manifesto.
And it started writing new software, the GNU operating system and sharing that was shared
with legal agreements, legal documents that were granting rights rather than removing
them.
So that's the sequence that we're trying to re-trace.
From understanding the new artifacts, these new AI systems, how they're working and which
legal frameworks apply to them, what are the principles that we want to have applied for
granting freedoms, and then we're going to look at legal documents to grant the rights
rather than remove them.
There is one interesting principle that is written inside the GNU manifesto, and that's
the golden rule that is, it's written, we can reuse it easily to apply to the AI system.
So if I like an AI system, I must be free to share it with other people.
That's the basic principle that we want to embed that we're looking for now.
And so far, what we've learned is that we really need to define open source AI in general,
not just focus on machine learning or whatever is new and exciting in this generative AI
space of the past year and a half.
So the other thing that we have learned is we need a definition of AI system.
And we found that the one provided by the Organization for Economic Development is quite
well accepted.
It's embedded in many legislations around the world and so far can be a valid starting
point.
And at least to get the conversation started, we can improve it later.
And this system definition has this concept of it basically, you can read it, it was very
in November, it was updated by the OECD.
And the other thing that is important that we have learned is that we've established
that for AI developers, we want practitioners that academia users of AI, we want them to
have the same benefits of open source, which is the autonomy, the transparency, the fact
that they have an agency, there is agency for the user.
But we also noticed that policymakers and academia and maybe the developers themselves,
developers of AI systems, they seem to be focusing more or concerned about transparency,
explainability and other objectives.
They're not thinking about open as a value.
So we need to work to match the expectations of these two groups and make sure that open
source AI helps ease the concerns of policymakers and academia.
In other words, it does not block for example, transparent or trustworthy.
We cannot have an open source AI that will never be transparent, will never be explainable
or fair, because otherwise, there will never be an open source AI that can be adopted or
that can be even legal if we look at some of the draft legislation that is flying around
the world.
So the next question that we asked ourselves in a small group is, what basic freedoms
do we need in order to share AI systems?
And the next, the sub question is, what is the preferred form to make modifications to
an AI system?
So the basic freedoms we have started by looking at the definition, the free software
definition and tweaked the language during a few meetings in person.
And we took the language to a point where it seems fair that we can have a more public
conversation.
And this is the current draft of the open source AI definition written down and you
can see it's nothing too controversial or too complicated.
We need to be able to use the system for any purpose without having to ask for permission.
And it's quite important because that permissionless is what enabled open source, the open source
world, the open source ecosystem to thrive.
We need to be able to study, we need to be able to modify and give it to others for any
purpose and without having to ask for permission again.
Now the next big question in order to get a complete draft is, what is the preferred
form to make modifications to an AI system?
And that's what we need to do.
This is the next big exercise that we need to do.
We need to get the specification.
So how are we going to be proceeding on this?
We need to start by identifying the technical legal specifications of what is made, what
an AI system is made of.
What are the components that go into it?
And what are these, the components that are, which of these components are necessary to
use, to study, to share, modify such systems?
Once we have that list of components that we need for each of those different four verbs,
for freedoms, then we look at the legal frameworks that are for those.
And from the legal frameworks, we can evaluate the legal elements, the legal documents that
accompany them.
Matching, for example, if one component is under copyright or intellectual property in
general regime, then we can say the license, we can evaluate the license and see if that
grants the freedoms.
So after we repeat this exercise for more groups, then we'll have a better understanding.
We can create that checklist.
So here's the, how we're going to proceed.
And we're going to proceed by evaluating a few examples, very specific elements, very
specific systems like BTR or Lama2 or Bloom, and we'll split into small groups.
And we're going to ask the questions one by one.
What do I need to give input and get an output?
So that's the use or and modify, et cetera.
So for example, if we want to give one by one, let's look at PTA.
What do I need in order to get an output from PTA?
Then probably we'll need weights, inference code, for example, in this one as elements
and components.
Like then why is PTA giving an input gives one output?
This is what we need to know.
We probably need to know the architecture, what went into building the dataset, maybe
access to the dataset itself and calculate the biases, et cetera.
Then moving on, how do we modify and get a different output from PTA?
They're big question.
And finally, what we need in order to share it, you know, what share the original version
or the modified version?
So we'll need to run this exercise for more than one of these systems and write, get those
components in general, analyze the legal frameworks, analyze the legal documents, and write up
a summary.
And that's going to be our-- most likely, it's going to be our basic components of the
checklist that we have at the end of the document draft definition.
In terms of timeline, we need to work-- we need to activate, like, at least-- we need
to move very fast because everyone is-- there is already enough confusion on the market
and many groups that are talking about open source AI without having a big-- without having
a shared understanding of what that means.
And we want to get with version 1 in October of this year.
So towards the end of the year.
And this means that we should be really having a release candidate around the beginning of
the summer.
In order to get to that, we need to have monthly release cadence of drafts and a constant
public review of our work with these town halls that we're going to be running-- that
are going to be running every two weeks at different time zones.
And the important piece here is that-- so we're going to create working groups and we're
going to create working groups to analyze these AI components.
And we're going to be releasing new drafts as we go.
Monthly with a monthly cadence.
Hopefully by the end of May, early June, we'll have an in-presence meeting.
We want to have enough support from different stakeholders.
And I'm going to talk about that.
What do we expect for the release candidate?
Is to have at least a draft that is completed in all its parts.
And support from at least two organizations, two groups for each of the stakeholders in
that we have-- in the groups that we have identified that I will show in a second.
And for version one, it's basically a larger group of support.
So more stakeholders that support and endorse the definition.
And we have identified six categories of stakeholders.
The system creators, the ones who are going to be creating AI systems and they will need
to-- so the ones that will create the AI systems.
And the license creators, the ones who write the legal documents to apply to the AI system
of components.
The regulators, we want to have at least-- going to want to have conversations with regulators
to get their feedback.
If they may not be able to give us endorsements, but at least we want to hear what their thoughts.
We're going to have early exposure to that.
Then we have licensees, the ones who seek to study, modify, share an open source AI
system.
So it's engineers or developers, researchers.
On the last two categories, it's where we probably need most help is end users.
So the ones who, one, need to consume the system output, but are not necessarily interested
in studying or modifying or sharing the system.
And then the final group is the subjects, those who are affected by the effects of the
system outputs, whether they are upstream or downstream.
We use this to indicate, for example, prospective homeowners whose mortgage application is evaluated
by a bank through an AI.
That's a downstream subject.
Or for example, photographers who find their image in a training data set.
That's like content creators.
Those are upstream subjects.
We want to be talking to these organizations, too.
And we want to have their feedback.
And maybe and hopefully also they're endorsing the definition at the end.
One thing also that I want to say is that this doesn't end, this process will probably
not end with version 1, because this is going to be the first definition of open source
that has a version number attached.
So we'll need to have by the end of the year, once we announce version 1, we'll need to
have in place rules for maintenance and review of this definition.
We're probably going to need to maintain and update it, given how quickly the technical
landscape changes, we will have to adapt.
So our immediate next step is we want to have the process make it more public.
Until now, we worked with a private drafting group that has been helping.
And now we got to the point where we feel there is plenty of momentum on one hand and
plenty of shared understanding of where we stand and what are the roadblocks, the biggest
ones.
So we want to have public discussion forums.
We're starting today with this public biweekly town halls.
And this will open up also to more opportunity for more opportunities to volunteer and help
out.
We'll be updating our project landing page, the opensource.org/deepdive.
We need more stakeholders to get involved and we're raising funds.
And we're also setting up the OSI board to review and approve version 1 once it comes
out.
And the drafts are being published.
They're already public and they're already public also the comments.
You can go to deepdive/drafts and you'll find a list of the published drafts and you can
join the conversation in there.
And with that, I want to open up to questions from you.
I see that there is a little bit of a discussion here already.
Do I have domain experts?
Yes.
So some domain experts have already volunteered.
I'm talking to basically friends.
Like there is one of the developer advocates and outreach advocates at Intel.
He's a personal friend.
I'm going to talk to him next week.
The people at Luther AI have made themselves available to help out to analyze Pythia.
And I'm reaching out to developers at Meta to get an explanation of Lama, Lama 2.
And I'm happy to talk to more people.
I have other people who have also volunteered to help.
And we got expertise also inside the board to help out.
To review, to run those reviews.
The topic of content creators and the New York Times with their lawsuit.
Yes, the legal team, the legal experts inside the board are already aware of that.
They're following it.
And I'm pushing the board and the board itself.
People inside the board are getting more expertise and getting ready to even write opinions eventually
on those topics.
It's really interesting to see what's happening in the content on the content creators front
and those legal issues.
Any more curiosities?
Maybe I can spend more time to talk about that checklist idea.
The idea is to get it is to get the completion of that document of the open source AI definition
needs to have something that resembles that can help that can help the license committee
or the AI committee that will be formed.
Some committee inside the open source initiative to evaluate the legal documents that are coming
together with an AI system.
So that an AI system can be judged whether it's open source or not.
Whether it grants the four freedoms that it's supposed to grant.
That is the checklist basically.
Yes.
Daniel.
The question about the getting the discussion people from the global south and not just
the United States and Europe.
Absolutely.
It was one of the eye opening conversations I've had with one of the meetings we had last
year was in Africa, Ethiopia with the digital public goods alliance.
Members meeting, members summit, private event with the DPGA members.
It was really eye opening.
So we are absolutely open to that.
And more than happy.
Like one of the call for actions, one of the things where you can help is to put us in
touch with the people who can participate to these meetings.
And workshops.
So I'm happy to follow up with you, Daniel.
Yes.
Amanda.
Good idea.
Yes.
We'll publish the agenda as we go forward.
Ian or John, I don't know how to pronounce your name.
Probably so.
That's one of the things that we need to understand.
What kind of so access to training data is probably unavoidable.
The question is what kind of access?
What level of access?
The full on training data set?
Or is it sufficient to have a detailed description of what went into it?
Or something else?
That's what we absolutely that's probably one of the most important, most difficult
questions to ask.
And most delicate conversation also.
That's why we need to look at the individual specific.
We try to have this conversation in generic terms.
And having the conversation in generic terms ended up generating a lot of yes, but.
Or yeah, but in this case, maybe if.
You know, lots of uncertainties.
We need to be specific.
Let's look at specifically what's happening individually with PTA, with Lama 2, with FIDO,
with one of these with OpenCV components, like OpenCV algorithms.
Let's have a look at specifically what these need.
And then we generalize.
SBOMS with yeah, of course, like again, with the expert, with someone who has been modifying
Lama 2.
For example, this is one of the questions I asked one of the one of the friend of mine
who's been working with and modifying Lama 2.
Let's have a chat.
What do you what do you actually need in order to modify the behavior of the Lama 2?
For example, that's the exercise we need to do.
Responsible data.
Okay.
Amanda, can you send me?
Yeah, I'll save that.
And I will if you have people who you know who will be I'd be happy to talk to them.
I see other people typing.
Did I answer your question?
Okay.
Thank you.
Yes, links to slides.
I got to publish them.
So the next steps I mentioned, one is to we're going to be creating these these these forums,
public forums where we can we can have conversations more more openly.
And let me pull it back.
And and run the exercise.
I have scheduled meetings next week.
As we as we get more as we run these exercises, analyzing PTA and analyzing Lama 2, building
that list of elements of components and getting through the the the analysis of the legal
frameworks and and and their legal things like let me get back to the slide where it
shows.
Yeah, this is the exercise that we need to do.
This one.
We need to go through this pipeline as quickly as possible.
And once it's completed, we'll have version five, draft five.
And from then on, we'll keep on iterating with with more online meetings and we'll try
to be more more visible, more transparent from now on.
Everything will be public.
And if you follow us on Mastodon and and on LinkedIn, you get the updates.
But as soon as hopefully end of next week, we'll have the public forum, if not the beginning
of the week after.
By the end of the month, for sure, we'll have the public forums that you can sign up and
have discussions and conversations and get updates.
All right.
Are there any more questions or doubts?
Yes, we should.
We should be studying also applications not based on machine learning or deep learning.
Yes, Jean Pierre.
You have any specific suggestions, recommendations for one example that we or two examples that
we we need to look at?
Claire, the best link is open source.org/deepdive.
But that page is in the process of being updated.
Diane, yes, ML Commons is looped in with this initiative and as is the Linux Foundation,
Linux Foundation groups.
That's another thing that we should be we could be doing is to publish all the organizations
that have been participating so far, following the development so far.
I offer.
Okay.
I think we can also do voice.
Voice questions.
If anyone has.
Yeah, we'll share it as a PDF, don't worry about it.
All right, folks, if there are no more questions, I'm gonna close the recording and
we'll make available the recording and a slide deck.
And I'm gonna be available again in two weeks, similar content.
We're gonna alternate the times so that instead of being in the afternoons in
Europe time, we're gonna be in the morning in Europe time.
So we're gonna try to follow to get the Asia Pacific
audience to follow, an opportunity to follow.
So thanks everyone, enjoy your weekend.