to start the recording. Thank you. Yes. So welcome everyone to our biweekly town hall
for the open source AI definition process. And you can hear I've got a little bit of
a sore throat, but I'll hopefully be able to make it through. I will start. So these
are our community agreements that we have at every meeting. Some of you may have already
seen these. One mic, one speaker is about non-interrupting. Also when we get to the
Q&A, if you have multiple questions, please ask your question and then pause and let at
least one other person ask their own question before you ask a second question. Take space,
make space is a similar spirit. You know, just to invite others to share space with
us. And that some feel more shy and some feel more extroverted and everyone's voice matters.
Kindness is just that the work is hard, but we don't have to be. And just to remind ourselves
to be gentle and curious with each other, even when we disagree. Forward motion means
focusing on what's possible and not letting obstacles prevent the process from moving
forward. Similarly, solution seeking, just this work is very complex and it's vulnerable
to suggest a solution, but that is how we move forward. And anything else that people
would like to add to our community agreements for this meeting? You can say it in the chat
if you want. Okay. I'll continue. So yes, we are creating an open source AI definition
this year. And the current version is still 0.0.8. That's been the case for about a month.
And these are the pieces of it. Maybe Nick could drop the link to the HackMD page into
the chat because this is very hard to read. It just shows you the parts kind of as a map.
So we have a preamble. We have the four freedoms, studies, modify, and share as applied to AI.
And then we have the it's not circled, but we have preferred form for data information,
code and model. There's some description there. And then the current version also has a legal
thank you, Nick, has a legal checklist of what the licenses would be on the specific
components that would be required in those three categories of data information, code
and model. And what we're working on is versions. Yes. And we're open to comments. That's right.
And you can actually comment on that document. HackMD is a commenting platform. So what we're
working on right now is 0.0.9. And there will be some changes, a few changes. So in the
preamble, we are clarifying that recipients of the freedoms are developers, players, and
end users. So those freedoms of study, use, modification, and sharing. We are crediting
the Free Software Foundation for initially developing these four freedoms because crediting
people is a good thing to do. And so we're adding that in. And you can see in this larger
box how those freedoms are enumerated or described. The language should not be surprising to anyone.
And we did develop these four freedoms in a series of co-design workshops at the end
of last year. Also in the four freedoms, we are going to, in 0.0.9, underline that the
components must be free from encumbrance. That prevents any of those three user types,
developer, deployer, or end user from exercising the freedoms. So just underlining that, yes,
the four freedoms must be respected. And also if you're a little confused, you're not seeing
0.0.9 in these images. You're seeing 0.0.8. But I'm just indicating where the changes
will be. Also in preferred form, we are going to add
definitions which will be just a phrase, not a sentence, for the terms OSD compliant, which
is a requirement of data information, and OSD conformant, which is a requirement of
model parameters so that the legal requirements are clear. And the code components just need
to be licensed under an OSI approved license. So that's very straightforward. The code or
software can exist under those licenses. And the licensing and legal requirements are slightly
different for those other types of components. And so we're going to define what these terms
mean, compliant and conformant, the next version. And then, oh, someone unmuted themselves.
Please just stand by until the Q&A. If you have a question that you'd like to ask before
the Q&A, you can drop it in the chat. Okay. So the checklist. The checklist, we are in
the next version going to actually move it into a separate document. We realized that
in trying to create the definition and also to operationalize the definition in the same
process was a bit like jogging and juggling at the same time. And so we thought, let's
just focus on the definition. Let's basically the definition will stop at preferred form.
And then obviously operationalization of the definition is quite important. And that is
the checklist. And we're just going to separate those documents and also those processes.
One change that you will see in the checklist in version 9, and I guess we'll figure out
how to label the versions of these documents as well. But if you're not, we will figure
that out. It will be updated so that all the components are from the model openness framework.
So right now, if you look on the left, the data information components are coming from
the EU AI Act. So training methodologies and techniques, training, data scope and characteristics,
training data providence, etc. Those are not coming from the model openness framework,
which is a list of components from the Linux Foundation. It's coming from the EU AI Act.
And we just because of all the great work that the Linux Foundation is doing to create
an online compendium of AI systems and the openness of their components, we really want
to be able to rely on that for our own definition. And so we are going to use their component
list exclusively in our in our checklist. And I'll just read Stefano's comment, the
data information piece is going to look the same in 0.0.9. Oh, not because it's decided,
but because the topic is still being discussed. Okay, got it. So okay, so we're not yet. So
eventually, we will be transitioning over to model openness framework components. That's
not happening in 0.0.9. Thank you for the clarification. Okay, system validation. It's
pretty much the same as last time. So thank you to Arctic and LLM 360 for helping to identify
documentation, we found that it's really crucial to have creators help out with identifying
the legal documents describing the rights and permissions associated with the components
of their systems. So this screenshot of the progress and validation based on the process
of the review, which is being done by volunteers. And also the the results of that review so
far have not have not changed since last time. And yeah, we just find that we do need creators
to help provide documentation in order to to know whether a system would meet the requirements
of the open source AI definition. And Stefano's typing. I'll just wait for that if it's on
validation. Okay, pause. I'll read I'll read the comments if it comes up. Okay, so what's
next June, which we're almost at the end of through October, we do we want to obviously
complete the validation phase resolve comments and release versions 0.7.9. And then cut the
release candidate with sufficient endorsement, organizational endorsement. Okay, just keep
going. And this is our timeline, we had to update our timeline, because it ended at June,
I believe. And now we have to think through to the end of the project in October. So we
will be at hospitals for good in New York, both the UN event and the side event. We will
this is in July, I'll be doing a virtual event for sustain Africa. And this is to share the
OSAID and also to get further feedback. Let me pause and read what Stefano is writing.
The 0.0.9 draft includes a lot of small changes accumulated over two months since the release
of the previous draft, but all the pieces of 0.0.9 can still change based on community
feedback. Okay, that makes sense. Okay, so August, we'll be in Hong Kong for AI dev. And
September. Gosh, let's see if I can pronounce this correctly with my cold. Merdeala. Okay,
that's pretty good. And Buenos Aires. And then October, we will be launching the stable
version of the definition at all things open in Raleigh in the US. And then we will also
be doing a data workshop in Europe, in a city TBD. And the focus of that workshop, it will
be to write a policy paper to try to resolve some of these challenges with the sharing
of data sets. Yeah. Yeah. And as Stefano is saying, nothing is set in stone yet. Okay.
So yes, and actually, you've actually already seen most of these. Yep. The different events
that we're going to and when they are. So how to participate in this process. We do
share updates on the process and opportunities for volunteering also discuss issues of you
know, disagreement and difference of opinion on the public forum, which is discussed on
open source.org, which you can join for free, you do have to sign up just to prevent spam.
And then we have these bi weekly town halls, both for the this is one for the Europe, North
America and our Americas time zone. And then we have a second one. That is Europe, Africa
and Asia. So we cycle back between those two times. And then yes, if you would like to
volunteer a validation, particularly I think about volunteering we need at this point is
if you are the creator of a an AI system and would like to, you know, show that it is open
according to the definition that we have now, that that would be the most valuable type
of volunteer just because those are those are the those individuals that have this documentation
information most at hand. Yes, there's also a blog that we update and I can share that
and their summaries are shared every Monday on the blog. And yes, we highly recommend
the weekly summaries. So yeah, we will now do a Q&A. And what you can do is, I think,
raise, raise your hand and you can come off mute or you can just ask in the chat and I'll
read it like I've been doing throughout the meeting up to you. Love to hear your thoughts.
And for all those who who are not as familiar with our organization, Stefano, whose shots
I was reading is the executive director of the OSI. So if anyone was wondering why, why
is she reading aloud all these comments from this one participant? That is why he can't
participate live today. But that's why I was reading his comments. So yeah, I will just
be shy for a bit. Yeah, don't be shy. Yeah, don't be shy. You can actually click on the
microphone and speak or you can just chat as well. It's OK. Yes. OK. Oh, you're welcome,
Stefano. Yeah, thank you so much for coming. OK, yeah, go ahead, Gerardo, you can unmute
yourself. Hi. Yes. What's your question? I've been participating in several standard committees
on IEEE about the ethical use of AI and several AI definitions, and I'm finding that most
of the people I met there have not yet, do not yet know about this initiative and I'm
changing that. But I've been wondering if we don't need to push this discussion a little
bit forward with the scientific community, especially with certain researchers that are
dealing with this on several bases. I think I've covered most of the AI ethics discussions
that are occurring, but it seems to me there's more going on that probably we should be a
part of. OK, yeah, I may not be the person to respond to that. My primary role is or
my role is running the co-design process of the definition itself within OSI. But Stefano's
typing, but that sounds very, does sound very useful. And thank you for bringing those experiences
you had in other organization and standards making processes here. That's very, very helpful
to us. Gerardo, so we're working with several researchers and several organizations as well
and we would love if you have contacts with other researchers with whom we could work
with, that would be splendid. I just would like to highlight something because you mentioned
ethics, right? So even though, yes, ethics is really important for us, we want to see
open source AI being used for good, right? For the benefit of humanity. But ethics, as
the open source AI definition is concerned, is out of scope. It doesn't mean it doesn't
matter. It does matter that open source AI is used for the good, but it's just something
out of scope. I'm not sure if that clarifies your question.
Well, it's more on the way that for most of the discussions we are having, some of them
are about the age of tools and so on. There is a need for those groups to know a little
bit of the strains that we want to impose on these AI models to be labeled open source.
Because it's something, when you're talking about the ethics of using AI, that also brings
in the fact that the open source approach is more ethical in the terms of the way things
are constructed, in terms of the transparency, the sharing of knowledge. And one of the concerns
most of all of these groups are in is the issue of explainability. And probably that's
something else, but probably something that we should be addressing. The explainability
becomes easier when something is really transparent and clear and open source, more or less forces
you into this. And so it's more the other way around. It's not that this issue depends
on them. It's more that they, that's my part, they have to be aware of all of this.
That's a very good point. In fact, we are in touch with a few researchers around explainable
AI. And it's really, really interesting. So happy to connect with you. Thank you.
Thank you. Thank you. Does anyone else have a different question? Thank you, Gerardo and
Rick.
Hello, Anastasia. So I see a comment about how the data information piece is going to
stay the same in 0.9. Is that talking about how you're not going to change how you address
the topic of data and the availability of information about the data? And I guess I'm
curious about the general thinking since open data may not always be realistic, but it is
this potentially important piece. So I'm curious about the focus or lack of focus on open data.
I guess just in general.
Yeah, I would actually, Stefano, if you want to chat or come off mute, I would love for
you to answer that since it seems like you I mean, Stefano is is the leader on that particular
element of this. If he is on the chat. He is. Oh, but he is not. I see his. So I'm I
in the absence of Stefano, who made a correction on something in my slide. So obviously he
has information I don't. I actually can't give anything other than what he just said.
So there's two pieces of information shared. One one is that data information will not
change from output. Oh, Stefano is coming back on. Stefano, we were wondering if you
could answer. OK, I would still just love for you to answer Anastasia's question.
Did you want her to ask again? Did you hear it? OK, I know all he knows. OK, so then I'll
just continue. So there's two pieces of information shared once that data information will not
change from 0.0.8, the link to which Nick shared and also that the checklist will conform
to the MOF. So the way that I take that to mean. Is that.
Stefano, do you want to do you want to speak? I don't know if you're maybe you're not
know that you can speak. OK, it won't change only because the discussion is not complete.
OK, OK, OK, can't speak. OK, yes. So there will be there will be a shift to the components
coming from the model openness framework or MOF. And there may be I guess there may be
other changes as well, because Stefano is saying the discussion is not complete.
So maybe I can, Ximing, mirror. So there has been a lot of discussions around the data
information and I'll share a blog post as well that Stef wrote, which is very interesting
and also point a discussion topic that we have here. This is something that we're receiving
a lot of feedback and hearing the working group members also participated in those discussions
and to try to understand the role of data and data information. And this is actually
a crucial point of the open source CI definition. So let me just drop some links here and we
look forward to hearing more feedback on the discussion forum.
OK, thank you. And Stefano has just written, we may even remove the text altogether and
put a placeholder instead. And thank you, Nick, for that explainer link to the explainer
post on data information. I I'm sorry if that wasn't satisfying, Anastasia. That is that
is the level of response that I think we can give to you right now. But thank you for asking
the question. Does anyone else have a question? Yes, Gerardo, go ahead.
Just one more probably comes from the model we are working with, but I have an issue with
defining codes that trains and codes that trains a model and code that uses a model
of the same thing. And I think we should be splitting those and make it so that it's more
explicit to say that both parts are to be open source, first of all, because they are
probably not the same thing and and that most of the "open" AI things usually have that
second part of the code open and open source, the thing that uses the model to generate
stuff. But they keep close the code that was used to generate the model. And I think it
may be important to split and make it explicit that both parts are considered codes and they
are and they have to be open license and open source for the whole thing to be open source.
And something I haven't yet seen and why it's defined here as just one thing, but usually
it can become those two codes can be developed separately by different people on different
teams. And there could be, let us say, the temptation to license to open license one
and not the other.
Okay, so regarding the three kind of categories of AI systems, we have data information, code
and model, we are basically trying to have as few categories as possible that were still
descriptive of the different types. And obviously, there were other types of categorization we
could have used. That one seems pretty solid. In terms of the types of code, we are using
this maybe, maybe you're aware of this, and maybe not. This list of types of code components
or artifacts used to create AI systems, or used in AI systems from this model openness
framework that was developed by a group of researchers and practitioners at and affiliated
with the Linux Foundation. And we so as not to invent the wheel, because there's so much
that we are doing ourselves, we said, How can we rely on the brilliance of others. And
so we are using those code components. So we are we are not going to, I believe, change
those components as listed in this document. And maybe Nick could even share a link to
that it's a white paper is where those components live. Now, I think the Linux Foundation is
also spinning up some websites and landing pages. But as of now, I know that they that
you can find those in the white paper. So we are we're, we will just rely on that work
that they've done. Let's maybe take one more question. And then Yeah, you're welcome to
order. And then we'll call it a day. And Stefan, I was just saying we all care about open data.
And we're very concerned about the issue of accessing data suitable to train an AI, which
is true. Yep, absolutely. So, um, okay. Any, any other question from someone? I would say
another question from someone who hasn't asked one yet. And I'll just keep reading what Stefan
was saying, because he would be presenting with me if he were available. So he's saying
we're also planning a conference specifically on this topic, which is that event in October,
in in Europe in the city TBD is that comments or workshop on data, the issue of data and
AI, which is such a substantial one. Um, okay, I'm not seeing any questions. Thank you. Thank
you to everyone who came and who did ask a question that was really useful. Yeah, thank
you, Gerardo. Thumbs up. Yeah, so I think we can turn off the recording. And thank you
everyone for coming and have a have a wonderful weekend and do find us