The open source AI definition came out at the end of August with a new version
009. This is made of three main elements. It defines machine learning, open source
AI. The preferred form for making modifications is tied to the concepts of
machine learning. Because this is the technology that
requires a little bit more thinking because it has
this concept of trained models, trained weights and parameters. So the
weights are defined as the model weights and parameters made available under
open source initiative approved terms. And then there are
examples. Here what's important is the fact that we're trying to be vague
enough but signal precisely the intention. So the vagueness is because
we want to make sure that the text can resist time. It doesn't have to be updated
every time a new technology, a new model architecture, a new AI technology or
technique gets pushed out and made available. But also we want to use
the text so that the intention of the drafters is clear. The examples
provided are just part of the definition and they need to be
read together to understand it, to evaluate whether that signal, that
signaling of intention is clear enough. That should be clear. So from the source
code requirements also, this is a space that we know a lot more about.
Like what is the source code and how to deal with all the licenses etc.
But what's important here is that the requirement to release the source code
used to train the system. So one needs to be able, one who releases software
needs to be able to understand, one who releases an AI system needs to share all
the instructions, details including all the software used for training,
for validation, for testing. It's very important because that's the part where
collaboration can happen and improvements can happen iteratively.
And data information from the data front, the text here hasn't changed yet.
Although it's still quite convoluted and complicated, it could be refined. We'll
talk about that later. It needs to deal with the fact that laws are
complicated. And so this, again, the intention here is to give whoever
receives the software enough of the code itself and the datasets or the
provenance of the data so that the science can continue. And then also
innovation can keep on happening, building on the shoulder of the giants
exactly like it happens with the open source software where you don't have to
reinvent the wheel. You can build on top of someone else's work. So when
we released the version 009 of the open source AI definition, we
also released text to explain why the data set is considered, the release of
the training dataset is considered a benefit and not a requirement. It's
because training data are covered by laws that limit the resharing of the
datasets because of privacy rules, but also copyright law and even other
legislations like indigenous knowledge is not protected with copyright, it's
protected by other rules. And we need to take that diversity of legislation into
account and we need to make a difference between open training data, public
training data, and private data. So all of these have to be covered in a
different way, have to be treated differently because they are
different. And so the other thing worth reminding everyone all the time is
that the OSI board has set some basic criteria to approve the open
source, the results of the co-design process. We presented these slides a
couple of weeks ago in China, but the board requires that the
definition is supported by a diverse type of stakeholder and by
diversity it's listed not only into interest groups like users, developers,
deployers, subject of AI, but also geographic distribution. So we don't
want to have only Europeans or North Americans or South Americans, etc. We're
making an effort to go around the world to disseminate this work
and gather approval around the world and this is thanks to a grant from the
Alfred P Sloan Foundation. The other requirement is that the definition needs
to provide real-life examples. So once approved we need to make sure that
we have systems that we can point at and say these are open
source AI. And right now comfortably we can say that the
complying systems are PTI, the set of models released by
Yale AI Institute and LLM 360 and TII also. So non-profit research
institutions who have released the large language models and similarly
powerful AI systems. And we need to be ready by the October board
meeting that will happen on October 27th in North Carolina. So let's go through
the relevant comments that we have received this past few days on the
forums. We had Alison Randall basically requesting to be more
explicit about the requirements. This is a fair request. The text
tends to, the text of the definition tends to be more vague, to leave some vague
words in there. Like I said before, the intention is to be vague enough but
signal clearly the intentions. So it's worth rereading the text to
make sure that those intentions are clear. And especially one of the
intentions that Alison points out is the requirement to be explicit about
allowing, adding requirements the same way that the open source definition, the
classic open source definition allows for some requirements that are considered
to be good. Like a requirement for copyleft, you know, the persistence of
propagating the rights to downstream users is something that needs to be
evaluated. Whether the text that exists today allows that or if the text is
too vague and doesn't allow for that propagation downstream.
Technically, also legally, we need to understand how that can happen but
that's a different story most likely. Also be explicit about the fact that if the
training is done on public data, so data that actually can be distributed, there
are no exclusive IP rights, no natural exclusive IP rights. Like content created
by humans are, they always will have, I mean most parts of the world will have
copyright or civil rights, due to in European continental and moral rights.
But that doesn't mean that, for example, temperatures of the ocean, that
kind of data, that information doesn't have any right naturally. So
we want to consider that. She also suggests renaming data as source data.
This is something that I'm personally skeptical about. I would love to see more
people leaving comments on the forum because there is no, I mean, so data
is not source. Source is the word that has been traditionally used to
signal the source code or the preferred form for making modification to the
software. It's also mentioned in the original open source definition as such
and data is not the source of the training, training the outputs like
the weights and parameters. So I'm less reluctant. I mean it's called
training data in literature. So anyway I'd love to hear more comments
about this on the forum. And speaking of that concept of source as data, an
interesting comment received by a person, Professor Leon, he's a professor at
Stanford University. He made a good comment on the document on the
text. He's saying that the data is basically the data set is the output of
the processing of the original data and he's arguing that it's a lot more
important to get access to all the scripts used to build the data set
rather than the data set itself because the data set is not very comprehensible
without the code. And it's an interesting comment because it
really gives you, changes the perception. The data set is more like a
binary of the original data. And the source code is actually the code used
to create those tokens. So a very interesting comment in there and one
that might require also some refining, fine-tuning of the text of the
definition. Then we have comments on, we have received comments on hardware
considerations from Mariana Taglio and Alison Randall. This is an area, hardware
is an area where the open source initiative and open source in general
has not considered because it's a completely different layer and
can be isolated. Even in AI I think it can be isolated. Adding
hardware considerations would make the whole specification, the whole definition
a lot more complicated and I'm not sure it's viable. But you know if you think it
is, this is your time to leave your comments on the forums on this topic.
To me getting detailed aspects like hardware specifications, the
carbon footprint and things like that is interesting from the social benefit
perspective. But I don't think it really helps with the concept of improving,
collaborating, innovate on the AI systems. It's a little
bit the considerations about ethical use. They're valuable but they need to be put
at a different level, like a legislation level for example. But your comments, I
mean please leave your comments in this part if you think they are part of
the, if they're important for studying, share, modify and distribute AI
systems. And finally just a couple of days ago Carsten Wade made this proposal
to map visually the rights to distribute data set. I think it's an interesting
representation in a quadrant type of way where if you're
building on data, I mean he has this quadrant with two axes. One is on the
vertical axe, you have the IP intellectual property rights, present or
absent. And then if you want to have an integrity of the
pipeline stack, just another axis. So if you're
training something on public data, then basically anyone have high integrity
then you must release everything including the
original data set because basically why shouldn't you? Since there are no, I mean
since you should have all the IP rights. But if you're training on
private data then it's open source AI minus the data, D minus.
I think it's an interesting visual on this. Or if you don't have
the, if you choose not to release the data then it's
definitely going to be a closed, not open source AI. So let's talk about what's
next and that is we're going to be reviewing the text,
close some of the comments, most of the comments and release a release
candidate, have a release candidate version by probably in the next, within a
couple of weeks. So if you have more comments, please do it as soon as
possible. Although there will still be time to change after the release
candidate. And then if you're ready to endorse the open source AI definition, we
are looking for individuals and organizations who can endorse it and
that means that your name or your organization affiliation will be
appended to the press release and the announcement page of the open source AI
definition. So if you want to be part of this release, please email me or Mer,
the email address is on the deck. And just to give a timeline, we are
in September now, we gave a few talks around the world. We are going to
Buenos Aires next week, we Ashland in Oregon this weekend, we've been in
Daba and Bangalore to present this definition and we're going to
be holding more town halls every week until basically until the end of
October for the official launch in North Carolina at All Things Open.
We're going to be holding a special data workshop on data
in Paris also in October thanks to the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation grant.
Alright, so the way to participate is to endorse, so you can email me or
Stefano or Mer and you can keep on commenting on the forum. And with that,
time for Q&A. So take the floor as you want, open your mic or type
questions if you prefer.
I can see Ted comment saying not sure why hardware is needed.
Yeah, go ahead Ted. Yes, Stefano, thank you for sharing, this is really helpful.
Two questions, one is can you share the slides that we can distribute to many
people who cannot attend this town hall? Yes, so the session is recorded, I'm
going to cut the part without the audio and we're going to be sharing the deck, yes.
Okay, so you will share through email? Yeah, all of them are
shared on the forum, so I will put the link on where we're going to be
putting it so you can subscribe and get that one. But yeah, I can send it to you via email.
Okay, and secondly that endorsement, so it's just an email, is there any
template or just a simple email that endorses the RC1 unstable version?
Just an email saying, hey, I'm interested, my organization is
interested in endorsing this and we're going to be putting you in the
loop, so every release candidate will make sure that you have it and
once we get closer to the press release time, we will ask you formally, this
is probably going to be at the beginning of October, for a quote. Okay, can I
suggest that we put a link on the relevant website, so that I
can propagate or send to whoever is interested in endorsing it.
Just one click, one click link, so whatever individual or
organizations, we can hit on the quick list of names or organizations and
that would be it, instead of just a separate email.
Oh no, absolutely, yes, we're thinking about also creating a landing page with
the text and the button below that says, yes, I endorse it, name and
affiliation. Yeah, okay, all right, that'd be great, thank you, I have no more
questions. Thank you. Anyone else, any doubts, ideas?
Overall, it looks good to you?
All right then, oh, Jay, is someone typing?
All right, if there are no more questions, I mean, if you have more questions, you
can always email me or ask directly on the forum, really feel free to use all
the resources we have. I want to thank everyone and