All right, everyone, welcome to this, I don't know how many we've done of this already,
public town hall to get an update on the process to define open source AI.
As you all know, this is a long and hard process.
The agreements that we have in here, I like to remind everyone, and especially I'm fond
of the fact that we're moving forward.
We must be keep going and we must reach a conclusion.
And if we find something that is blocking the conversation, we take notes, we try to
move on, we'll get back to it later.
And we want to find a solution which is really relevant for delivering something on time
and reaching agreements.
This is what we set for our objective, and I'd like to remind this.
We want to get to a workable, usable, agreed upon definition of open source AI.
This is absolutely the goal and objective.
And I got to say that I'm getting more comfortable that we're reaching a conclusion.
And in fact, in...
Okay, got a wrong slide here.
Okay.
And my system is really slow.
So here's the status on the structure of the definition, which many of you have already
seen.
It's made of a definition of AI system at the beginning, the preamble where we set the
rules, we set the principles, actually, the principles that we want and why we want to
have a definition, what value and what advantages we think that's going to bring to the world
or to the ecosystem in general.
We also set clear out of scope, and so the boundaries of what's in scope for a definition,
what's left out.
And finally, the four freedoms, which are the basic understanding, the most succinct
way of communicating what is an open source AI.
And below that, we're going to be...
We're working on defining the legal terms, and we'll talk about the draft six, which
was released at the beginning of the month.
And I think it is going to give us a clear understanding.
So what I want to say here is that it looks like very few comments are coming in on the
top parts of the document, like the draft, preamble, out of scope, AI system definition,
and for freedom seem to be fairly set, especially the first three.
The fourth, maybe some small details, but it looks like these parts of the document
look done.
I really encourage you all to reread also the top part.
Don't get fixated on what's working on.
The more...
I'd love to get a sense of what's happening, and if really we can consider the top parts
complete, and if they're going to be...
So that we avoid having surprises at the last minute.
Now on the legal check terms, I mean, legal terms, the checklist, let's talk about what's
in draft six, which is very, very new.
The four freedoms haven't been changed at all.
What's added in draft zero six is the statement of the precondition.
What is that you need to exercise the freedom?
What is the fact, the statement that you need access to the preferred form to make modifications
to the system?
This is a sentence that is quite well understood in the realm of software.
We know because of practice, because it's been defined in various licenses, that access
to the preferred form to make modifications to a program, software program, you need to
have access not only to the source code, but also documentation on how to rebuild it, and
the tools and scripts to build.
So you need to have the compilation, for example, the make files and other pieces.
The GPLD3, for example, has a very detailed list of what's necessary to make modifications
to the program.
Now for machine learning systems, and we focus on machine learning here because as an example
of what an AI system needs in order to have the preferred form to make modifications,
you need three things.
Well, three sets of things, three categories of things.
Let's start from the bottom.
On the model front, we need model parameters, including the weights.
And maybe in some cases, we may need checkpoints for the stages of training.
And that's for the model requirement.
Then there is software that we need.
And the software that we need is software used for pre-processing the data, the software
used for training, validation, testing, and supporting libraries for the execution, like
the tokenizers, the search code, if there are the hyperparameter search code, if there
is one.
Then we need to know how to run inference on it.
And we need to have the model architecture, which is also a piece of code, usually.
Now at the top, data, and I have highlighted it, is the sufficient detailed information
of how the system was trained.
So this is not access, being able to download the full dataset as it was used for training.
But it's enough information to understand what went, from the transparency perspective,
what went into building that dataset, how it's been trained, how it's been collected,
who collected it, the procedures for labeling, if there was any reinforcement training, human
feedback, non-human feedback, rags, what have you, all of the methodologies that went into
building that dataset.
So this is something that many people have highlighted as still an area of contention.
And I'm fully aware of the fact that data is the most controversial part of the open
source of AI in general, and open source AI specifically, even more, because there are
so many open questions.
Now this is one of the boulders that I have highlighted at the beginning.
We know that this is an issue, but we've been going around for over a year, and we can't
figure it out.
So let's move on.
Let's finish this investigation phase.
Let's get to a complete draft using these assumptions, that we don't need access to
the full dataset, and see what happens.
See what we end up with.
Once we go back, we can revisit this decision, if it really looks like we have reached a
wrong or counterintuitive or counterproductive, or maybe it's decent and good enough that
we can work with it.
Now the data transparency requirements, this is something that we will need to elaborate
on in this new phase.
But let's see, because the wording that I've used in this draft are mostly taken from the
draft of the EU, European Union's AI Act, which, and these requirements have been already
criticized for not being clear enough, or not being extensive enough.
So I'm going to be on the data front.
We are going to be working closely with Creative Commons and Open Future, rather, to elaborate
a little bit more, to understand more the issue of data, and the issue of data governance,
as this is a sophisticated and complicated topic.
And all right, so phase two, which has started, is to look at the AI systems that we have
investigated in the phase one, which are Bloom, Lama2, Pythia, OpenCV.
And I'm open to add more, but the reason for this phase is to go through the list of required
components, the ones that in the draft 06 are required to exercise the four freedoms,
find them, find the preprocessing code for Lama2, preprocessing code for Pythia, training
and validation code for OpenCV, inference code, what do we use for inference on Bloom,
and find it, check the conditions under which they're made available, which I am not calling
them licenses, because in some cases, these are not copyright, especially model parameters.
It's not clear whether they're copyrighted or not.
So licenses for everything that is code, licenses for everything that there is documentation,
but we need to find all these resources and see how they are distributed, under which
legal frameworks and legal documentation, legal contracts or terms of use, what have
you.
We need to find them, we need to document them, because once we've completed this for
at least the four systems that I have highlighted, then we're going to go into looking at the
legal documents and write analysis, legal analysis on these.
So we're going to look at the Lama license, or the Lama terms of use, the Bloom rail frameworks
for distribution, use, etc. of Bloom, etc.
We're going to look at the Apache 2 license that is used by OpenCV, if I remember correctly,
in some of the pieces of OpenCV, and see how the language of the Apache license matches
the intention and how compatible it is with the digital artifact, the model weights, the
model parameters, etc.
That will give us the...
Once we finish this, and I'm hoping, aiming to finish this towards the end of May, we
should have the complete, we should reach a complete, feature complete list of elements
for a knowledge, have enough knowledge to be able to say, "Okay, this is what we think
open source AI looks like."
It needs to come with these components, the components need to be made available with
these, need to give out these freedoms, they need to allow these things.
And most likely, it's going to be a checklist, very similar.
Well, we'll see what...
The principles are going to be very similar to what we have in the open source definition
now, most likely.
So those are the steps that we have in mind.
And in terms of timeline, I think that we are still on time.
I still think that we're going to be able to have a meeting in June.
We're still discussing at this point, we're getting a little bit too close to June to
have an in-person meeting, but I have started to think that we might have, in order to...
We might have a virtual meeting, but hold on, we're still...
There are a lot of opportunities, a lot of trips that we can take.
We may have, instead of a one big meeting, we may have multiple ones at different times
around the time of June, because there are so many events where we're really committed
to go to, and we're going to be meeting many of the stakeholders at these events in Paris,
at PyCon in Pittsburgh.
And there's a meeting in Africa also at the beginning of June.
So we might be able to distribute this stakeholder meeting and the issue of a release candidate
around the month of June, rather than one big event.
But in any case, October is still the release of version one, stable version, whatever we're
going to call it.
And we'll add all things open.
So keep that in mind.
And yeah, these are the dates that I mentioned we already have in mind, committed.
So we're thinking about this roadshow, once we have a release candidate feature complete
definition.
The idea is to go through to these events and show the other meetings in this, but these
are the main ones, the top ones with the organizers.
We're partnering with the organizers so that we can have maximum exposure and we can use
the feedback between June, late May to October.
And of course, you're more than welcome to continue to come online, like we're being
super transparent.
We have these working that are set up to do the analysis, the early drafts of the analysis,
and then publish them on the forums where we are hoping to get more comments and feed
into the machine.
So no one is really surprised at the end when the definition is announced.
Easy to use as forums powered by open source discourse.
So fun and also mobile friendly.
All right.
With that, I'm happy to get any questions if there is any.
And if not, we can continue the conversation online.
All right.