All right, folks, thanks for joining this town hall.
We meet every two weeks, try to keep up to date the community about the evolution of
the draft and summarizing the conversations that we've been having on the forums and in
conferences like the conference that I just presented at here in Paris, in Cologne, Paris,
in a hotel.
So hopefully the network gods support us to go through this recording.
Just the community agreement, remember that we're trying, the one that I'm really focused
on and love the most is the forward motion, the fact that we are trying to understand
where the problems are and if we don't find an immediate solution, still we've marked
the spot, we move around, we'll get back to it because we do have to find a solution.
We do have a tremendous amount of pressure from all over the place, from politicians,
policymakers and from the industry, from academia, from the nonprofit and civil society to provide
some sort of guidance of what open source AI really means since everyone is using this
term.
And reminding that this is our objective to have by the end of the year a workable definition,
something that is acceptable even though it may not be the most perfect test thing that
we can imagine because the world is moving very rapidly and things might change in the
future.
So we need to find ways to provide solid principles that maybe will not change but allow for some
parts to be adapted.
We'll talk about some of the topics that emerged last week.
So the current version of the definition is still draft 008 and this was released a little
bit over a month ago at this point and it's made of some parts and parts that have received
very little comments in the past months are the preamble which is the place where we define
what we're talking about which is we decided to adopt the definition of an AI system provided
by the Organization for Economic Collaboration and Development or ECD.
It seems to be a widely accepted definition so we're going to use that as a reference.
Maybe it's worth going back and remind people at this stage that the reason why we have
a definition of an AI system is because we needed to have an anchor for the conversation.
In the free software definition, the free software definition refers to the program
and everyone understands what the program is or at least there is a very small margin
for error or misinterpretations.
But when it comes to AI there are misinterpretations and that's why there is a definition and these
definitions are also stated in law like the AI Act mentions, defines an AI system in a
very similar way to the OECD text.
So that's what we have.
And then we have in the preamble the reason why we are working on and the reason why we
want the definition of open source AI which is a very short summary of the intention to
give users the same rights that they have in software, the same independence, control
of the technology to enable permissionless innovation and collaboration.
Now the concept of user is also not defined in the free software space and this is an
area that has received some comments.
We want to be explicit and I think I'm working on a draft 0.9 and that will specify, will
contain a suggestion for what the recipients of the rights should be.
And draft 0.09 will probably mention the fact that we want end users, so anyone who is interacting
with the system, putting input and receiving outputs and also developers and deployers
of AI systems needs to be able to enjoy those freedoms.
Now below this part have not received a lot of comments so they seem to be fairly stable
to me.
The one part that is new in draft 0.08 is the concept of preferred form to make modifications.
That is something that is described in the free software definition as access to the
source code that is necessary for the actions of study the software and modify the software.
Now to study an AI system and to modify an AI system it's necessary to define what the
preferred form to make modification is and that's where there is a new section in 0.08
that says what the preferred form to make modification is.
I'll go into the details later.
And finally the bottom part is a legal checklist.
This is what I refer to as it's based on a paper from the Linux Foundation called the
Model Openness Framework.
You will see often referred to with the acronym MOF.
And this lists components of machine learning systems and in generic terms but they're defined
in the paper.
We use this as an ideal checklist that a future certifier or reviewer of AI systems might
use as a reference to say if this component is available under licenses or terms or legal
terms that allow the same grant, the same freedoms of the open source definition, the
original one, then if the required components are available under those acceptable conditions
then the AI system is an open source AI.
If not, most likely it's not.
Okay, so let's go a little bit into the details.
The key feedback that we have received is around what is required and what is optional.
So the pieces of optional components, I mean required
components are the biggest conversation is about data.
The original datasets are seen, some people have seen the training dataset into the optional
components and I believe they may have jumped to conclusions because the, well I'll talk
about it, but these are replaced with data information.
So let's skip through.
The other required components that I want to draw your attention on is the fact that
the data processing and like one of the components is actually required and data processing and
labeling techniques and all the disclosures about how the dataset has been built are part
of the draft.
And I'll go into more details later.
So there is a very lots of confusion around this part of the definition and we need to
spend a little bit more time to discuss.
Other minor requests are comments that we have received that are around the fact that
the legal requirements are described as available with terms like available under OSD, the original
open source definition, OSD compliant terms or OSD conformant terms.
Quick explanation of what this means.
The data information, I mean the concept here in data information like training methodologies,
et cetera, training, training scope, the data, the scope of the data, where the sources,
et cetera, are in documentation are probably going to be in the form of documentation.
The documentation uses different licenses and different agreements for sharing and distributing
for distribution.
However, the OSI has reviewed licenses that are not specifically targeting software.
So we don't have a way to say right now, we don't have a list of OSI approved licenses
for documentation.
So we know what they look like and they conform, they comply with the open source definition.
In other words, they allow for no discrimination of use, no discrimination of people, no field
of use, strict restrictions, ability of preferred form to make modification to the text, like
the source code of the documentation, et cetera.
So like you don't distribute a PDF encrypted as documentation.
That's not acceptable.
So that's what these words say.
And for the model parameters, we do talk about the OSD conformant.
So we use a different term because most likely model parameters don't fall.
Actually it's quite clear at this point, they don't fall into copyright law.
So using the word licenses and license approved, OSI approved, OSI compliant terms is not really
useful.
We need to be using a different framework and it's probably going to be more in the
contract law, at least that's what many of the lawyers that I talk to seem to think.
And that's, you know, OSD conformant means you still need to give us access to the, give
us the possibility to share, modify, give out free, without asking for permissions,
et cetera.
So it's a word that it will be more explicit in draft 09.
There will be a description in that lawyers can interpret more clearly.
So let's get into the concept of data information.
And maybe I need to take a little bit of a step back.
The intention of the definition is to provide in the upper part, so above the checklist,
what we call the checklist, in the upper part of the document, the stated intentions and
sort of a general, unmutable, general purpose reference point that can resist the test of
time.
That's why we have principles in the preamble.
The definition of open source AI is synthetic in the four freedoms.
The definition of preferred form to make modifications to a machine learning system is because machine
learning is the place where we have the challenges today of recognizing the new artifacts in
these AI, modern AI systems.
And so when we get into the preferred form to make modifications, we were looking for,
we were pushing the community to find a way to describe in generic terms, the intention.
And the intention is to have the possibility to recreate from scratch.
If I receive an AI system that I like and I wanted to give it to others, I need to be
able to have all the instructions and all the tools and all the data to recreate a substantially
equivalent system.
Because that's important.
That's one of the fundamental principles of open source has always been to be able to
have the instructions and be able to share those with others.
Now during the review process and during the co-design process, we asked volunteers to
evaluate existing systems and to rank the importance of some of the components.
And during that phase, a recommendation came out when they voted that many people voted
much higher the availability of the details about how the datasets were built rather than
the actual datasets.
So that gave us our suggestion that maybe it was worth testing the waters and understand
a little bit better what the issue around data is.
From the high level perspective, when approaching the problem, we realized, I mean, all of us
have had the same impression, data, the pipeline to build an AI system starts with data that
gets filtered, mangled, assembled, tokenized into a dataset.
The dataset gets fed into the training machine.
Training is an iterative process.
Data comes in at different stages.
All of this is complicated but should be described and made available.
And after the training is done, you get the parameters.
And with the parameters, you load them into an inference engine.
And that is what responds to, well, and you put an UI on top that gives you input and
outputs like think of chat GPT or other systems like that.
When you look from the distance at this whole pipeline, the intuition is that the whole
pipeline needs to be made available.
That whole pipeline is what you need to modify the preferred form to make modifications to
the system.
Now, when you start to zoom in, that's where the problem arises.
So when I started looking into one of these systems that in my mind were the two systems
that are the most open, the most freely licensed, freely made available, and that one is called
Pythia from the nonprofit called Eleuther AI.
The other one is from the research institute, ALEN AI Institute.
And Pythia has been trained on a dataset called the pile.
The pile is fully described.
There is that community working on it.
All the tools that have been used to assemble the pile, filter the pile, train Pythia using
the pile and all that, they're all released with open source licenses.
Now the pile has been an object of a takedown request for alleged copyright infringement
in the United States.
And since then, the original distributor of the pile has stopped distributing it.
Now you can still ask the Eleuther AI group to get the dataset, but the legal status of
the distribution of the pile is in jeopardy, or at least it's unclear in the United States.
But as discussions on the forum have revealed, the pile is perfectly legal in Japan.
And because it's distributed by a nonprofit and it's distributed for nonprofit uses,
maybe it's also legal in Europe, because Europe has reformed its copyright act a few years
ago and they have included an explicit exception for nonprofit text and data mining, which
is what the pile does.
So this raises a question, like what happens when you have...
Well, Dolma is in a similar situation.
Initially it was released with a license that doesn't obey, it's not compliant with the
open source definition.
It is imposing restrictions and permissions that needed to be asked to the island institute
before it could be used.
And then they changed the license.
So initially it would be not an open source dataset or an open dataset.
It has become an open dataset now with the change of license.
But upon looking at more closely, it contains probably the same issues that the pile has.
So someone could sue or request Dolma to be taken down for copyright infringement in the
United States.
So there are these legal issues around copyright, the fact that datasets can be open at a certain
point in time and not open at a later stage or vice versa.
And the legality of the distribution of this dataset may change over time and changes over
geographies.
So calling an open...
Anchoring the definition of open source AI to something that can change so quickly and
can change over time is challenging in many ways.
And there is another issue that is more technical.
There are ways to train systems without actually creating a dataset.
And one of these is called federated learning.
And in federated learning, each provider of datasets is more common.
It's common or, you know, yeah, it's common.
It's used with privacy preserving techniques.
If you have data that is owned by a different entity and they don't want to share it with
others, they don't want to create a pool for different reasons.
If they cannot create a pool because law, like privacy laws for medical records, for
example, doesn't allow hospitals to share data of their patients, then what they can
do is to set up training engines inside their own data centers.
And these training engines collaborate remotely in a privacy preserving way, training a model
without the data actually ever leaving their data centers.
So this technique creates models, parameters, but doesn't create datasets.
So when we were keeping this in mind, then we thought, OK, so this is a challenge and
we need to find another way to approach it.
And that's where we came up with the definition of data information.
Data information is, I didn't put this in the slides, but data information is described
in the draft, which I encourage everyone to look at.
The draft says that data information is, the intention here is to recreate an equivalent
system.
And the text says sufficiently detailed information about the data used to train the system.
So that, and this is the very important part, it's not just the information about this data
used to train the system, but the objective here needs to be taken into consideration
so that a skilled person can recreate a substantially equivalent system using the same or similar
data.
And this concept of the same or similar is important.
And I'll give you one example.
Let's say you have received a model that the original developer trained on Reddit.
This was an example brought up by Tom Callaway's bot from the AWS team, who doesn't agree with
the concept of data information.
And he said, what if someone trained on Reddit, but licensed the data from the Reddit corporations,
let's say for $100 million.
So you receive now, they have disclosed the data information, and they have given you
all the code, the source code used to train and run the system.
Now what about the, does that qualify, would that qualify as an open source AI?
Now, my answer to that, looking at the concept of data information, I want to be able, to
give an answer, I need to be able to know if I can build a substantially equivalent
system using the same or similar data.
So the same data would require me to enter into $100 million agreement with Reddit corporation.
But if you think about it, while thinking about it, I know that a data set called Common
Crawl contains the Reddit data already, despite the fact that Reddit tries to remove, to have
Common Crawl remove that data.
But that's a different story.
So Common Crawl has the Reddit data.
So before I can answer to the question, whether something trained on Reddit licensed data,
I need to extract, try to extract the Reddit data from Common Crawl, run the training.
If the model that I find, that I obtained at the end of the training, using the same
code from the people who have given it to me initially, if I get something that behaves
the same way, then I would say it's an open source AI.
If the original training data set from Reddit contains some really special source that makes
it impossible to replicate, then it would not be an open source AI.
And so I leave it at that.
I want to make clear that the intention at this stage of the definition, the preferred
form to make modifications to the system, is written in generic terms to accommodate
the fact that sometimes data sets don't exist and sometimes data sets cannot be distributed
or they can be distributed, but only in some geographies and only at different times.
So it's been written by lawyers and you can recognize in there some concepts like the
concept of the word skilled person, which is a term of art.
And it's meant to be a generic application of the principles of open source.
Now we have received also on the forums there have been proposals from Giulio Ferraglioli
and Tom to use something like synthetic data instead.
It's a fascinating example, definitely, and synthetic data is data created from scratch
by large language models and other techniques.
But it's really an unproven technology.
It would be really detrimental, I think, to anchor a definition to some technology that
is unproven, that is expensive and may not work in all cases.
Also this doesn't leave...
Yeah, it's unproven and it may not scale.
So what if?
And the other position that we have read in one of the comments, I think also this was
coming from Giulio, is that the whole pipeline must be open source before something can be
considered an open source system.
And I push back a little bit on this because if the GNU project, when it started and even
today, contemplates the option of running open source and free software, however you
want to call it, it's the same thing, on top of Windows, for example.
You can run...
You can...
The concept of free software that depends on proprietary libraries because they're part
of the system.
So the whole concept of complete, pure open source components in a system is not something
that exists in nature.
We have...
We, the communities around the world, have always accepted compromises when that led
to having more openness.
And I really want to have this clear and taken into consideration when we get into this debate.
And so these are the most important points.
There are other considerations that we have received.
I think, if we don't strictly require datasets, what are the incentives for other corporations
to reveal their...
To share, to create more open, more common datasets?
That is a very good question.
And in fact, I think that given the status of the legal status of policies around the
world that make the pile or dolma complicated to share is the reason why at the OSI, together
with Creative Commons, together with Open Future, we want to have a separate conversation
about the issue of data datasets and policies around that.
And we're working on a conference this year, sometime in October, to get this conversation
started because it's a very complex one.
We do recognize that there is an issue with creating datasets and sharing them.
And we wanted...
But we don't have right now clarity about how to fix this issue, how to create incentives,
how to create concepts like copyleft inside between data and training and models.
So that, for example, aggregators of large datasets who want to do the right thing, they
want to create more open models, they want to share their data in a way that preserves
the possibility for society to have access to models that can be controlled and shared
by larger groups, not just single vendors.
We don't know what the mechanisms are because copyright, which has helped us create copyleft,
does not help us cross the boundary between what is data and what is the trained model.
We need to think about contract laws, maybe, and maybe even policies like new law that
help us tie data to train models.
It's a complex topic, and that's why I think we're having such a tremendous amount of discussions
over two years of the investigations and then later the co-design process around the open
source AI definition.
All the hardest conversations have been around this concept of what about the data?
And I think we need to...
We really need to come to the conclusion that this is a very complex topic and that needs
to be...
The data issue needs to be taken in a separate trial.
And the other thing that I want to say is that the concept of data information, if you
read the definition and start from the end, start from the end, what is the intention?
The intention is to recreate a substantially equivalent system, whether you are using the
same data, exact data, because it's available, or whether you're using similar data because
one way or another you find it, but you end up with the same model, same behavior, then
that should be enough in the definition.
And by the way, so let's look at what...
Let's move on.
Let's look at what we have done to validate this hypothesis because that's how we've been
operating.
Let's look at examples.
Let's see what's happening out there in the wild.
We validated...
We went through a few systems.
We asked people to...
A few, more than...
Now we are at 12.
So we're trying to look at what happens with these systems.
Some we know, they are not passing the bar, like Lama and Mistral and Falcon and Grok.
Where does the definition fail?
We find that it's hard to find the components, right?
With people who don't know about it.
So for example, if you look at Grok, Grok is one perfect example.
It was developed by XAI, the Elon Musk thing, and they just share the model weights very
freely and nothing else.
Now if you don't find the other components, is it because they don't exist, which is probably
most likely, or is it because you couldn't find it?
The other thing is it's hard to understand that licenses sometimes if you don't have...
I mean, the volunteers, they may have limited knowledge about the terms of use and terms
of distribution.
So some of these reviews have been incomplete.
But despite this, we ended up, I think that we get a very easy sense.
We know that Falcon is missing information about 3M technology.
Their licenses have been modified.
They're not really compliant with the open source definition.
Grok, we know it's opaque.
Lama, we know it fails because of a variety of reasons, like lack of transparency, but
also it's missing other...
The license is not compliant.
But we know Alma, for example, they've been doing the right thing, and we expect it to
be a positive, passing the bar of open source AI.
By the way, they also released the data set.
And the similar is for PTA.
They're fully transparent, and they released the data set.
You can ask for it, and you can get it also.
But the issue remains with legal uncertainties around the world.
The other, Bloom, we know that we have everything.
It's transparent, but it fails because the license it uses for many of its components
are imposing restrictions and things like that.
So the concept of data information seems to be behaving exactly as expected.
And it's showing also that there is a very strong correlation.
Granted, it's a small sample, but there is a strong correlation between requiring data
information and having access to the data set to caveat those legal issues.
So I think it's working, and I'm not convinced that the alternative proposals are positive,
because the alternative proposals put PTA and even Olmo outside of the approved licenses.
And that is really not an acceptable outcome.
We cannot go credibly to either commercial partners, academia, and policymakers and say,
"This is the open source AI definition," and not have an answer when they say, "Okay,
which one is open source AI?"
And we cannot point at any examples, or we can only point at small, trivial academic
experiments as examples.
It's not going to work.
And it's not going to work because the industry and policymakers are already being pushed
to look at Lama and Mistral, and they consider those open source.
So if we don't come up with a counterproposal quickly, we will have lost an opportunity
here.
So what's next?
I really hope that we resolve these comments and we resolve this conversation around the
concept of data information with a release in 0.9, which we get support from organizations
that understand the principles behind it and validate it.
We started to get some positive feedback this week at a conference in Paris from Lina Gora
and publicly announced support for this concept, and others are coming in.
And then between July and October, we're going to have a series of release candidates with
trying to get more endorsements.
So there are two ways for you to help.
One is to look, keep on searching for systems that seem to be complying with the definition
0.8 or not, like complete, go on with the validation phase.
And yeah, and this is the timeline, and these are the things that we are, the places where
we're going to be speaking next and presenting and discussing with the community.
And as usual, try to join the forums.
I know I may have said in the past, also give us feedback through social media channels.
If you do that, please tag us because the algorithms on LinkedIn, some people are still
using X, et cetera.
We miss comments.
We miss the discussions.
They're very hard to find, and instead, the forums are the perfect place.
And of course, join the town halls because it's a time when we can ask live Q&A.
And with that, I will stop the speaking and see if there are any questions.
Well, I see that there's been quite a jump on the written form.
Trying to summarize.
Is there, do you want to?
Yeah, I think you all have voice rights.
You should be able to speak.
Do I have a path on the open source AI definition where Facebook's llama goes green on the list?
Yeah.
They release all of their training information, training data, and we can rebuild something
similar like that.
Yeah.
Yeah, exactly.
I got to say, conversations with commercial operators, I think that they tell me that
the secret sauce is actually in the training techniques because they seem to, that's where
the secret goes.
It looks to me, they tell me that that's where their secrets are.
How they score high on the leaderboards for benchmarks is how they train, and they don't
want to share it.
But I spoke with, for example, Lina Gora, they have this project called OpenLLM360,
France OpenLLM360, something like that.
And they've been training a system from scratch and they are releasing all of their information
and data, et cetera, because they want to do the right thing and they want to [inaudible
00:10:50] a model that is optimized for the French language.
So that other, and then they want to generate that collaboration on top of that.
So Honey Sabak comments that if we think the definitions settles on the training data method
must be open as well, then we may end up with few or no open source AI models.
It's one of the risks.
But also I want to point out that there is a little bit more than that.
The reason why I want to move on with the conversation, because it's a highlight how
complicated this is and how different from software this is.
On software, when you modify, you get access to the source code, you modify it and you
have to rebuild before you can ship it again.
So the concept of modification and studying are like that.
You study, you see the source code and you modify, rebuild and ship it.
For AI, you don't do this.
You can study just for the purpose to see if there are bugs you don't need to rebuild
or if there are issues, biases, et cetera, to evaluate a model around AI.
But for modifications, you have multiple ways of achieving the same goal without having
to retrain, which really is a much more interesting question to me than the debate about data.
How do we treat models that are fully disclosed, share their datasets, share the techniques
for the training when that training is fine tuning on proprietary models?
And I'll say more, that fine tuning is so deep that every layer of the neural network
has been rewritten so deeply that none of the behaviors and the benchmarks from the
original model apply to the retrained, fine-tuned model.
That is a huge question that we need to find an answer for today.
And it's been raised on the forum with an example of an AI system developed by Mozilla
to write captions for descriptions of images in the PDF.js tool.
And they mixed two proprietary models.
One is an object detection vision, computer vision model, and one is GPT-2.
It's a large language model.
We don't know anything about the training.
They have biases, etc.
Mozilla has fine-tuned these models, assembled them together to achieve a new system, a new
behavior.
It's that open source.
And they have released everything that they have done in a very reproducible fashion.
So what are we going to call this?
Is this open source AI built on top of non-open models?
Yes.
Interesting question.
Okay.
So, let's go back to the slides.
So, I'm going to show you a few slides.
And I'm going to show you a few examples.
So, let's go back to the slides.
So, this is the first slide.
And this is the second slide.
And this is the third slide.
And this is the fourth slide.
And this is the fifth slide.
And this is the sixth slide.
And this is the seventh slide.
And this is the eighth slide.
And this is the ninth slide.
And this is the tenth slide.
And this is the twelfth slide.
And this is the eighth slide.
And this is the ninth slide.
And this is the twelfth slide.
And this is the tenth slide.
And this is the eleventh slide.
And this is the twelfth slide.
And this is the thirteenth slide.
And this is the fifteenth slide.
And this is the sixteenth slide.
And this is the seventeenth slide.
And this is the eighteenth slide.
And this is the twelfth slide.
And this is the seventeenth slide.
And this is the eighteenth slide.
And this is the twelfth slide.
And this is the seventeenth slide.
And this is the eighteenth slide.
And this is the twelfth slide.