Let's start recording our session and get started.
Welcome, everyone.
This is our new format--
well, slightly new format in the sense
that we're going to be doing these town halls now weekly,
going into the session, going into the final stretch
before we have the open source AI definition reviewed
and approved by the board at the end of October.
At the board meeting that we have scheduled then.
So a quick reminder of our rules of engagement,
our community agreements that we call them.
This is our rules.
We want to have--
making sure that there are no overlaps
and people keep space for speaking and listening.
So take space if you are shy and tend not to speak.
But also, if you tend to speak a lot, take a break.
Consider others and ask questions.
Give space for others to come in and give their own things.
Be kind.
And the ones that I look always with in mind
is the think about the fact that we want to continue moving.
We can't stop discussing for too long.
We need to notice the places where
we have disagreement or difficult, complicated issues.
Maybe put a note in there and get back to this later.
And always look for solutions.
Listing the problems is OK to start the conversation,
but moving on.
And so let's review for-- this is the first time
we do this at this time of the week.
So you may have not seen the new version that
was released a couple of weeks ago, version 0.9.
We have presented it in--
I mean, we were in China with Mayor Joyce when this came out.
And basically, the principles haven't changed between 0.8
and 0.9.
The principles are that we want to have-- for an open source
AI, we want to have three kind of components
that can be grouped into three buckets.
The weights, the parameters, the architecture,
anything that is related to what we
call the model in machine learning
needs to be made available under--
needs to be made available.
We'll talk about the conditions for openness or availability.
The open-- the code used to train the system
needs to be made available also.
And also, you need to have a way to run the model,
run the AI system.
And then you need the data.
Everyone understands and agrees on the fact
that the data is where the parameters, the weights come
from.
And you need the data.
And the coalition, the group that
has discussed for many months how to solve the--
how to pass the big boulder of data
being many things in different legislations of the world
came with the description of the data, the requirement
the data has sufficiently detailed information
about the data used to train the system.
And that includes either the data set itself,
when it's possible and legally plausible to distribute safely,
or in alternative--
and also-- not in alternative, but also--
also the code with the full instructions
on how to replicate that data set.
And that includes the scripts to download the original data
and content, the code to run all the interesting--
all the interesting manipulation to go from the raw data
to the training data set.
And so the definition itself has the text
of what is required in a paragraph titled,
what is the preferred form to make modifications
for a machine learning system?
And describes the weights and gives some high level examples.
These are not-- this is not text that is strictly correct,
always--
always the-- always valid for every possible--
very strictly prescriptive about every possible system,
every possible kind of technology
that we can see today or available in the future.
These are examples that are useful to interpret
the actual meaning of the words above.
So for the model weights parameters,
that might include the checkpoints, for example,
if the training in the system is a large language model,
for example.
From the code perspective, it's the source code
used to train the system.
And this includes all the pre-processing code,
the training, the validation, the testing,
how it's been done, the supporting libraries,
and all of that code software.
And this, obviously, need to be made available
with open source AI approved licenses.
And for the data--
for the database, again, there is a-- this
is a little bit more worthy.
The intention here is that the open source AI,
the developers of open source AI,
must be sharing with others all the instructions
and all the knowledge that they have on how they built.
That's the intention.
The intention is to make sure that open source
AI carries the same meaning and the same practical values
that the open source software definition carries.
You need to be able to understand--
you need to be able to understand
how the system's been built, its intention, et cetera.
And you need to be able to learn from them,
from the original developers, and build on top of them
without having to reinvent the wheel or try to guess.
Maybe this thing has been done this way,
so I can improve it by doing this other thing.
No, it's building on top.
And this is where the--
building on top of what others have built,
one of the basic tenets of open source.
But we do have spent--
I mean, the community, and together with the--
also with the board.
And we have reviewed a lot of the comments
that we have received in the past.
And we have clarified also that we do have--
there is a-- we do have-- we do care about data.
We do care about the availability of the training
data.
We do know that the training data
is valuable to understand and study the AI systems.
And we also want to acknowledge that there
is different kind of data.
There is data that computers share,
and that would be--
make sense to always have open in terms of openly accessible
and as open data, following the definition of-- maintained
by the Open Knowledge Foundation.
But there is also training data that is simply public,
cannot be redistributed.
And that is basically the whole of the whole internet.
And where you have the right to crawl and build indexes on it.
This is one of the basic rights that Google
has had as a search engine for forever, since its existence.
And we need to continue to acknowledge the fact
that while search engines can crawl the internet,
they don't have the right to redistribute
what they have crawled.
But they have the right to offer the public
some new and transformative activity, actions,
and services.
So this is the same thing.
This is the concept of public training data
that is publicly available.
And then there is private data, which is another category
of data for which you may have the right to train on,
but you don't have the right to redistribute.
And so a reminder that we are working
within the constraints of the policies
that the board has set as criteria to have a definition.
The board wanted to have--
would ask us to work with the community
to understand, to have a definition that
is supported by a large coalition of individuals,
organizations, and groups with globally representative--
so a sample that is representative
of global communities, but also represent
various different interests.
We're not just representing the interest of research
and academia of individual developers,
or large corporations, small corporations,
European corporations, or governments
from other parts of the country.
But it's the whole--
we try to be as global and diverse as possible.
The other constraints that the board set for us
is that we need to provide real-life examples.
You can't really have a definition
that defines theoretical models, theoretical systems that
don't have any application in practice.
It would be not acceptable by the board.
And we also wanted to set a deadline,
because it's a hard deadline, because otherwise--
because the world needs this definition soon.
And it's better to have something
that is done rather than perfect.
So what's next?
In the next few months, we are working
to really solve the comments as they come,
and maybe release in the next weeks, couple of weeks,
release candidate version.
And then get a quick feedback with the top organizations,
groups that have worked in the process
to gain their endorsements, gather the last comments,
and march towards a stable version for all things
open on October 27.
So we are seeking now--
we're at the stage where we are seeking the comments
from individuals and organizational endorsements
for--
comments and endorsements for the draft.
So if you have--
if you're ready to say, yeah, we're
ready to endorse these principles,
just send us an email.
And you can email me or you can email Claire.
I've been assisting our project.
You can get in touch with Nick.
You can even go public on the forum already as you prefer.
We want to have--
we need to start moving.
We are already at the first week of September,
and we have only six weeks of time
basically left before we finish the process.
And yeah, we've covered a lot of space, a lot of time
over the months.
We've been traveling quite a bit.
We're trying to be presenting in many parts of the world,
presenting and discussing with the community
to make sure that there are the least amount of surprises
by the time we issue the version, version 1,
stable version in all things open.
I can also give you a preview.
You see here in October, there is--
we have two events scheduled.
One is the all things open launch,
but also there is a workshop that we're
organizing for around specifically about the issue
to discuss and understand better the space of data governance
distribution, et cetera.
We'll have more details this coming week made available.
And this is all thanks-- all the travel and all the--
and the workshop that we're organizing in Paris
is thanks to a grant, a large grant given to us
by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.
So how to participate?
You can definitely still email me or Mer,
the preferred for the endorsements.
You can also send public comments
on discuss.opensource.org.
Can definitely signal that you appreciate
the stewardship and the role of the Open Source
Initiative in driving this process
by becoming an OSI member.
You can also donate as you become a member.
And you can join these downloads that--
realize this slide needs to be updated.
Coming-- there's-- there being--
there being-- they're opening now weekly at alternating time.
One week is going to be at this time.
One other week is going to be at 9 AM Central European time
so that the Asian community can join.
And now-- yeah, now we've got time for Q&A.
So a comment from YouTube, an open AI
should prove that its training data is all legally licensed
open source data.
Right, so this is a very interesting question
because it's a frequently asked question, actually.
And so it's been debated for many months.
The short answer is that legally licensed open source data is--
is a-- is a big--
is a big-- is a different--
is a different set of what you think it might be.
And we may want to qualify.
So think about the fact that Google Books, for example,
has built a product built on legally--
legally acquired books, scanned, and done object character
recognition on it, and created a transformative work,
and was sued.
And then they won the lawsuit.
Makes me-- makes us think that the concept of training data
legally licensed open source data
is something that needs to be--
needs to be clarified.
So it's a gut reaction that we all go towards.
But we need to think about the consequences.
It's a big-- it's a big topic.
And that's why we're hosting that conference in Paris also.
So Joshua.
Hello.
This is Joshua.
So in the latest draft, I've been
spending most of my time really trying
to think through reading the definition
from different viewpoints of users, especially
a developer viewpoint.
And so I've been really digging in and thinking about
if I'm using Protobuf or TensorFlow
or these other common frameworks and formats for AI models, what
my world view looks like.
And one thing that really stands out to me
is that generally speaking, we're
gravitating towards these binary formats as what
we understand as the model.
And this is different than the abstract kind of approach
to thinking about what an AI model is in general.
It's, in a sense, broader than the AI model,
which is more narrow, which is counterintuitive.
You would think it would be just the opposite.
And the reason why it's somewhat broader
is because these binary formats allow
you to do a lot of things that go perhaps
beyond what you would normally think of as part of the AI
model.
But when you need to identify in your code base what
is the model, you point to that file.
That's the model.
And so I think that there's going
to be some gap between a lot of people's
intuitive understanding of what the model is
and what the intent of the model is by OS in this definition.
I think it would be helpful to put a little bit more
in the definition.
In the online feedback forum for the latest definition,
I added some comments specifically around this idea
that you should be encouraging you
to be explicit about saying that you should not
use the AI model as a way to pass through, say,
binary blobs or object code.
And the reason why I sort of came to that conclusion
is because I was looking at real examples
where people were using things like Protobuf and other--
in TensorFlow and using variables that just
store data effectively as part of their training.
So they're just storing verbatim blobs of information
that are then used as part of the program.
But it's that interaction, but it's stored in the model
from their perspective, from the user's perspective,
and in the documentation.
So I think it would be helpful to have a little bit more
nuance in the definition to clarify that a trained model is
not the same as merely storing files that can then be reused,
that it should be about a little bit more detail around that,
just to help abuse of the open source AI definition.
I think-- yeah.
So I'm not sure I understand exactly--
in fact, I was emailing you to have a conversation
to clarify what you actually meant.
And I'm glad you came for this and explained it via voice.
So I'm still a little bit puzzled
by the technical details here.
But the general principle of the definition
is that it must resist as much as possible the test of time.
And it needs to set high-level principles at this stage.
If you want to have a mental map to frame the intention here,
the open source AI definition file,
the way you see it linked in the chat,
is the page that the FSF, the Free Software Foundation,
hosts and calls what is free software.
It's the basic principles that we
want to have represented in a view of the world, what
needs to be achieved.
That page has gone through multiple iterations.
Like, if you go below and you read it,
the initial freedoms were three, and then a fourth was added.
And wording has been changed on that page to clarify.
But the principles, what is free software, those three,
and then letter four freedoms have pretty much
remained the same.
What has changed and has evolved and derived from that
is the open source definition, which
is a sort of a checklist to evaluate,
in practical forms, software packages used by--
in order to be included in the FTP servers at the Debian
project first, and then became the open source definition
that are currently used, those 10 principles,
to evaluate the licenses and legal documents.
We want-- we're trying to do the same thing here.
The open source AI definition is what is free software page.
And then the new split document, the checklist,
is more of those 10 points practical interpretation
of, in practice, of what will have
to happen for an AI system to be judged, evaluated,
to be respecting the original intention written
in the definition.
So what I would recommend is that we
spend a little bit more time, collectively,
to think about the interpretation.
Instead of making the first document longer,
we could be spending a little bit more time
to refine and review the-- and we
have more time with another set deadline
to finish the checklist.
Make that document a little bit more rich.
Bentley?
Yeah, I noticed this definition doesn't
mention content generated by models
under an open source license.
This might be much a bigger question,
but is there a plan to address the content generated
by an open source model, how that will be licensed,
or is that part of a much bigger discussion?
That's a good question.
So the jury's still out of what are the legal ramifications
for that part.
But definitely, the definition does not
touch that the same way that, more or less,
the open source software definition
doesn't say whether you can use a C compiler to build
malware or other things like that.
It's a separate-- it would be a separate conversation.
There might be legal documents that
say you cannot use this model, this AI system,
to create--
to infringe on someone else's copyright
or to invent things that have already been invented
or do other things.
But that's something that will have to be evaluated
by the legal community.
[AUDIO OUT]
- I have a question.
Can you hear me, Stefano?
- Yes.
- By way of introduction, I'm a tech attorney.
I've been practicing for 15 years.
And for better or for worse, I've
done a lot of work in the open source space.
The one question I had is, at the top of the call,
you went through the definition.
And you explained that there are three parts to the definition.
Is it fair to state that the first two
parts of that definition have not generated
any controversy versus the third?
- Yeah.
Well, not completely true.
So the first two parts, meaning the model weights
and parameters, and the second part--
- And the source code.
- --the source code of--
so there has been debate.
And there will continue to be a little bit.
In the legal community, I believe
that the legal nature of the weights parameters
is still being debated.
Some legislations may not consider those subject
to any exclusive right.
And whether they should be considered
under any IP law or other exclusive rights
is to be debated.
It's not ferocious debate, but it's an intellectually
stimulating one.
And on the code front, on the source code front,
there is debate over whether the training code should
be strictly required or not.
And there is a little bit of a push and pull.
I've heard rumors about that requirement,
strict requirement, as being a little bit too limiting.
Too limiting.
- Got it.
But just to clarify, the third component of the definition,
with respect to the training data,
is the most controversial.
Is that correct?
- Yeah.
Correct, yes.
Because, yes, instinctively, all of us,
at the beginning of the process, everyone had the same thought.
Data is where the weights come from.
Some people use the term source, which is confusing.
It's not source code in the same way.
But it's where it comes from.
If without the data, you don't have the models.
You don't have the parameters.
And therefore, given that requirement,
all of the pipe, the whole pipeline
needs to be open and open source.
But data is not source code.
It doesn't fall under the same easy, air quotes,
legal framework.
It's a whole different beast.
And realizing that became the big boulder
that we had to navigate around, find a way to navigate around.
- Got it.
Thank you.
That's very helpful, Stefano.
And I apologize.
I have read a bunch of the comments on the various versions.
But obviously, I don't have the full history here.
And nobody knows this stuff better than yourself.
Did OSI, at any point, consider using different words
to describe models that would fit within this definition
rather than open source as a way to resolve
the complaints from various members of the community?
Was that considered as an option?
- That is a very awesome question.
That is a very awesome question.
It was one of the very first questions,
is what we're going to call this thing.
And yeah, I'm on the left.
But yes, unfortunately, though, our hand
was forced by the fact that open source AI, as a term,
was already being used.
And even abused by some players.
And I can be public about it, because I've
been public about it.
Meta is one of the abusers of the term.
They keep on using, referring to open source AI.
So in order to safeguard open source, the term itself,
we don't have another choice but to call it open source AI
and work around it.
- Thank you.
That's very helpful context.
That's all I have.
- Yeah.
I see Joshua typing.
Are there any other questions from the Mozilla group or YouTube?
Josh, I see you typing.
Feel free to grab the mic.
- Thanks.
Yeah, it was just sort of a follow up.
My point is that, in principle, we
know that when training a model, that we
know that when training a model, that it gets trained on code
at times.
Some of the data is code.
Some of the data is object code.
We know this because GitHub and other things
are often used as the training data.
And we know that models sometimes make use of just
verbatim storage.
Instead of taking the data and trying to learn something
from it, sometimes you just save blobs of data in your model.
All major models, model formats, TensorFlow, and so forth,
have facilities for doing exactly that function.
TensorFlow Save Models has a bunch of things.
Protobuf has options.
And I don't think, in principle, that is not what you're saying.
You're not saying that training can be taking data,
like an object code blob, storing it in the model.
And then when you build your AI system and you use the model,
copy that data, load it into an executable area of memory,
and run it.
Now, if I'm building consumer electronics, though,
and I'm sending updates using my model, which
is going to be an increasingly common paradigm, given
the fact that we have just huge amounts of AI hardware being
put out there, then it would be an attractive thing for me
to update my platform via that AI model.
And some of the things I'll put in there are, yes,
they're technically trained.
They're trained to say, here's a lookup table of what
should be executed when the system initializes,
the AI system.
And I think it would be good to just draw a bright line
and say, no, you can't just say that--
you can't just move something technically
into what is the model and get around these principles
that we're making clear.
And that's the same thing as if you
were to move that code elsewhere in your AI model.
I see your point.
Now, it's more clear.
But I would recommend that we go back
to the reason why we put, at the beginning of the document,
the definition of what is an AI system.
Maybe that helps.
Because if we go back to the definition, what is the AI
system that we are defining in this work, in this document?
The AI system is anything that, for implicit objectives,
given an input spits out an output.
So whatever you call that, whether you package it
in a binary that loads a blob and executes
a virtual machine that executes something else,
if what we're calling here is what we're defining
and what we need the corresponding--
the preferred form to make modification of
is whatever that system is, however it's packaged,
however it's shipped, whatever it ships.
So when we go into the implementation,
some reviewer who wants to--
someone like, I don't know, the Linux Foundation
wants to--
may want to have a requirement some day,
maybe will have a requirement that says,
we only accept AI systems in our projects that are open source
AI following the definition of DOSI.
Then they will have a standard set for specifically
that technology, the same way that they have the model
openness framework now for the generative AI models.
And in that place, they can put all of the requirements
specifically for that technology to say,
nope, that loading of that binary
here is not a good thing.
It's basically a workaround.
It's not acceptable.
Or we'll have to wait and see.
I mean, another way, another approach that we could have
is to wait and see what--
if this threat that you have in mind
is actually going to show up.
It's not just a theoretical threat.
If it will be showing up, we're thinking one of the tasks
that we have to do by the launch is to really come up
with suggest recommendations on how we're going to be
monitoring the efficacy, the adoption of the open source AI
definition, the availability of other--
availability and reviewing of the existence of open source
AI systems besides the initial ones that we have identified,
which, by the way, are the ones released by the Eleuther AI,
Alen AI Institute, LLM 360, and most likely,
DII, we're working to understand those better.
So those are the ones that pass the open source AI definition
right now.
Thank you.
I see.
Yeah.
Ben?
So when a company modifies an open source AI model
for commercial use, at what point
does the modification become a derivative work subject
to the original license?
And would existing legal tests around open source licensing
be sufficient to determine the AI model modifications
and the derivative work aspect of it?
Or do you foresee a whole new level of legal guidance
needed with regards to these type of things?
Yeah, that's a very good question.
Frankly, lots of it depends on what the models themselves
are considered under laws.
Because right now, yeah, it all depends
on what contracts get built around them
and how those propagate between--
all the rights propagate between this new artifact,
the trained weights, trained parameters, to derivatives.
Yeah.
Not easy.
So there is a conversation now happening on the license
review mailing list, which is the community of volunteers
who've been reviewing licenses, software licenses.
And they've been asked to consider
how to handle licenses and other legal documents that
are not covering software, so the traditional space.
So if you're interested in joining that conversation,
I would highly recommend to join the license-review mailing
list.
I see a question from Peter.
Other non-profits in OSI ecosystems,
like GNOME, Alliance Foundation, Physotek Foundation, et cetera,
have any of them attempted to independently define
open-source AI or provided input to OSI about OSI's definition?
Oh, Peter, yeah, this is a great question
because it allows us to explain a little bit more
what the process has been.
So this is not OSI's definition, the same way
that the open-source definition is not OSI's definition.
We merely maintain it for the community.
So we have worked from the very beginning with Linux Foundation
and FSF and others, reached out to them
and asked them to contribute to the definition.
This definition is not written by us.
It's written by a process held by a co-design process.
It's a process designed to work with the people affected
by the decision, not for them.
So yes, all of these organizations
mentioned, plus many others-- Creative Commons, Eleuthera
AI, Mozilla Foundation, many other groups
that have participated to the list.
And we have somewhere on the website,
opensource.org/deepdive, we have a list of the groups
that have been-- and the volunteers that
have been included.
, All right.
Are there any more questions?
[AUDIO OUT]
OK, then.
I'm going to call it a day, call it a week.
Thanks, everyone.
This has been very useful, very interesting for me.
I hope it's been informative for you, too.
And I would like Nick is saying on the chat,
our discussions continue on our forum,
discuss.opensource.org.
And the license review working group is available.
Peter, stay on the chat here.
I will send you the link where to join it.
It's old school, meaningless.
Thank you, everyone.