All right.
Thanks for joining this panel meeting again.
Sorry for my voice.
This is the result of a week of conversations in Brussels in very loud environments.
I think I stressed out my vocal cords a little bit too much.
And I caught the false debug, which is not COVID.
Just a little cold.
So the purpose of these meetings is to keep the tempo and get live conversations and live
updates on the most important things that have happened in the past couple of weeks.
And let's remind everyone our principles under which we operate.
We try to have -- make sure that one person speaks at a time.
There's no crowds around Mike.
Try to make space for others.
If you tend to be quiet, speak up.
You can use the buttons to raise your hands in this meeting, but you can also type if
you prefer not to speak up.
But please give feedback.
This is the best place to have quick interactions.
Let's use them.
And I don't think we need to be stressing the fact that we want everyone to be nice.
And keep in mind, we need to keep moving.
We need to finish this process.
And if we face an obstacle, we move around it and we should be getting back to it later
rather than stop it and admiring how big and insurmountable it is.
And we need to focus on solutions.
It's a multi-stakeholder, co-design process.
It's basically pioneer work for us.
And we know there are a lot of things that don't work that can be done better.
But we need to focus on what actually works and keep on moving.
Are there anything else that we need to take care of?
All right.
Reminder.
I was wondering whether to keep this slide or not.
But I think I want to remind everyone that our objective is to have an open source AI
definition that is workable, that is good enough by the end of the year.
It's really important.
And everyone is asking, not only is asking for one, but I think that we really have this
responsibility to create, to come to an agreement, to agree on something.
And notice the version number 1.0.
It's not necessarily going to be the most perfect one.
We will always be able to fix it.
And a reminder for what we have so far.
We have a definition of AI systems in a document, version 5.05.
And we have basic preambles for the basic principles of why we need an open source AI.
And we may want to have this wording also reviewed and straight up as quickly as possible.
Because that's another question that I get asked often.
Why do we need open source AI?
Why is it important?
I refer to this preamble, but I want to make sure that we are quoting that.
The other piece is the what's Atascope?
And there has been a little bit of discussion around what is Atascope.
I encourage you to give feedback on this text, too.
Because I don't want to, you know, I want to have it finalized as quickly as possible.
I don't think that it's bad, necessarily.
But we want to have a conclusion very quickly.
Then we have the four freedoms.
There isn't much debate around this right now.
Although there are a couple of questions that I will highlight later.
And what we're working on right now that is missing is this checklist of legal documents.
And I give you an update now on this, on the work that we've been doing.
So the four freedoms as described here are at the core of the open source definition
of AI.
And we're at the stage where we need to identify what are the preferred forms to make modifications
to an AI system.
And in the process, understand what we're going to be is highlighted here.
And we're at the stage two.
We have a list of components that we have identified thanks to the work done by Linux
Foundation AI and Data Commons, Generative AI Commons Working Group.
They have provided a list of components for machine learning systems.
And we have been using that list of components to identify which of those components are
required, they are a must have, in order to be able to use a system, to study a system,
modify and share it.
And then once we have this list with these matching points, we're going to be progressing
on this, on this, on this line, on this timeline, where we're going to be checking whether the
components have or fall under which legal frameworks, whether that's exclusive rights,
exclusive rights like intellectual property, broad term, copyright, patents, secrets, or
what have you.
Or if they don't, what kind of legal frameworks they fall under.
And then we're going to be looking at the licenses as a next step.
And the licenses are legal documents, legal terms, with which they are distributed.
We're going to be identifying gaps.
And from those gaps, and from the list of legal documents, we're going to make a checklist
to evaluate the freedoms in these legal documents.
Now we started working with two groups, analyzing specifically Lama 2 and PTI as examples, two
examples of generative AI machine learning systems.
And the members of these groups are in this list, me and Mer, are almost basically observers
and facilitators of the meeting.
And we have experts of different, different capabilities.
All of these people are working for a company, one way, shape, or form.
But they're participating, not representing their company's views.
They're representing us, experts.
But of course, for transparency, we list their affiliation.
So this is the Lama Working Group and PTI Working Group.
It's a little bit smaller, but it includes people here from different parts of the world
also.
So with them, we have gone through, the process has been, we're at the point where we are
at this working group report.
They need to go through these documents.
They're going through these documents.
Let me share with you what's happening, what's happening in here.
So for, we built this table, you may have seen it in draft five that I published at
the beginning of last week.
The draft five of the definition of open source CI has this table at the bottom, in which
you can see the list of components, and then on each, on the first column.
And then there are other four columns.
Those four columns have, basically, they're going to be X marks, whether the component
on the row is required, so it's mandatory.
It must be available to use the system, to use LamaTo, or to study LamaTo, or to modify
and share it, LamaTo, so individually.
And the components are split into four categories.
There is code, and this is what happens, what are the analysis done by the experts in the
working group for LamaTo.
And it looks like, in order to, the kind of code that we need to, there is pretty much
consensus on the kind of code that needs to be available for using LamaTo is the inference
code and the libraries, such as the tokenizer and hyperparameter search code, et cetera.
So those are required to use, seem to be.
In order to study, there is a little bit less participation of this group, like only one
person so far has filled in the table.
And it looks like training code and data pre-processing code and the other libraries are required
to study and to modify.
Similarly, there is little participation, but there are some boxes in here.
Moving forward on the data front, doesn't look like any of the data is required to use
the system, but SC is the initials of StackFano Zacchiroli.
He's looked at the, he's left these comments that training data set and other data documentation
is required to study.
And similarly, testing and validation data set is required to modify the system, but
not to use and share.
And finally, on the use front, looks like there is pretty much consensus that model
parameters is necessary to use it and study, modify, and share.
And maybe usage documentation, according to StackFano Zacchiroli, is required to modify.
And moving forward, Pithia, this one working group has done a little bit more work and
it's a little more comprehensive.
You can see that in order to study the data, it looks like there is a lot of boxes checked
here, which is very interesting to see.
Some data is even necessary, according to Sarah Young, in order to run, to use the system.
It's going to be interesting to see, to have for her, the rationale behind this decision.
And on the data front, sorry, that was the code front, yeah, okay, so on the code piece.
On the data front, some data required to use, but there is a unanimity that, again, a lot
of data is required to study, which is also very interesting and needs to be investigated
further.
And when we build a model for execution and model architecture and parameters seem to
be necessary, but also modify and share.
So this work is making progress.
We are, we have scheduled two more meetings with each of these groups next week, and we're
going to drive for completing these cards by Friday, so that we can have two complete
analyses and publish them for a wider conversation on the forums.
This is going to be a very major milestone for us, and a very good, important result.
Now, the forums that we launched, we launched them, was it last week?
They already contain a lot of interesting conversations, but I wanted to highlight three
of them that I think are very crucial to have some sort of, to have a, to drive towards
a conclusion so we can release a T in three weeks, four weeks, we can release a new draft
of the definition.
And I think that the top and most important one is the conversation around data, and you
will see it on the forum.
This is one of the ones with the highest amount of comments on it, I think.
It's worth keeping an eye out in there, because I think we need to come close to a conclusion
very soon, or at least to try to understand what the consensus is, or if there is no consensus,
we need to highlight why, and what are the reasons, the main reasons for that lack of
consensus, the controversial part.
It's very crucial in there.
And the other thing, the other conversation we have ongoing is that I think is important,
it is the one on the definition of AI system, that right now we've been using the one provided
by the organization for economic cooperation and development, the OECD.
There are a couple of comments, one by Richard Fontana, but also others, that, arguing that
the definition by the OECD is too wide, and too, that covers pretty much everything.
Everything digital.
And we may want to revise it.
So I don't have a strong attachment to that definition, or any other definition, but we
need to have a definition of AI system, because the open source AI needs to refer to a system,
and not to individual components, or pieces.
We need to have a framework of reference that we can tie to.
I go back to explaining that the open source definition for software refers to programs.
And programs, even though they're not defined either, but pretty much everyone knows what
they are, the discipline, and the software, the computer science is old enough that we
know a program when we see it.
For AI, I don't think we have that luxury yet, and we need to be able, we need to be
a little bit more specific.
So if anyone knows of different, better, well understood definitions of AI systems that
we can use and reuse, so please go and make suggestions on that thread.
There is another one that is very interesting to me, at least, and there's a conversation
around the meaning of the verb share, because there is an argument being made that the sharing
needs to be clarified, that we can share the systems with the same conditions under which
we have, under the same legal conditions for which we have received it.
I, you know, it's a very quite legally type of question.
I'm not exactly sure I understand where that conversation, that question is coming from,
but I see people involved in it, and I would recommend someone looks at it and tries to
explain or tries to find a converging solution.
So what are the next steps?
And maybe, let me see, I see a question in here.
Nick, the result for Lama2 and PTA, should they be similar?
Eventually, yeah, I mean, probably they will not, because they're different people making
different evaluations.
They should be similar, because they're similar systems, similar architecture, similar things.
They should be similar, but if they don't, then that's what the process is going to be
like.
We're going to have to have a conversation once we have also Bloom, for example, the
three of them, we will have to find a way to identify the diversity and why, explain
why things are different, and drive towards a conclusion.
I think a lot of the work is going to be around explaining exactly what access means.
I'm sensing from conversations I've had with multiple people that the concept of access
to the data, access to the architecture, access to the documentation is different.
Sorry.
Sorry for that.
All right, so what are we doing next?
We started recruiting people, but we need to review this list of components and the
checklists that the two working groups on PTA and Lama2 have started, and also we started
recruiting people to analyze Bloom OpenCV, and we may even need probably will recruit
for more other systems if necessary.
But at least we want to look at OpenCV as a curiosity mostly because it's a non-generative
AI just to validate that list of components down the line.
That's for the next couple of weeks' work.
And just reminding everyone, the timeline is here.
We have draft five released in February as scheduled.
We're going to be releasing 06.
We keep on going with these virtual meetings, town halls, and work group activities, trying
to speed up things so that we can get in end of May, early June with an in-person meeting
that will eventually resolve the last controversies and issue a release candidate.
This is a very aggressive timeline.
I keep on stressing this out.
We need to keep the tempo, and that's why I'm putting so much energy into this.
Once we have the release candidate, the idea is to take it in a roadshow around the world.
We have found already three partner conferences in different ways in different parts of the
world where we can host a presentation and a review of the release candidate.
And so we get to number version one in October.
The criteria for respectively release candidate and version one is to have representatives
from each of the stakeholders to support it, and all of this information is public now
on our website.
And these are the categories of stakeholders where we would be putting logos in here as
we go.
And that's the other reminder that I want everyone to keep in mind.
It's not going to be perfect.
And the board of the OSI is already working on setting up a committee that will be looking
into the review and approval of version one when it comes out, because it's going to be
the board's purview to review and finally approve the work of the community and take
over the maintenance of this definition, because this is going to be the first version, the
first definition maintained by the OSI with a version number in it.
And yeah, we're working very hard to make sure that we have the funding to support all
of this.
So but I'm crossing fingers.
I think we're going to be okay.
And if I run out of funds, I'm going to let you know in advance.
And we got the forums.
I'm pretty excited about this.
So they're easy to sign in.
If you have already a member, log in for any of the open source initiatives, websites,
and opensource.net, it's going to work seamlessly.
If not, you can register, become a free member, or now is also a good time to sign up and
become a full member so that you can vote also at the next election that are coming
up for the board.
And we're also draft 05.
Since last time we spoke at this time, it's a new thing.
So go and look at the latest draft also.
And leave your comments on the you can leave comments directly on the draft, or you can
leave comments on the forums if they're more generic.
If it's specific for, you know, I want to change this word, I would recommend leave
the conversation on the draft.
But if it's more generic about and requires larger, more text and stuff like that, like
leave it on the forum.
And with that, I'm happy to take questions.
Victor, public link to LamaTubePT session.
No, well, actually not yet.
Not yet, because we want to leave the groups to work a little bit more, you know, in peace
and without having to be, you know, like under, what is it called?
Under, you know, like a aquarium type of thing.
We're going to make public everything as soon as the work is done.
Matt is that correct as an answer?
I cannot hear you.
Sorry.
I need to enable you.
You should be able now to unblock your mic.
And now you're muted.
You need to unmute yourself.
Thank you.
It's only been three months, three years of pandemic.
Yeah, so the groups themselves, they meet as small groups, but the membership is transparent.
And then we report out all the documentation that's being created, which is the summary
and also the tables that Stefano shared.
And that really is the report.
I think we're also planning to make the slides that the groups are working from public, which
is effectively the agenda.
So that's how we're balancing transparency and also people being able to have a meeting,
which I think also has value.
So yeah, open to any feedback.
Thank you.
you