All right, thanks everyone for joining this day in the slide access.
I'm Stefano Maffulli, I'm the Executive Director of the Open Source Initiative.
And a reminder, we've been doing this work thanks to a grant from Alfred Sloan Foundation
and a donation from MercatoLibre, which has joined us as sponsors.
Okay, so let's go through quickly a little bit of the history of how we got here
and what we were doing and why we're doing this.
So, why we're defining the Open Source AI now is because
these technologies, since the introduction of chat GPTs or the Open AI launches,
have significantly, significantly impacted how the IT environment in the software spaces
has operated and worked and changed a lot of the fundamentals of our understanding of software
and the Open Source definition.
At the same time, we've seen an incredibly fast reaction from governments around the world,
especially the United States, Europe, but also Japan, China, have started to write laws directly.
And some of these laws, especially the AI Act is very explicit, mentions Open Source AI
and Open Source systems and models without having a specific understanding of what that means.
And the reason for the regulators to do that is to allow for special carve-outs for research and innovation.
Like having seen how the Open Source definition worked for software
and allowed for a thriving ecosystem that is worth apparently 8.8 trillion,
or in any case, it's a huge sum of money, and it's underlying the whole digital infrastructure.
So regulators want to keep everything safe, keep society safe, but at the same time,
they want to make sure that the risks are reduced.
And trying to find that balance revolves around the concept of Open Source AI.
And third is this open washing thing that we've seen a lot of companies,
and especially one abusing of the term Open Source and calling out meta in this space,
for releasing models and releasing artifacts that are not Open Source by any stretch of imagination,
especially their licensing in terms of conditions or not.
But because there is a lack of clarity, they can claim whatever they want,
because there is no easy way to push back and point at a widely agreed upon definition of what Open Source AI actually means.
And so we asked them, I mean, this is just to show the Digital Public Goods Alliance
have given a little, illustrated what they think the benefits of Open Source AI is in general.
So without further ado, let me start from the history.
What we've done is that in late 2021, when I joined the OSI,
we knew it was immediately after Copilot was launched, and it was immediately clear that the word was not going to be the same with that.
So we launched this research that we call Deep Dive AI.
We wanted to understand the space.
So in 2022 and 2023, we ran, if you want, research endeavor.
We interviewed experts. We started to ask them questions.
We published them in a form of deep podcast.
And I recommend you to listen to it because it's really, if you're new to the space,
it gives very good introduction to the legal aspect, the technical aspects, copyright, business and society security.
Also, there's an interview with DARPA program manager for AI security, very eye opening.
Next year, we've done, I mean, in the same year, we also run four panels with four experts covering business, society, legal and academic views.
And we published their report. So if you don't want to listen to the podcast, you don't want to listen to the panel recordings, look at the report.
It summarizes the issue. And together with the webinar series, with interviews and presentations from experts from different parts of the world,
we knew at the beginning or in the middle of 2023, we knew that the issue that we needed to solve was that of the availability of training data.
We knew that that was the problem that we needed to solve in some way, shape or form.
Because it was the most controversial one.
So we thought about using a co-design method to come up with a solution, a plausible solution.
So we went around the world, we asked people questions and we also set up online meetings in order to have more variety.
And we asked them a series of three questions. The first one, what you should be, what should the words or use the verbs,
use, study, modify, share, mean for in the realm, in the domain of artificial intelligence.
And after a few meetings in person and online, it was not too complicated to reproduce the basic principles of the free software definition and port them to the domain of AI.
Then we needed to understand how to implement those freedoms. If you want to use, if you want to study an AI system, what do you need?
So we collected virtual working groups online to analyze four types of systems.
One is Lama, which is completely proprietary. The other one is Bloom, which is very open science, but with a bad license.
PTA is a very open science LLM and OpenCV group analyzed the computer vision neural networks, zoo models, models in the zoo.
So to, to, to find the analysis, to, to look at it from, from also the angle of something that is not an LLM.
And we run some votes, not scientific. I, it was never the intention of being scientific. I've seen conversations on the forum.
The idea was to gather a little bit of feedback that will allow us to move on and check an hypothesis.
The hypothesis here was given the, that known, it showed that the groups were not unanimous in saying that the training data was always necessary to study and modify, especially for modify.
For studying it, it was, that component was a little bit higher.
But we have an hypothesis and the hypothesis to solve the problem of data was to see, okay, if we don't require it, what happens?
So we asked the third questions. Let's go outside, look at the, look at the world, look at existing systems and check which ones would comply if we don't require strictly the training data.
But we require the other components, which is the data processing code and the training code.
So we, we threw, we widened the search to more models to, for this validation phase.
And in fact, we ended up with the expected results. In other words, none of the systems that we knew were bad, like LLAMA or,
or Bloom, for example, we knew that those ones would not pass for different reasons.
So that was that signal. It was just a signal that there might be a way to solve the issue.
And the result was this, right? We, the definition is structured this way.
There is the four freedoms and then the requirements for the preferred form of making modifications to machine learning into these three pieces.
You have to have the weights, the parameters need to be available with freedom respecting licenses and legal terms.
Software needs to be complete for the training, the training and for the data processing.
And then you need a very detailed description of what the data we use for training actually is.
So Redmonk put it quite nicely and he called this the AI conundrums, right?
And he quotes Giulio Ferraioli here. And this is a very interesting quote.
So it says that if we assume that the definition requires full release of datasets, one thing is certain.
It would be a definition for which very few existing systems qualify.
And also those that qualify are less powerful and limited to specific domains.
And then because then the other thing to solve, I mean, the other approach to think about this conundrum is that on the other hand,
we have in the free software and open source movement a long history of making exceptions and finding ways to solve the problems
in order to have more freedom and more open source software.
Now, the other constraints that we have in this whole process is that the board, the OSI board, required three basic pillars, the elements.
We want the definition to be supported by diverse stakeholders.
That means not only end users, not only developers, but all of them.
So end users, developers, deployers of AI, subjects of AI.
And they want to have global representation of diverse interests in the list of endorsers and support.
They also require, the board also requires that the definition must include relevant examples of AI systems.
And this is for a specific tactical reason.
The regulators will not consider the open source AI definition as an interesting one or something to follow and imitate if it is not a general one,
if it doesn't cover general cases and if it doesn't cover and if it excludes clearly anything.
I mean, if it really limited to only small domains.
And it needs to be ready by October. And again, the main reason for this is timing.
The AI Act is already out there and is already law.
And it's already the legislation process, the normative process has already started.
This means that there is a hyperactivity in Brussels, but also in D.C. and in California to convince and educate policymakers that open source just means access to open weights, access to the weights.
And that's all they need to care about. And maybe a little bit of description of transparency in the form, if you're familiar with that data cards or other formats that are pretty lightweight to describe in metadata sense, the data set used for the training.
And which is not sufficient. So there is an urgency to come up with a working definition.
OK, so we're working on Release Candidate 1, which has some clarifications and basic concepts.
This is just a screenshot. It's not really don't don't refer to it too much.
It's going to change between now and when Release Candidate is released.
But I wanted to show here the structure of the document to illustrate a major feature that has been here in its intention from the beginning.
There are probably two main, two macro parts. The top part includes the basic concept, like what is a definition?
What is it that we are defining? Which is it? What is AI? What is an AI system?
And we added here, we may add based on feedback from the forum, the machine learning definition so that we have a list of framework reference of the topics that are covered below.
Then there is the actual open source AI definition, what it is, right? The preamble, why we want it and what is open source AI, which includes the four freedoms.
Now, the four freedoms, as you know, even in the free software world, the free software definition, the freedom to study and the freedom to modify are followed by a sentence that says precondition for this is access to the source code.
And further, the source code is defined as the preferred form of making modification to the program, which is later clarified also in other documents, including the licenses, etc.
Now, we need a frame here to understand what we're talking about, what we need, what is the preferred form of making modifications to an AI system.
And in order to do that, we need to limit the scope. We cannot talk about all of the AI. We need to talk about machine learning in this specific case.
It's the most pressing and urgent matter. Let's finish this part. So the second part, now we enter in the second macro part of the definition.
This part is one that is most likely to change and evolve in future versions of the definition.
So the preferred form of making modifications here lists the three major blocks of an AI system, a machine learning system, which are data piece, the code piece, and the parameters weights and sets conditions for those.
And then we added, which is already in 0.9, space for clarifications. These clarifications serve the purpose of clarifying that whether you call, when you want to call and use the term open source,
refer to anything that spits an output based on an input, whether you call it an open source AI, an open source AI system, open source model, open source weights, open source model or open source weights.
Basically, these are all equivalent terms. You cannot skip the line to some extent and say, well, it's an open source model only.
So, you know, the rest of the definition doesn't apply. No, if you want to call it open source model or open source weights, you have to comply with, we have to provide the preferred form of making modifications to that system.
Now we're also working on a new FAQ and the new FAQ entry will clarify further the four types of training data that are plausible and possible in this world.
And that is clearly, you know, open training data, public training data, obtainable training data and unshareable non-public training data.
And we believe that we believe that all of these four types of data can be part of an open source AI.
We don't want to limit the open source AI only to open training data or open and public training data, because that would limit the capabilities of open source systems and would limit the domain of open source systems.
So open training data typically is something that, you know, you have, you can fairly assume that there is global coverage, global possibility to distribute that data.
And that is a collection of facts like time series of wind speed and ocean temperatures.
And it may seem safe, but I discovered that when trying to immigrate to China, going to China for a business trip,
I noticed that among the reasons for Chinese government to search on entry and exit of the country to search digital devices is for the availability, for the presence of weather information, weather data on the devices.
Meaning this means that even that kind of data is not necessarily easy to circulate around the world, like one can assume.
Public training data is data that others can download, like, you know, the archive of my blog posts, for example.
And this is also this is subject to availability, right? Links go stale and everything like that.
But we can work around that with tools like common crawl or Internet archive and software heritage and places like that where they keep, they can keep the archive.
But that's the public training data. The obtainable training data is data that you can buy or data that you can, you know, they can be obtained if you ask.
Things like the ImageNet data set, for example, and the unshareable non-public training data is private information, that kind of like medical, medical, medical data.
This kind of data can never be asked for, can never be distributed.
And so we need to be careful, but we want to have open source AI medical systems.
So we need to find a way to work around this, this piece.
So I can give a very quick overview of where we're thinking that the release candidate might go to explain things a little bit better.
So in the data information piece, we're trying to make it clear that the requirements are a must.
Like the, we noticed the confusion between the work that we create.
So we're probably going to use, suggesting is to use the word build instead.
Substantially equivalent systems stays together with, but we are adding the fact that the data information needs to work with the code below.
You cannot just say data information alone.
You cannot look at data information alone and think that you can be replicating.
And this is, if you saw online, there was a comment from Professor Perciviere, who highlighted how much the knowing about the data and knowing how it's been processed is the crucial, crucial piece.
And specifies here in particular, if used, so for example, if one uses training data that is publicly available, it needs to be made available.
And for the code specification, there is a clarification that the code must be complete.
You cannot just say, hey, here's the code. No, I need to be able to run it.
I need to be able to run it together with the data information.
I need to know I need to get a working data set in some way or form.
And there is also one line in addition that we're working on.
It's a way to cover all three of these pieces.
So code, data and the issue here is that code weights and data.
The issue here is that could be contractual terms.
And actually, there are like the responsible AI license family has in some of the they show that they played the experiment.
And they have a way of in one contract to say, take this model, take this data and use it under these conditions.
So what we're trying to say here is that we need to have a we need to give away to people like the groups at the OSI who will be reviewing these contracts.
To make sure that we can evaluate the these packages that cover different artifacts,
because if you notice the code individually, the elements code parameters and data,
they have this provision that says code shall be made available on their OSI approved license.
This means that, yes, individually, some elements are covered, you know, they can be covered by this license.
But collectively, we don't have a way in this definition. So it was a missing piece.
And that's what we're working on on this final line.
All right. So these are the groups that we're working with to get endorsements and get different representation and timeline.
We're still aiming to get version one ready for all things open in North Carolina in October, the end of the month.
So for now, you know, we want to hear your voice. So endorse the concepts embedded in the draft.
It's unlikely that they're going to be changing going forward. But the adaptations and clarifications, absolutely.
They're coming because the intention is there.
The intention is to make sure that we have a clear definition that is white, has white support and preserves the principles of open source.
All right. And with that, I think we can go to open the floor for questions.
If you have the mic, you can probably open it yourself or you can type.
Yeah, so I am here. I've obviously shared a lot of my thoughts on on where we're at.
My main concern here is that this is a needs to be a litmus test like the open source definition.
And the open source definition has the benefit of being able to approve a license and then have that license self applied to millions of projects.
Whereas in this case, we really need to look at every single project.
This is getting applied to or somebody needs to look at it, whether it's us or more likely it's going to be the project itself.
And so my my suggestion or my my belief is that this doesn't function as a litmus test and that words like sufficiently detailed and if I can tell you, well, I've got a skilled person here and they're going to say, well, it's not skilled enough.
We've given you enough information. Right. So there's not there's not going to be a way for us to really tell anybody that there is not a source.
I sort of going and trying to implement the thing ourselves based on the information that they've given us.
So let's say that they do achieve the certification.
They get that they get the mark. Does it protect the four freedoms? And I think it's quite clearly I don't think Steven's done a really good job of saying, get these are the kind of proofs that you would need to show like you need to show me that you can make the same modifications to a machine learning system with fine tuning.
Right, we know access to the source data as what you can with access to the source data. I think, you know, as a practitioner, it's clear that that's not the case.
I mean, I feel like we need something that people can self apply, which is like the OSD.
And so it really needs to be something where you say this is the ingredients. This is the manifest. And maybe it's even an electronic manifest, like a JSON file or something that says these are the scripts, the training script, the training data, maybe optionally.
And then with those checkboxes checked, then you get access to the mark, right?
So yeah, I mean, I don't think unless somebody sat down and actually like, tried to size the four freedoms on systems that have been through this, like I maintain that it doesn't function as a litmus test.
Yeah. All right. So it doesn't function as a litmus test. And that's what we tried in the validation phase.
So we said, let's take the, at the time, the definition also had a component called the checklist, which I haven't mentioned.
Basically, the checklist is the list of components of AI systems as described in the model openness framework, which is a paper.
I don't know if you're familiar with it. It's a paper from the Linux Foundation. That paper lists 16, 18 components and classifies the availability of them is used to classify where they stand in three classes.
Open class one is open model class. That's the only way around. Class three is open model class two.
Open models, basically just the weights and model cards, some metadata, model card and data card, technical report, then open tooling.
If they make available also data pre-processing and some other and some other inference code and some other pieces of code.
And then a top class is open science where they provide every everything, every required component, including open training.
I mean, the training code and the training and testing data sets.
So one way that the validation phase work was to say which of these components are required, then one could go and use the model openness framework and see the availability of these marks.
You put zero at this bar, which is between class two and class three and class one, between open tooling and open science.
And that could be one way of having that litmus test.
What we discovered is what you were saying. It requires the finding.
This doesn't work at a glance the same way that open source software and open source license approved open source licenses work.
You cannot look at the repository and see if there is a check the license file could check the open source initiative website and say, hap, this is open source approved or not.
It's not because there are so many different components with different nature.
Some documentation is on a blog post, some code is in GitHub, some or other repositories.
Some of the models are on Agnephase or Kaggle.
Finding all these pieces for a third party of a viewer is almost impossible or very, very complicated without the collaboration of the original developers.
So this is an issue that we are aware of, but it's also an issue that we don't know how to solve today and it could be solved with practice tomorrow.
In other words, there might be a space, a place in time where Agnephase maintains a community of experts or I don't know.
There is a collaboration effort with universities and in fact we started talking with a few of them to see if they want to have, if they want to help us expand in next year the validation phase and fine tune the key indicators of what an open source AI needs.
Because I have a theory in my mind, but it's just a silly theory.
If you're not releasing the data processing code and if you're not releasing the training code, you're not open source.
It's a very, in my mind so far with the samples that I've seen, it's an easy test, but it's not an easy one to solve.
The nature of this animal of AI machine learning is that they are not software, simply.
And even when software, there are examples where understanding if it's open source or not is complicated.
And there are different ways of interpreting what open source means.