>> Hello, everyone.
>> Hi, welcome.
>> Do you want to take it now?
>> I will.
>> It's becoming a tradition that we tag team on this one.
>> Yeah.
Teamwork.
>> So, yes, welcome to the online public town hall for the
open source AI definition for May 3rd.
We always go through our community agreements.
Those who have been here before are familiar, but just to
remember one mic, one speaker, take space, make space.
So if you ask a question, wait for others to ask before you
ask another one.
If you don't want to ask a question, pause and let others
take a chance to speak.
And if you don't usually speak in a public venue, we invite
you to say what's on your mind.
Kindness, just that we -- the work is hard, but that we be
gentle with each other.
And obviously hate speech is not permitted in this space.
Forward motion.
We start by focusing on what's possible.
And we note obstacles and come back to them, but we reroute
around them and do what is possible in the moment.
We seek solutions.
And we know that that is vulnerable, but it is crucial and
that we are all needed in this work.
And are there any other -- any other community agreements that
we have for this meeting today?
Okay.
So -- playing with my windows one moment.
There we go.
Okay.
So, yes, as you all know, our objective for 2024 is to have a
stable version of the open source AI definition and that is
still scheduled for October.
Where are we now?
We have a couple slides that are similar to our last meeting,
but the last meeting was in a different time zone, so I'm
hoping this won't be redundant for anyone.
We are on version 0.0.8, which is feature complete.
It's our feature complete version.
So we have the preamble, the four freedoms, which have been
here for a while.
And then we now have a checklist, legal checklist for
required and optional components that has the required legal
checklist for every single component.
So that has been the new content for this version.
And very briefly, how did we get here?
I see there's chat, and I will trust Stefano and Nick to pause
me if I need to attend to that.
So we started with the four freedoms in the fall of 2023.
I know some of you are actually part of this process.
And this was study, use, modify, and share.
What should these open source principles mean for AI?
And so we had in-person co-design workshops.
We had one at All Things Open.
We had one at Linux Foundation Member Summit.
We had one at the Digital Public Goods Alliance member meeting
in Addis Ababa.
And from that, we came up with the definitions of the four
freedoms for AI.
So these are in 0.0.8.
And they should not surprise anyone, but we've now formalized
them for this technological context.
So we have use the system for any purpose without asking permission,
study the system and inspect its components, modify for any purpose,
and then also to use with or without modification, again,
for any purpose.
I actually will pause for comments at this point.
Let's see.
Yep.
Oh, I see.
Great.
So in the winter, we asked this very big question.
What components must be open in order for an AI system to be used,
studied, modified, and shared, of which there are many,
many different opinions and many, many valid opinions?
And we started doing this, again, by having in-person workshops.
We were at AI Dev in December in San Jose.
And then we got some really good feedback,
which is that working in person only is exclusionary because not
everyone can be in the room.
And so we shifted into virtual work groups in January of this year.
And we also decided to have our work groups focus on specific AI
systems self-described as open so that we could get specific in all
these different questions and debates around open-source AI.
And we're basically looking for systems that represent a diversity of
approaches to AI openness.
And we chose Wama2, Bloom, Pythia, and OpenCV.
And then we recruited members for these groups.
And we were very concerned about having global representation.
So we conducted specific outreach to Black, Indigenous,
and other people of color, particularly women and individuals
from the global South.
And part of being a member of the work group is to have your name and
affiliation shared publicly for the sake of transparency.
And over 50% of work group participants are people of color.
And you can see them here.
And, again, the deck will be available on the website.
So the first thing that the work groups did is they selected the required
components.
So we started with the model openness framework,
which was created by Matt White and colleagues at Linux Foundation.
And you can see those components from that paper on the left,
things like data pre-processing code, training code, evaluation code.
And then there's also model and data components as well that aren't shown.
And then we had work group members vote, initialed vote.
So that's a public vote of is this component required to use or study or
modify or share the system as a whole.
And then I, and this is also public,
created a Likert scale based on the number of votes per component.
And we came up with certain components that were, yes,
this definitely should be required down to no,
there really aren't many votes saying that this should be required.
And then that, that results of that Likert scale, the required, likely,
maybe, probably not, not required,
but into a public forum post for further feedback.
And that became version 0.0.6 of the definition.
So that is the first version of the definition where we actually said,
these are the components that we think should be required for something to be
open source.
And what we just finished early spring was a second activity of the work
groups,
which is to look at the legal documents for these required components and see
are the,
are there legal documents in these systems that are associated with these
components as described?
So we had the required components, which are, there's code components.
As you can see a couple of model components and then a number of data
information or in this earlier version,
data documentation components.
And then we asked volunteers to find links to the documents or licenses that
reference the rights to access and use those components.
And then to evaluate, to look through the document and say,
is use restricted or allowed is modification restricted or allowed is sharing
restricted or allowed for all these different components.
And these are the, so, and this is just a zoom in on the result,
which is 0.0.8. As you saw in the beginning, we have,
we are calling it data information now.
And so data sets are not required,
but information about training and methodologies, scope,
and characteristics provenance labeling procedures,
if used and cleaning methodology is required.
And then we have code components, data, pre-processing code,
training, validation, and testing inference and supporting libraries and
tools. And then two model components, architecture and parameters.
And you can see on the right,
the legal frameworks that we're using for each and then a longer list of
optional components.
This is basically the remainder of the model openness framework components
because obviously we want as many components as possible to be open,
but these are not required. So then, so basically all these data sets,
we say we would love if they're available,
but they are not required to for the system to be called open according to
our definition, additional code elements model.
I see for some reason, I didn't put a highlight on model,
but you can see it in there and other, which is for example,
a research paper or a technical report.
And then just again,
that it's very important that we have a representative process.
It's a global definition. And so this requires global consultation and we
have various stakeholder groups that we're,
that as part of our outreach,
particularly as we move into the next phases of the project and I can go back
to this if people are interested in it,
most involved in the current phase are system creators and licensed creators
and licensees. So people seeking to study, use, modify, and share the system.
And then to increase, I guess, identity-based diversity.
We, I'm using phrases like this one that are specifically inviting,
for example, Black, Indigenous, Latina, other people of color, women,
you can read that paragraph.
And then we also do outreach,
specific outreach to bring underrepresented groups into the process.
So next steps, spring through fall.
So now through October, basically. Right now we're doing definition validation.
So we are seeking volunteers to review. It says one to three.
This is not accurate anymore because now we've decided that we want to do about
10 systems total. So it's actually about six additional systems.
Using that same procedure as of the spreadsheet.
So finding the legal document and doing the analysis of each component,
according to these definitions of study, use, modify, and share.
And we're hoping to have that complete by the 20th.
So in about two and a half weeks.
And these are the systems that we're currently looking for to review.
And we have at least one volunteer for everything except Arctic,
Snowflake Arctic, which is a new addition.
But additional volunteers are welcome on all systems. It's a big task.
So I'm sure that Casey and Mark and Victor and Jan and Racine would love to
have a pal to share that review task with.
And you can email me if you're interested in that,
being a volunteer on any of those systems.
Again, to test the definition against the documentation available for these
systems, the legal documents and licenses.
And our timeline for the rest of the year, we did just release 0.0.8.
We may do a 0.0.9, depending on if there are changes that come back,
major changes that come back from this definition validation activity we're
currently engaged in.
We will have a virtual launch event associated with the release of RC1 in
June, and that date will be TBD.
We had been thinking of doing something in person, and then we thought
inclusion, this is a very important event.
We want as many people to be able to participate as possible.
So we decided to do virtual.
And then we will have a stable version released in October,
and that will be in person.
That will be at All Things Open in North Carolina.
And we have additional virtual and in-person meetings where we'll be
sharing and seeking feedback on, I guess, RC1, release candidate 1.
You can see where we'll be.
And some events, you can see we have the month but not the date.
So we're still working on certain details of this road show.
So, yes, we would love for you to be on the public forum discussed at
opensource.org, and I think that's the QR code.
We'll take you to that site, which you can join for free or become a
paid member.
And we have these biweekly town halls, which you're at right now, so you
know about those.
And then if you're interested in volunteering for definition validation,
you can email me or you can direct message me on the -- on that discussed
platform.
So thank you.
And, yes, Stefano, do you have anything to say before we do the Q&A?
>> I don't know.
Maybe we can share the news.
Shall we?
>> Oh, yes, Stefano.
>> Well, you know, we got -- we have received a grant from the Sloan
Foundation.
So we'll be doing a lot of the -- we're well positioned to have a lot of
participation, a lot of those travel, a lot of those trips to those events
will be supported by this program.
Maybe you can go back.
I had something also I wanted to mention.
Go to slide 28.
I don't know why I remembered this in my head.
I said -- mental note that I wanted to say something here.
Oh, yes.
So here you can see how the legal frameworks in the column legal
frameworks, we have the legal frameworks, the legal frameworks, the
legal frameworks, we have -- we talk about data information available
under OSD compliant license.
And when you look at the code, like inference or data preprocessing, you
see that the legal framework is available under OSI approved license.
And then if you look at the model -- oh, no, yes.
Parameters -- oh, it's cut.
Available under OSD -- parameter says OSD conformant terms.
I think it's interesting here because code, we know that is licensed -- I
mean, we know the licenses, we know the legal frameworks, we know it's
copyright mostly, there is some patent issue, but we've been using OSI
approved license for a long time.
So straightforward, we don't have any problem.
Judging whether the code component are suitable, are available under the
open source principles.
For data information, which is mostly documentation, it's a little bit
fuzzy, but still we can debate -- we know we can identify -- there is no
definition of open documentation.
But I think we can easily identify licenses that give us the possibility
to read the documentation, modify, and redistribute to others.
So that's why we're using the term OSD compliant license.
Although there is a question whether we should use OSD compliant or OSD
compatible.
So compatible with the open source definition or compliant with the open
source definition.
So it's a little bit of a debate and it's ongoing on the forum.
I encourage you to go find the thread and vote.
There is actually a little poll in there.
But the model parameters is interesting because model parameters don't seem
to fall under copyright law.
And there is discussion whether any other exclusive rights apply in
different jurisdictions.
So it's different between like Europe, United States, China, UK.
There is still a little bit of a debate.
So that's why we're using a more generic term that says OSD conformant.
So we want to have -- leave the flexibility to interpret how the
principles or how these parameters are distributed.
Until the dust settles on the legal point of view.
These are the questions -- these are the points that I think will have
to be clarified in the next few weeks during the validation process
among other things.
So if you have opinions, if you know someone who might have opinions,
now is the time to go and check the document.
Because the definition, the draft 08, 008 is feature complete.
It has all the elements that we want.
And if no one really objects or if there are no strong pushback, I think
it's going to be -- the release candidate is going to look very similar
to what we have now.
So any questions, I'm happy to -- me and Mer here are happy to answer.
>> A question on the GDPR.
I can read it.
Shall I read it for the recording or Jan, do you want to come off mute?
>> Yeah, go ahead.
>> I can unmute.
So there's been questions about like when it's -- a model is generating
results that someone is saying, oh, this isn't -- I want to remove this
from this.
From your results according to GDPR.
Wouldn't it be very nice to also have a possibility to do it?
Because if you just have the model, you cannot really remove it.
Because you have to remove it from the training data and then retrain to
get a new thing.
>> Yeah.
I -- yes.
But that is such a big question in fact.
And I'm really curious to see what the results of the lawsuit that just
happened against open AI.
Granted that is a closed, opaque, we don't know what's happening inside
there.
The fact that the source data is not required is because it's exactly for
this reason.
So if there is private information in the source data sets, those -- that
data set cannot be distributed legally.
So that's why we want to know what's going in there.
You know, we went into the training data set.
We want to know exactly how it was filtered.
You know, the duplication, all that thing.
That's why there is a requirement on data preprocessing in the code
section.
Because that's what it means.
You should -- you know, sometimes it's very valuable also to know exactly
how to have the exact same instruments that went into the training.
Building the data set for the training so that one can retrain the model
and/or readjust the parameters with their own data.
Or similar data.
In fact, the exact spelling of the data information requirement is -- says
it needs to be sufficiently detailed information about the data used to
train the system so that a skilled person can recreate a substantially
equivalent system using the same or similar data.
We hope that this solves the problem.
And if -- honestly, yes, if there is GDPR data inside the data set and the
model itself has it, then you should be able to rebuild the -- with your own
data without it.
And maybe that model itself is illegal, right?
In some legislation.
So there is a higher standard that applies here.
>> Thanks.
Any other questions?
You can chat or take yourself off mute.
If anyone has any other questions or thoughts.
>> I can come back on and just ask a little bit of a background question
here because I missed a couple of town halls.
So what is the idea of not requiring the training data in full and just have
the opaque model?
Because that sort of seems to me to be counterintuitive to the spirit of the
open source definition.
And I understand for the legality, but one can also say, well, all open
source models should be legal.
Is that the only thing or is there something more as well?
>> No, I think there is something more.
So many -- the fact that data set did not make it into the draft 06, was it?
Is because the working group as they were evaluating the various systems,
not enough of them put the requirement of the original data set as strictly
required to modify, study, use, and share.
So they ranked higher other -- like the training information.
Like the training code, the documentation on the data used were ranked
higher.
And so because there are so many machine learning systems that don't have
the original data set, like it just doesn't exist because it's not created.
Like for anything that is used with -- learning and other ways that are
privacy preserving.
Then there is that question of private data.
Where it might go -- I mean, it may be part -- I mean, technically part of
the -- good part of the originating data set.
But can be obfuscated or hidden from the model itself.
Like we were concerned -- we are concerned.
I mean, all of us are concerned about generating -- putting the bar so high
that there is no incentive.
Not only there is no incentive into releasing open source, but there is
actually a very strong disincentive into the open source AI.
And in fact, if you look at the amount of lawsuits that any of the more
open foundation models that have been released, they're receiving just
because they've been transparently saying, hey, we have scour the web and
incorporated pretty much anything that we could find.
That, you know, give us -- while on the other side of the spectrum, we
have things like Lama 3 or open AI, they don't say what's inside the
data sets, what went into their training sets, because they don't want to
be sued.
So we're trying to see if there is a balance to be found.
And let's -- the validation is also for this.
Like do we have a set of models out there that already exist that can
fit into the open source AI definition and we can actually work with
them?
Yeah, we want to be pragmatic, but we also want to maintain the
principles right.
The principles that we want to give users freedom, agency, control
over the technical choices doesn't necessarily mean that we want to
have the full spectrum of everything always open all the time.
Because it may be that there is enough elements even without having
the complete spectrum.
If you have looked at the model openness framework paper, it's an
interesting read because it has -- lists all of those components and
then gives a sliding scale of what's required for the -- to be included
in the Linux foundation projects.
And it scales from basically just give us the model parameters all the
way to give us everything.
And they call it open models, open tooling, when some more extra
pieces are available.
In open science where there is everything.
So we're trying to find a balance in there where there is a bar where
we can say, okay, this is open source AI, but -- and then everything
else goes on top.
Yeah.
All right.
So the transparency is a feature of open source.
>> I just want to pause.
I just want to pause.
Because we can continue this conversation for a long time.
Is there anyone else on the call who has a different kind of question?
And if not, we can continue this conversation for a bit of time.
Okay.
No.
All right.
So, yeah.
So we can continue, I don't know, to the half hour maybe talking about
this topic?
>> Yeah.
I just want to also announce the fact that we're going to be talking
about data in a separate talk.
Like there is absolutely a need to better understand the space also
as data becomes functional.
Which is a new thing.
Fairly new thing.
And we want to understand it a little bit better.
One of the stops in September is in France.
And we're working on a workshop specifically to start the
conversation that I'm quite sure is going to take a little bit longer.
Because transparency is the feature.
I want to highlight that.
That's why we're insisting on having data information, provenance
and all of that.
And the code for the training.
The code used for the creation of that data set.
I think it's going to be -- it's a good compromise.
But let's see what else exists in there.
>> I see Claire, you have a comment.
Do you want to come off mute, Claire?
>> Sure.
Thank you.
So this is just a question to see if there is any current effort
going into keeping track of any other definitions of open source
AI.
And specifically thinking about anything that might be referenced
in any emerging regulation or policies that might be coming at a
government level.
Knowing that I think it was referenced in the AI act, but I'm
not sure how it was referenced or what they defined it as in that
act.
>> Yeah.
So thanks for the question.
Because the AI act mentions multiple times, a couple of times
that it's a free and open source AI system without providing any
explanation of what that means.
So it was one of the triggers to push for this project to start
two years ago when we saw -- when I saw the first draft of the
AI act, I was like, oh, we need to have -- we need to help
regulators understand this space.
And we're having fairly good, intense conversations also with
the American agencies which are now under pressure to come up
with regulations inside to -- right.
To control a little bit this market.
As it comes out, there are so many foundation models that it
talks about risks and they all want to know what open source
means, what open means in this space and what the implications
are for public in general, for public interest.
>> Thank you.
>> Maybe one final thought or comment and then we'll close the
session.
I saw you typing.
If you want to have a last thought, you're more than welcome
to share it.
>> Maybe I see types.
I can say watch the space, watch our blog, too, because we're
going to be continuing the conversations around data.
I think it's a really important space where we don't have a lot
of practice.
There are new legal questions that are being raised like what
is exactly right, acceptable when it comes to text and data
mining.
New regulation around text and data mining specifically
appearing around the world like Japan has an approach that is
very -- Europe has introduced it as a new right and it's still
having -- there are some limitations to it, though.
So policies are going to be written and all the lawsuits in
the United States which are very interesting and we're waiting
for them to be clarified.
Yes, so Claire, the outreach plan is vast.
Like we've scrolled through with Mayor, but yes, we are reaching
out to a lot of the AI communities, startups, developers,
conferences like new rips and others.
Yeah.
Granted, it's going to -- remember what I like to remind
everyone, that the open source definition came out after at
least 15 years of experience in the free software world and when
the developers were few, computers were not as ubiquitous as
they are now, and it took a while to become so well-known and
widely respected, so we'll have to be doing this work of open
source AI.
We're defining it in a few months.
So we're going to have to do a lot of work after -- continue to
do a lot of this outreach work in the next years.
Yes, if you're coming to PyCon, you'll find us there.
That's our next stop.
All right.
Thanks, everyone.
We host this every two weeks.
I think that next week I'll be at PyCon, so we will not be able
to have this.
But we'll meet again in two weeks and the forums are still
going to be active and available.
Thanks, everyone.