Good.
Let's get started.
Thanks everyone for joining this public town hall.
I don't even remember the fifth in the series,
but there's been a while we've tried to be transparent
about the process and what's happening
and give a very quick overview
of what's been happening in the past few months
and look at the latest draft
and have a quick glance at what's coming next
because we're really approaching the last months,
actually the last weeks of the drafting process.
We really are getting close to something that is workable.
Let's start with our community agreements
to remind everyone that we are welcoming a place,
we're also trying to balance with moving forward
and finding converging towards a solution,
leaving the largest building blocking paths,
elements for something that can be fixed in the future.
And we are aiming quickly towards having a definition
for open source AI by the end of the year.
So where do we stand now?
Remember, this is a reminder of what we've been working on.
We have a preamble that sets the objective
of why we're doing this, what are the objectives,
what are the reasons why we want to have a clear definition
of open source AI, why that's necessary.
And we want to also clarify what we think needs to be fixed
and we need to be addressed the issues that AI creates
are to be resolved at a different level,
at the government level, governance level,
deployment levels, and not inside the documents
that are used to distribute and make AI systems available.
Then we have worked quite heavily to define the freedoms,
to define exactly what is open source AI in practice,
what are the identifying elements of when we see it,
we will know that that system is an open source AI.
This top part, before what we call the legal checklist,
this top part is the most important piece
and the most urgent piece that we need to get right
and we need to get it right quickly.
What follows below is the space,
is what we are reviewing and revising at this stage.
The top part looks fairly stable
and I really urge everyone to look at it,
to give it a very solid, deep read,
to see, to highlight possible mistakes,
possible areas of improvement,
because we really need to put this to bed
as quickly as possible.
And since no one has been giving a lot of comments to this
in the past couple of iterations,
I'd love to tell everyone, to remind everyone
that this is very important that we complete the process
and this top part is really, really, really the top,
the most important one.
What comes below is the,
what comes below the legal checklist is,
basically, an operation manual,
or at least recommendations and the initial recommendations
for operators of the,
for the people who would be reviewing AI systems
and evaluate whether they satisfy the definition
about what is open source AI.
And because these are strongly targeting,
this checklist is strongly targeting
machine learning systems,
because those are the systems that introduce new elements
and pose more challenges at the moment.
In the future, it may be different,
but at the moment, machine learning is what is creating
this uncertainties around what is open source,
rather than other systems.
And the main reason is because the AI systems require data
and they produce, machine learning systems require data
and they produce model weights.
And these two elements are fairly new in the software world.
And we haven't really been thinking about how they interact
with the open source definition.
This whole exercise of finding the open source AI definition
revolves around these disruption, if you want,
this disturbance in the understanding
of what open source means.
And that's what we are analyzing.
This checklist is the piece that we are using
to evaluate whether a system is open source or not,
the response to the open source definition for AI or not.
So what we've been doing, we started in the fall
and we found these principles with co-design workshops
that we run in multiple parts of the world,
like in October in Raleigh, North Carolina,
then we went to Monterey.
We went to Alisabeba with the United Nations
Digital Public Goods Alliance to run another workshop.
And the result of these conversations,
also we had conversations online,
came out, produced this Four Freedoms for AI,
which is basically the four freedom for free software,
adapted and reviewed and purposed for AI systems,
thinking about the definition of AI system.
Then we focused on understanding the required components
that one needs to have for a machine learning system
in order to exercise those freedoms.
So what do you actually need in order to have access
to these systems?
So we had, again, more workshops in person in San Jose,
and then we run virtual work groups online
to analyze four specific systems,
Lama2, Bloom, PTI, and OpenCV.
And you will see a variety of elements in here.
You see Lama2, it's a commercial project
and distributed with legal terms
that include restrictions,
and the Open Source Initiative has already called Lama2
not an open source system.
But it's relevant to have the analysis.
We looked at Bloom because it's an open science project.
It's very open in terms of it distributes
a lot of its components,
and it's very complete from the science perspective.
Also, we know that it's been shared with our license
and with legal terms that prevent some uses.
PTI is another open science project,
and it's very permissive.
And OpenCV is similarly an open source project
with lots of openness and lots of open components
made available, but it's non-generative.
So it's a computer vision, machine learning,
machine learning system.
So adding a little bit of variety.
We asked for volunteers and we reached out to volunteers
to have the most, the widest possible diversity
in different levels and different stages.
We invited experts from like the developers
and technical experts of each of these groups.
And we included others.
Like we invited Davide Testugine and Jonathan Torres
from Meta into the LAMA working group explicitly
because they are experts.
And if someone couldn't find a component,
we could ask the experts to go look for them
and to tell us whether those were available or not.
And that's the reason why they're here together with,
for example, Stella Biderman from PTI.
And we worked also, we aligned our work.
We started with the model openness framework
that is produced by Matt White, Ibrahim, Adad
and others from the Linux Foundation and other researchers
who they have analyzed machine learning
and they grouped the required, the components
that go into producing, distributing a system.
And we based on that list of components,
we asked the volunteers in the working groups
to go look and see which of these components
you think is required to study,
which one is required to use the system,
which one is required to share and modify.
And they voted for each of these components.
Then we composed and weighted all those results,
all those votes.
And we came up with a recommendation summary
of what is required and what is less necessary
or gathered less votes from the working groups.
And that has produced the latest,
no, that has produced a list of components
for which we needed to go look at the legal documents.
So we had the required components,
we grouped them into three main areas for code,
for what we call model, and then for data
because the votes didn't reach a very high threshold
for the votes of the working groups
didn't reach a very high threshold
to require the original training dataset.
And because of other practical considerations,
we substituted the information,
we built a proxy for the access,
having access to the original training dataset.
We replaced it with requirements for data transparency.
Like we wanna have the maximum amount
of transparency on the data.
And we wanna have also the tools
instead of the actual dataset,
the tools to build compatible data datasets.
So we want to have the code
that went into building that dataset as an alternative.
And now with that list of the required components,
we went and looked at the legal frameworks
for each of these components.
And we ended up with having basically everything
we discovered basically that everything,
all the required components,
they fall under copyright quite clearly
except one of the components.
So everything that is code,
so in this slide, you can see everything
that is in the pre-training, I mean, the code section,
in the data transparency section,
that's documentation basically.
And in model architecture,
those are all distributed as code
that is written by a human,
falls squarely under copyright
and maybe patent law eventually.
But it's something that we are very familiar with.
It's an environment that we understand very well.
It's an environment where we have, it's a legal framework.
These are legal frameworks for which we have licenses
and clear understanding of what those means.
But for the model parameters,
and these include, for example,
the weights and the biases.
For model parameters, we don't have a universal understanding
around the world of what these fall under,
what kind of laws they fall under.
So we have to be a bit more careful evaluating
what are the terms that we want to apply here
and how we want to have,
evaluate the legal terms
under which model parameters are distributed.
So I mentioned that we worked a lot
to get global representation in this process,
because ultimately we want,
we have engaged with,
we have identified these groups of stakeholders,
like system creator, license creators, regulators,
licensees, end users, and subject.
And we have tried to engage with as many as possible.
With the most involved ones in the current phase
have been the licensees and system creators
and license creators,
so lawyers and integrators and developers.
And we are expanding our reach now at this stage
to end users, subjects, and regulators.
And as a proxy for regulators,
we're gonna be engaging with civil society
who talks to regulators, lawmakers around the world.
And so we have closed that phase,
so we have now the next steps,
what's happening in the next steps.
We're getting ready to release the next draft, draft 08.
I'm actually at a conference this week
where I gathered a lot of feedback
and may be able to release at 08 before May,
and maybe go into Pittsburgh at the PyCon
with an even higher version number,
even more clearly towards a release candidate with a 0.1.
So skipping that level
and going into minor release numbering.
And like a feature complete,
but with close to be a release candidate in June.
Between in June, we'll hold in-person or online.
This is getting into a territory
where we'd love to have it in person,
but we also would love to have different people
from different parts of the world.
And so it's probably most likely gonna be online
instead of in-person, but we'll see what happens.
In any case, in June, we wanna have a group
of important relevant stakeholders
who have been involved into the drafting process
to meet and release the release candidate number one.
And during the summer months between July
and the end of October,
we have a plan to go through a worldwide roadshow
to demonstrate, to illustrate, to advocate for,
and gather in different parts of the world
and gather more sustained to support
and endorsement from different groups and organizations
so that at the end of the October in Raleigh
at All Things Open,
the OSI board can review the draft with the comments
and release the stable version at the end of the month.
And this is our plan.
I think we're getting very close to the finish line
and it's really exciting.
If you haven't been involved until now,
I really, really, really, really encourage you
to go to the online forums
where we have healthy, deep conversations.
Keep coming to these down-home meetings,
ask questions, and stay engaged
because we are making history right now.
We are writing a definition that we hope will remove,
that we want people to use to remove uncertainties
and doubts from the market.
People are releasing more models.
They're using the open source moniker.
They are confusing regulators
and legislators around the world.
And we need to provide certainties.
We need to provide a stable view
of what open source AI means
so that regulation can come in
and encourage innovation without causing harm,
without spreading more disinformation
and providing a positive environment.
So with that, I'm gonna take a pause.
And if you have any questions, I'm happy to respond.
Any curiosities?
- Yeah, I just have a question.
So again, you may have touched based on it,
but I was not sure it was clear.
You do not touch at all on the data used for training
except getting some form of transparency.
Do I get it right?
- Yes, that is correct.
This is a, it's really,
we started to work on a frequently asked question document
because it's becoming recurrent now
as more people are becoming aware of the process.
The data issue has been,
we have debated it at the very beginning
and it's been really confusing.
It's been really, it's been going around in circles.
Like the very big issue with data
is that if we require the original dataset
to be distributed together with the model weights
and parameters and the rest of the code,
we will automatically exclude from the pool
of possible AI systems.
We will exclude systems that don't have data
where the data is not available, right?
Like federated learning,
federated learning or privacy preserving,
training mechanisms, all of those, for example,
will not be part of the open source AI ecosystem
because there is no data.
The other reason is that many times
you have the right to download, for example,
information from a website
in order to do data mining on it,
but you don't have the right to redistribute it further.
So also in these cases,
you got a model parameters
that you can definitely use.
You have instructions to rebuild that dataset,
but you cannot really have the original dataset
because it's illegal to distribute it.
And so to obviate for these issues,
it's much easier and probably also more relevant
to have access instead as a proxy to the tooling,
to the filtering and to the instructions
on how the dataset was built as a minimum.
Again, these are default requirement.
Nothing really prevents from something like
Starcoder or other systems
that have been built with open science in mind
and have been very careful.
Like Luther AI is working on the pile
to a new dataset that is more,
since they became more concerned
about the copyright status of the input,
the training datasets,
they're rebuilding the pile,
excluding all the possible sources of lawsuits
and DMCA takedowns.
So nothing excludes from building datasets
that are relevant and important
and can be distributed further,
but that would make the open source AI,
would put the, having that as a harder requirement,
would put the open source AI at a disadvantage
compared to the commercial proprietary systems
where they basically don't even disclose
the list of the data.
Yeah.
- That makes sense.
Thanks a lot.
So that's indeed very clear.
- Absolutely.
- Thank you.
All right.
If there are no more questions,
then I will close it here.
And again, please go to the forums
and there is a long thread about data
where you can see the past conversation
on this very hot topic.
And yeah, we can continue there,
or we can also move on to the other big issue,
which is defining and understanding a little bit better,
gathering more comments on the legal status
of the model parameters and understand,
get more suggestions on how we should treat them.
Thanks everyone for joining and talk to you soon.
In two weeks, we'll redo this.
Bye.