So let's start the recording. Hello everyone, my name is Nick Vidal. I'm the Community Manager
at the OSI. Today I'll be presenting and staff will be joining us shortly for Q&A.
And but if you have again if you have any questions just put it on chats. Later we are going to open
up for Q&A. So today we're going to be talking about especially RC1 that was released two days
ago. And this release candidates has introduced a lot of changes and hopefully we're converging in
the right direction based on community feedback, right? Of course there are a lot of controversial
topics still. People are still asking about the community feedback. So I'm going to start with
the community feedback. So I'm going to start with the community feedback. So I'm going to start
with the community feedback. So I'm going to start with the community feedback. So I'm going to start
People are very passionate about their opinions.
And that's perfectly fine.
And we're here to hear everyone's opinion.
Now let's start with the question why define open source AI now, right?
Why now?
So of course, there has been a huge popularity of AI, especially large language models in
the past, I would say, two years.
And so this is something that has been over media.
People have been claiming that they actually have an open source AI or large language model.
But there's no clear definition of what that is.
What that actually entails.
What's actually open source AI.
And for that reason, OSI being the, I would say, the champion of open source, the open
source definition, we felt that it was important for us to step in, not just ourselves, but
together with other community members, other nonprofit organizations, to try to come up
with a more open source AI.
And we're here to hear everyone's opinion.
Bye.
Yes, bye.