Welcome to the fourth Town Hall. The scope of this Town Hall is to get people the chance
to interact live with the process, ask questions, and get regular updates on what's happening
and what's hot. So for the live meeting, just a few ground rules. We want to be giving space
and being nice, listening to questions, but also make sure that people can ask questions
and feel empowered to do so. But we also want to make sure that we're moving forward. We're
not getting stuck debating forever. We need to make decisions and keep on going. And let's
remind everyone that the objective for 2024 is to have a working open source AI definition.
And by working, I mean it must be something that has endorsements from different groups
and can be put in practice and allows for open source AI systems and components to exist.
It's not something that is theoretical pie in the sky. We love it, but nobody can use
it in practice. What we're working on is to have a definition that is made up of a few
pieces. We have pretty decent understanding of all the pieces in here, minus some wordsmithing
and clarifications, but the basic piece that we're still working on is the license or legal
documents checklist at the bottom. So what happens, we have clarified that what is open
source AI is basically something, it's referred to AI system. And the reason for it is that
it gives us an anchor. It gives us a way to clarify what we're talking about, what freedoms
we want to use. And it helps us run, drive the conversation around what do I need in
order to use an AI system? What am I actually using? What is it that I want to study? What
is it that I want to modify? What is it that I want to share? What kind of practical outputs
or practical elements, examples I want to get out of this freedom, out of this verb?
And so we've been running this exercise with four groups that have been split into analyzing
four systems, Lama2, Bloom, BFIA, and OpenCV. Three of them, the first three are generative
AI systems and OpenCV is non-generative. It's a computer vision program, computer vision
framework, set of libraries with different algorithms. And some of the algorithms that
OpenCV uses are neural networks and so machine learning based systems. And we wanted to see
with a little bit of differentiation, if the requirements are different for non-generative
AI systems so far. So you see the people who have volunteered to analyze the systems and
there is a lot of diversity here, geographic representation from all over the place, from
all places in the continent. There is academia represented, there are industry players, there
is civil society interest in here too, and government organizations like the ITU. You
can see a lot of diversity here. I'm really happy to see the involvement of the very wide
breadth of people volunteering their time to contribute to this effort. I kept saying
this from the beginning, this is not the effort defining something new like open source AI,
having a new definition. The Open Source Initiative is not the work of a genius in a basement
that comes out with a secret text. This is the work of a community that puts their brilliant
minds together and drives towards consensus, drives towards a shared understanding of what
open source AI means. That's what's going to make this valuable.
So the summary, so these groups have been looking at the list of components that have
been produced by a list of components, generically described in a working paper that is almost
ready for publication by the Linux Foundation AI and Data Generative AI Commons Working
Group or initiative inside the Linux Foundation AI and Data Foundation. They have produced
a list of components that they want to use as a reference for judging the projects that
are going to be hosted by the Linux Foundation. We've taken that same list of components,
we passed it to the working groups, and each of them have been looking at the list of working
groups and have been answering the question, what do I need in order to, which component
is necessary, which component is required to train, to study, or to run a system or
modify and share it? And a summary, very quick high-level view,
is what are required are the training and evaluation and testing code, there is a requirement
for inference code, model architecture, model parameters, and supporting libraries and tools.
That looks like there's pretty good consensus. And then a few other things are on the likely
required, maybe required, are data pre-processing code, data sets, and usage documentation.
And then on the right-hand side, you see what's likely not to be required.
We have asked the group to vote for each component. We compiled the votes into one document that
I will show, and we split the results. This is an example of the table that the working
group has been using as a reference. They've been filling in their initials in the cells.
For each row, there is the component, and on the column side, there is yes or no. Is
it required for using? Is it required to study, et cetera?
Then we compiled, we're compiling the exercises. It's going to be done today, completed today.
We're compiling this spreadsheet with the sum of the votes for each of the components,
and we're going to grade it with a very simple algorithm. Basically, a yes if the median
is higher than two votes, et cetera. I mean, yes, is the median higher? It's a yes. It's
lower? It's a no. Pretty simple. This is what it's going to look like, and we're going to
share this as the exercise completes today. I'm going to summarize and make it public
next week on the forums.
So, code, we can see what's required. As I mentioned, inference code is mostly likely
on the data front. This is the interesting part. A lot of the groups are leaning on the
maybe or maybe not. Maybe not. This is an important result and something that we'll
have to spend a little bit of time debating as soon as the exercise finishes. My sense
is that this is the crucial. We knew from the beginning that the conversations around
data are crucial. Some of the live interactions that I've had with people in the working group
have been along. I've been sort of describing what the highlighting, I've been highlighting
to me the fact that definitely data is often, if not always, necessary, but the level of
access is different in the mind of the practitioners. In other words, for example, during one of
the conversations with one of the working groups, one of the questions from a volunteer
was what level of depth do we want to organize or do we want to understand the verb study?
So how deep do I want to be able to study a system? Because there is a very radical
difference between studying a system because I need to write a PhD dissertation or if I
need to study and understand it enough so that I can evaluate, for example, its transparency
according to the regulation from the AI Act or a slightly different level of understanding.
What level do I need to have if I want to only understand enough so that I can modify,
retrain, improve, fine-tune a system? That, in my mind, means diving deeper with other
conversations with some of these working groups has been highlighting how the level of access
to the original dataset is also something that we need to clarify and we have an opportunity
to clarify. How much do we need the dataset in full, like all the terabytes or petabytes
of the original dataset or in some cases, some people have argued that it's enough to
have a very good detailed description of what went into the dataset, maybe a randomized
sample of the data inside the dataset. It could be sufficient to study, to modify, etc.
This is a conversation that we'll have to dive deeper in the next iteration.
The last thing that I want to say around the data issue is that a lot of the debates are
also on the availability of data in general. Many of the practitioners that I talked to
highlighted how not having access to data in general is a problem. The uncertainties
around the regulations for text and data mining and the privacy laws and the very different
implications of the copyright issues that have been raised in the United States and
other places, they're all putting obstacles and this lack of clarity is blocking a lot
of the freedoms that we want to unblock instead.
I've been discussing with the people of the Open Future in Europe and we're starting to
think about opening another separate conversation around data governance. This is something
that might happen in the very near future where the data conversation will probably
be spun off or another parallel conversation will start to talk about the availability
of data.
Moving on for the model recommendation, no surprise here, we know that we need to have
the model architecture and the model parameters and unsure about the model metadata and model
card. This is probably because there is not a lot of clarity over what those components
actually mean because the paper from the Linux Foundation is fairly new still. The communities
need more time to digest and understand what each individual component is.
The other interesting thing is the groups have many, many people have voted yes on the
supporting libraries and tools. That's because depending on how the supporting tools are
described and the Linux Foundation has described them quite well in detail, they include in
here things like hyperparameters, search code and tokenizers that most people consider necessary
in order to interact, for example, with the system.
This is the summary. This is where we are. It's interesting to see how we got very close
to the framework from the research paper on openness in AI from this group and the group
Liesenfeld and Dingelman. This is it. We're going to be ending the vote on the working
group today. We're going to wrap it up and summarize the exercise.
One thing that is quite becoming clear is that we're really focusing on machine learning
right now. This is something that we expected when we started at the very beginning of the
process that we were actually, this definition of open source AI is very close to, I mean
very close. Right now, it's being driven by machine learning. We're going to be talking
mostly about this. I'm not sure exactly how we're going to be dealing with this slight
change, but it may be necessary to clarify this in the definitional documents. I still
don't know exactly how to deal with this. Because there was a conversation months ago
and so many people have argued that what we want to have is a definition for AI in general
and not machine learning specifically. This is something that will be brought up again
and we'll have that conversation. Then there is one highlight that there is an interesting
question from the forum, very thought provoking from Richard Fontana. He's been driving the
conversation around whether we need a definition that refers to open source, I mean to AI systems
and not to its individual components. He makes a very compelling argument and I encourage
you all to check on the forum and see the debate because one of my highlighting here
is only one of the questions that Fontana raises. It is one of his latest messages.
He's talking about whether the terminology may have the effect of narrowing or interacting
in weird ways with the open source definition, the one that refers to software. My current
line of thinking is that the definition of AI system is something that we have to introduce
at the beginning because the conversation that we were having was going around in circles
because we were talking about things like, "Oh, but what do I need to exercise the freedom
to use a model?" People were thinking about data, were thinking about our components.
It was really not clear. There was no clarity in there. As soon as we introduced the concept
of AI system, then everything started to drive and to be more aligned. Now that we got into
the deeper parts of the debate, we're starting to get a much clearer understanding of what
is necessary to use and to study and run and what kind of components we're talking about.
This is being formalized by the industry groups inside the Linux Foundation. There are other
groups that are working in a similar fashion on listed components for machine learning
systems. It's becoming more clear, that whole aspect. I'm not too married to any of these
ideas. I do want to clarify and answer the question to Fontana.
I believe that every single component – now that we have identified every single component,
each of the components will have its own terms of use and terms of services. Some are going
to be software code and those will be distributed and will be available with licenses like any
other piece of software that we are very used to. Other components like model parameters,
etc., they will be covered by other law and other legal frameworks. I don't think that
there is going to be much of an interaction between the open source AI definition and
the open source software definition. There's going to be interaction, but there's going
to be a clear separation between one and the other. I don't think that there's going to
be any complication in here. We'll have the list of components and we'll have the legal
frameworks understood for each of the components. We will have a way to read and interpret each
of the individual components' legal documents that go with them. We'll be able to generally
understand the freedoms that we must have for each of the components.
One thing that is interesting, though, is that we also are going to generate – we
will need to have some sort of dependency graph. For example, a component that is like
the model parameters. The model parameters will have a dependency on maybe on the tokenizer
because otherwise you're not going to need it. So, model component, model parameter,
and tokenizer will have to come and be shipped together in order to be used. That's why we
need a definition for a system, in my mind. You cannot say the component itself is free
or an open source like the model itself because the model itself is not going to be usable
without this tokenizer, for example. That's where I think we're going to be heading
towards, this dependency graph and the bundles that are necessary in order to have an open
source AI. That's why we need a definition of a system because we need to have some way
of anchoring that conversation. But we may not need it and just reference to the graph.
We'll see where we end up with.
That's for the next step. Today, the final vote. Then, next week, early March, we're
going to be releasing a new version. We're still on time, in my mind, to get to June
with a release candidate. The criteria, to repeat, the release candidate will need to
have the support of at least two representatives for each of these stakeholder groups that
we have invited to the conversation. Version 1 will have to be supported and endorsed by
at least double as such or at least five representatives for each stakeholder group. We will be announcing
it in late October. That's the deadline.
Between the release candidate and version 1, we're planning a worldwide tour to show
the release candidate and host small workshops to iterate with other stakeholders around
the world. We're fundraising for this. Stay tuned and we'll show details probably next
week or the week after.
I think we're getting much closer to have a full list of stakeholders yet. It's always
good if you have friends or contacts that you think should be involved and should be
following this. Mostly, we're looking for end users and subject category and in some
ways also regulators, although not necessarily government employees or policy makers because
they're not going to be able to freely give feedback. But organizations that work very
closely like lobbying organizations that work very closely with policy makers, they'd be
very useful to have a read into the definition as it's being drafted so that they can help
us understand what the regulators are concerned about.
We create a definition or we come up with a definition that is not illegal out of the
gate. Let's put it that way. Either illegal or impossible to implement in many parts of
the world because it clashes with regulation.
And a reminder that we'll probably have to keep an eye on the evolution of the world
and keep an eye on the definition that we come up with so that we can adapt it in case
there are changes in the technological landscape that will force us to create either another
checklist separate. Like if we're now focusing on machine learning, maybe there's going to
be some new technology or some variation of machine learning that we require to review
the list of components. And at that point, we will have to adjust or add a new checklist
to the bottom of our definition of AI. So we will need to keep on working.
And with that, my encouragement for you is to join the conversation in the forum. We're
making an effort to start publishing weekly also a summary of the forums on our blog to
make sure that everyone has an opportunity to stay on top even though their inboxes get
full. And a reminder to everyone that on opensource.org/deepdive, you will find a link to the drafts and the
drafts themselves are – you can comment on them directly.
So with that, I'm open to opening the floor for questions and answers from you. I can
bring up your mic so you can speak up or you can type it however you want to talk.
I believe Isabel is writing a question. Let's wait for that.
In the meantime, it's very good that we're seeing these types of discussions. And I find
it particularly interesting that we're actually discussing what's the meaning of each one
of those verbs, right? What's use, what's study, what's modify, and what's share? I
see a lot of discussions there in the forum around those verbs. And in particular for
study, it really does depend on how deep it's study, what's the meaning of study. And I
was looking back here at the free software definition and I'm just going to read through
this, the freedom, what, right? So the freedom to study how the problem works and change
it so it does not – it does your computing as you wish.
So it's clear here that the idea behind this is just study how the problem works and to
modify. If you really want something deep, like to study to really understand that, it
becomes clear that you need more than just access to the code. You have to have a lot
of documentation to understand the idea behind that. And the same applies to data. You have
to have not just the data should be open, but also how the data was created. How was
it filtered? So in a way, it becomes impractical. And the open source definition and open source
software has always been pragmatic, right? That's one of the key ideas behind open source
definition. And so having a study so deep like that, perhaps it might become impractical
to actually apply that. So that's what I wanted to share here.
Yeah, that's a good point. I've been rereading the classic documents myself and realizing
that that's the spirit. It's very, very practical. The freedom to study, all the descriptions
inside the Kino Manifesto, the benefits are for scientific progress. And it talks about
the schools will not have to waste too much in order to acquire software and for teaching
and let the students understand what's happening. So there are multiple facets that are useful
to go back and read.
All right. So if there are no more questions...
Isabel.
Okay, go ahead.
Yeah, so Isabel doesn't have a question, but she actually shared exactly those discussions
around the verbs use and share. And thank you, Isabel, for sharing that.
Wonderful. Yes, thank you. So today we're going to start with publishing a forum wrap-up
on our blog. And we're going to be publishing the recording as usual and the slide deck
for this town hall. All right, everyone, thank you for joining. And we'll see you in two weeks
at a later time. So that is compatible, more compatible with the United States and West
Coast in general. And we'll keep on hammering on this. We'll have a new definition, new draft
at the next meeting. Thank you.