Hey folks, this week Aaron joins me and we talk with Simon and Stefano about the open
source AI definition.
That's something that was just minted and did not come a moment too soon.
It's a super interesting conversation and you don't want to miss it, so stay tuned.
This is Floss Weekly, episode 816, recorded Tuesday, January the 14th.
Open source AI.
Hey folks, it's time for Floss Weekly.
That's the show about free, libre, and open source software.
I'm your host, Jonathan Bennett, and we've got something that we've been teasing, it
seems like, for months now.
We're actually going to do a deep dive on the open source AI definition.
I've got a co-host that is not also part of the team that wrote the definition, and you'll
get this joke here in just a second.
But I've got Aaron with me.
Welcome Aaron.
Hey, thanks.
Thanks for having me.
Aaron is going to be sort of our AI optimist.
Is that how you described yourself?
Yeah, a little bit of an optimist.
I don't think it's taking over the world as quickly as people think, although it's doing
a lot of crazy things these days, it seems like.
Especially since I do use it on a daily basis for work and for other stuff I'm working on.
I tend to be, if there's one person in the room that's a little bit more optimistic,
I tend to be that person.
Yeah.
I've explained this on the show before.
My theory, working theory as of now, is that artificial intelligence falls into sort of
the same place that the crypto bubble did, but also the same place that the dot-com bubble
did.
And that is that it's a bubble, people are doing dumb things with it, trying to figure
out where it makes sense, but once the bubble bursts, it's going to stick around and it's
going to be something that sort of changes the way the world works indelibly.
That's obvious with dot-com and with cryptocurrency, we're still sort of in the process of figuring
out what that looks like.
I think it's a good analogy.
Yeah.
10 years from now, we'll kind of have to think back, what life was like before we had AI
just assuming that it was there and that we could ask it to do things.
It's the same difference of worldview that I have with my children, because I remember
before the internet was just always there, and my kids don't.
They've always been connected in some way, the household has been at least.
So it's just totally different.
All right.
Well, let's bring the guys on.
So we have both Simon Phipps, which that is the joke that I was making, that one of our
co-hosts is also a guest, but we've also got Stefano Maffoli.
And welcome guys.
And you two are the absolute experts, from what I can tell, in what it means for an AI
or for an LLM to be open source.
And let's, I guess, go to Stefano first and sort of taking that as the prompt to use an
LLM term.
Tell us what is all of this about?
Thanks for having me.
It's a pleasure to be here.
So what is open source AI?
Yes, let's start there.
It's really not that different from other open and open materials or artifacts that
we've been thinking of.
We need to have, we want to have freely free access, freely available access to all the
components and all the pieces that have made that artifact that you have received.
So it sounds, sounded really simple and almost trivial at the very beginning of the conversation
that we had almost three years ago.
But it was quickly, we quickly realized that all the paradigms that we were used to apply,
like the term source, just to get started with, didn't really match the technology.
And so we had to study a little bit the issue and we had a long process.
And the end result that I can, today, I can simply say that an open source AI is an AI
is a system.
It's a system that makes you, gives you a free availability to all the pieces that made
it.
And that includes the parameters.
So the results of the training, the code that does all the training, the code that produces
the training data set and the data itself when it's possible to distribute that.
And that's it.
Sounds simple.
I'm kind of thinking of the, and I know this is not exactly the same thing, the free software
and the OSI, those are two like overlapping, but at the same time, separate things.
Because I can't help but think of the five freedoms that the Free Software Foundation
talks about.
And that's the freedom to, when it comes to software, to run, to copy, to distribute,
to study, and then to change and improve a piece of software.
Are we kind of talking about the same thing when it comes to open source AI?
Or is it a similar sort of overlapping definition, the way that the OSI and the free software
definition?
Right.
Let me start from scratch because maybe the whole concept of open source AI definition
throws people off balance.
Because what we have done, the principles are really the same.
And in fact, if you look at the document that we have published, the OSI published at the
end of last year, the document really lists all those freedoms that you are talking about.
An AI, and we talk about systems, I can talk about it later, but the AI pieces, in other
words, something that produces an output, infers an output based on an input, needs
to be made available, needs to be able, you as a recipient of that system, need to be
able to study, to share it, to understand, to run it, to execute, to have those outputs
generated for you.
And you have to have also the freedom to modify it, change it, change how it works so that
others can enjoy the same freedoms that you have received.
So those principles are really the same.
What is really missing when you look at the definition of free software is that sentence
that says the precondition to exercise the freedom to study and the freedom to modify
the software is access to the source code.
And that's the words, those are the words that we were missing when we started looking
into AI specifically.
We didn't have a very good way, we didn't have any way of understanding how an AI system
can be really studied deeply and modified to change its behavior.
That's what we have researched for the past almost three years.
And what we came out with is a way to describe the equivalent of source code for software,
which in the open source definition, it's a definition point number two, it's called
the preferred form of making modifications to the code.
It's not just the source code, but also instructions on how to build dependencies of libraries
and versions and of course, language compilers and things like that.
All those things, knowledge about those pieces need to be shared in order to have access
to the source code.
That's interesting that you mentioned that.
I'm trying to find the exact, my notes on this, but there was a court case in, I believe
it was in Germany, here recently, where a router manufacturer used some code that was
under the GNU, the lesser public license of the LGPL.
And they got sued, not because the code itself was missing, but that extra stuff, like the
scripts needed for compilation and installation were missing from their source code repository.
And someone sued them and said, "No, you've got to provide this under the LGPL as well."
And I've commented before that every time the GPL, the LGPL, or any of the other, but
particularly those two, because they have the strongest copy left protections in them.
Every time they go to court, I'm kind of like, "I hope this turns out okay."
Because there's sort of this nightmare scenario that a court says, "No, no, no, this is a
contract, not a license, and it's not a valid contract."
Or there's various ways that that could go poorly.
But the German court found that, yes, not only is it a valid agreement, but it looks
like, reading between the lines here, it looks like a conclusion was come to before the court
case happened, but then the court case kind of rubber stamped it.
But the extra stuff was shared, and so it was confirmed that, yes, you can force someone
to share your compilation steps as a part of the source code license.
So that's kind of a...
It's good to see that confirmed in court.
Right.
It's really a fundamental component, a fundamental piece of the whole movement, is to have access
to the source code as defined as the preferred form in which a programmer would modify the
program.
Because obfuscated source code is not source code in the context of the open source definition.
Missing information about build scripts is really not open source code.
Yeah.
So what OSI has done is they've put together a definition for what open source AI...
What it has to be, like the minimum requirements.
I guess the next step then, or maybe this has already been done, is to begin to produce
OSI-compliant licenses for AI models.
Is that what's sort of next on the horizon?
I'm jumping way to the end with this question, but it just comes to mind, and I'm very curious.
We are, as OSI, we are ready to start evaluating licenses that do not cover squarely or exclusively
software.
Historically, the OSI has never taken into consideration licenses that cover, for example,
content, music, or databases, or other things that are not necessarily software.
But we are ready to evaluate other sorts of licenses against the open source definition,
the original one, the 10 points one.
There are efforts that we are aware of, of groups that are writing new documents.
They're not licenses technically, or they're not necessarily going to be licenses, but
they're terms of use and distributions.
There are other legal terms that are squarely new and that cover only specifically parameters,
data, and datasets, and code also, and they're all comprehensive, put together.
Yes, we're ready to do it, to review them.
This is another sort of strange, tangential question, but when we talk about open source
beyond just software, what immediately comes to mind is open source hardware.
Has OSI been involved with any of the open source hardware efforts, like defining what
that looks like, or has that been left to...
You want to jump in, Simon?
You have thoughts about open source hardware, don't you?
Yeah, well, so this came up before Steph's time.
There is another organization called Open Source Hardware Association, or OSHWA, and
OSHWA did what frequently happens in open source communities.
They gave us the great honor of using our logo as the basis for their logo, and in trademark
law, that's a big problem because that means you have to ask them very politely not to
do that.
And so at that time, which was about 10 years ago, 12 years ago, OSI and OSHWA had to reach
a legal agreement agreeing that they would deal with open source hardware and we would
deal with open source software.
As a consequence, OSI has never actually got into defining what open source means in the
world of hardware, in the same way that the Open Data Institute, ODI, talked about what
open data was, and OSI, again, has never got into defining what open data would be.
So the open source hardware definition...
Sorry, the open source AI definition is something of a departure because it's really OSI's first
move into something which is not pure software.
But I think it was a necessary thing to do because the boundary is such a series of dotted
lines that it's very...
Whereas with hardware, you can tell, well, you know, that's fairly clear.
Even actually open source hardware is fairly unclear.
One of the things I did when I was at Sun in 2006 was release all of the Spark designs
for the Spark silicon chips as open source under the GPLv2.
We called it OpenSpark and we released all of the Verilog designs because it turns out
that silicon chips are actually software as well.
They're just software that's compiled to silicon.
So the dividing lines are kind of hazy there as well.
But OSI as an organization doesn't harbor an opinion about open source hardware and
does not produce a definition in that region.
So can I jump in because I want to augment a little bit this part.
Like, why did we jump in?
Why did we feel the urge when hardware is not...
We haven't done the same for hardware.
I think what Simon just said, hardware is programmed by a human in some sense.
Like the chip design is done by a human and then it is compiled into silicon.
So you can see the mapping is pretty easily translated into source code being written
by a human compiled by a compiler into executable code.
For AI, what we noticed was that these systems look a lot like software, but they're not
programmed by humans.
They apprehend, they learn by themselves.
They have capabilities that emerge semi-randomly.
I'm not a technician, so I don't understand exactly why.
But what I've been told is that these things just start to execute and become...
They have new capabilities.
They're not programmed.
And the question is, therefore, how do you fix it?
If it's consistently creating issues or spitting out the wrong answers or whatever, you want
to fix it, you want to change it, you want to give it to others, what is it that you
actually want to ask?
It was easy for the hardware piece.
It's not that simple.
It wasn't easy.
It wasn't immediate for the AI piece.
That's what triggered the research.
Yeah, yeah.
That makes sense.
Before we get any further into this, we really ought to stop and define who we are talking
to.
And I know that both Stefano and Simon are involved with OSI, and I honestly could not
tell you what each of your exact roles are.
So let's go there next.
Start with Stefano, I guess.
Where are you in the OSI org chart?
I'm the executive director of the Open Source Initiative.
I started three years ago, and I'm in Italy now.
You're at the top of the chart.
No, the board is actually at the top.
Well, okay.
That's fair.
Simon, where do you fall in this?
Well, I was the president of OSI for about a decade, give or take the odd year here or
there.
And when I quit the board of directors, I had foolishly started some work on open standards
and public policy.
And there was nobody to carry that work on if I just ran away and disappeared.
So OSI hired me to be their director of policy.
And so for the last three years, I've been OSI's director of policy and standards.
And then we hired somebody else to look after US policy.
So I've been the director of EU policy and standards for the last year or so.
And I actually don't do anything at all to do with AI.
I look after making sure that things like the Cyber Resilience Act doesn't break open
source and making sure that the standards organizations create standards as if open
source was real.
Those are the two things that I actually do as the day job.
But one of the things I'm going to have to do now, Steph made a very clear statement
when he took over as executive director that OSI needed to do something about defining
open source in the context of AI.
And I'm now going to be taking that definition forward into Brussels and performing the necessary
education to help people understand that, for example, Meta's Lama AI system is not
open source because the licensing includes field of use restrictions and other insights
drawn from understanding what AI is and working out how we should legislate.
And that's necessary because people have already started writing legislation about
AI.
It may be really young, but there is already on the statute books in Europe the Artificial
Intelligence Act, and it contains within it an exception for open source AI.
So somebody had to define what open source AI means, and that was Steph.
No, no, no, no.
Wait a second.
It wasn't me who defined it.
I mean, that's…
Don't point this at me.
No, no.
Well, that's crucial because different from the Free Software definition and the open
source definition itself, this is not the work of a lone person, smart or otherwise,
coming out of their garage with the sacred text.
This was the process.
This process had to come from the community of AI developers, researchers, lawyers, copyright
holders, subjects of AI systems.
All of these different stakeholders had to be consulted, and we needed to find a definition
that matched what was actually happening in the space, providing some guidance, of course,
and bringing our expertise and experience from 30 plus years of Free Software experience.
But it was definitely not the work of my work.
We absolutely need now to go ask one of the AI image generators to generate the image
of Stefano carrying the tablets of stone out of his garage.
Yeah.
No, I think that the point Stef's making there is actually really important because
there has been the question asked, you know, what right has OSI got to define what open
source AI is?
And this then reads back to the open source definition itself, you know, what right has
OSI got to define what open source means?
And the answer is that it's actually the OSI's role is to collect together the consensus
on what it means.
That's what we did with the open source definition.
There was a definition that came out of Debian that became the open source definition, and
over a fairly short space of time, it became obvious that the consensus of the global community
was that the open source definition was the canonical explanation of how you can tell
that a license is an open source license.
And now what Stef has done for the last few years is he has run this exhausting global
program where he's held public meetings, he's hired facilitators, he's hired authors and
writers and what's happened is he's asked AI experts and open source experts and people
who work in social development, he said to them, "What is open source AI?"
And over that time, he's gradually evolved what the answer is, not by being clever and
working it out for himself, but by identifying the consensus of this huge crowd of people.
And that means that the definition is really a consensus definition in many ways.
Now, because the field is younger, there are some dissenting voices, but you go out and
ask anybody who actually works in AI on open source, nine out of ten of them, and I can
tell you the name of the tenth, but nine out of ten of them will tell you that this definition
is pretty much right.
They might want to nuance some of the words or some of the concepts, and indeed, OSI is
putting in place a plan to evolve the definition to a V1.1 or a V2 in the future.
But this really is a consensus definition rather than an imposed definition from Steph.
There you go.
He's got it.
There's Steph with the open source definition coming out of his garage.
That's great.
I'll just stop here.
I think we could take a moment and just say, on some level, that is impressive.
That's pretty amazing that we could do that, that we could go, "Hey, here's a cool idea.
Let's have a machine draw a picture for us," and it comes out that well.
It is cool that we live in these times where we could do that.
Yeah.
Can you imagine?
Do you remember when you had to go to a bookstore to order a book?
I still enjoy going to bookstores, but yes, point taken.
Point taken.
Yeah.
Hey, I wanted to dig in, if I could, a little bit more into the nuances of what we're dealing
with, because one of the things that really interested me, two things.
One is that there could be a dependency on something that lives outside the source code
for the thing to work, as a problem statement.
Then the other, that it may have self-generation capabilities and how do you license them.
I'm just curious if what made me think initially was about, yesterday, I discovered and started
playing around with Whisper from OpenAI.
I'm not sure if you're familiar with it, but it's a text to speech translation tool.
It's under the MIT license, so you can go do whatever you want with it under that license.
But I'm just curious if there's some examples of things that are already out there where
those two things are problematic already.
Do two things that are problematic?
Sorry, I wasn't sure what you mean.
An example of some AI tool or AI LLM or something that's out there that is either self-generating,
do you have an example of something like that that could be problematic?
Or the other one is where it's totally dependent on things that are outside of what could be
covered under a license or what could be considered open source and thereby invalidates the idea.
Do you mean self-generating as in Skynet?
That programs itself and improves?
I don't know if I'm going that far, but something where, I think you were talking about it,
Simon, where it would be difficult to categorize what was covered under there because it wasn't
necessarily programmed by a human.
All right.
Okay, now I understand.
So the case of Whisper is interesting because the license is extremely permissive.
We're very familiar with it and it covers the parameters, like the weights, the trained
weights of that engine.
What we don't know about Whisper is how it's been built, how the training happened, what
kind of data sources they use to have those results.
Those pieces are missing.
And that is why we wouldn't consider Whisper an open source AI, despite the fact that the
weights are openly and freely available.
Because what we have defined in the document, the open source AI definition, what's defined
in there that is brand new is the definition of preferred form of making modifications
to an AI system.
If you want to change the behavior of Whisper, sure, you can fine tune it.
You can add layers to it or you can modify manually some of the, or randomly poke at
the weights themselves inside the matrix.
But you will have a much easier time if you knew what kind of data went in there, have
a full list of it.
If you had the training code in order to understand how that training was done, you had all the
code that was used to generate the training data set.
Because training data, I mean, the original data needs to be massaged, needs to be filtered,
needs to be deduplicated, tokenized, etc. before it can be fed into the training machine.
So all of these pieces are required to understand, to have a fully, to have access to preferred
form of making modifications to the code, sorry, to the system, to the AI.
That's the new thing that's in the definition.
Yeah.
So would it be fair to say then that that particular model, some of it is still a black
box.
You don't know where it came from.
It's just you have this black box kind of artifact that's part of it.
And to make something an open source AI, we want to get rid of all of those black boxes
and be able to see inside of all of them.
Yep.
That's exactly.
Or at least know where they came from.
So you can't, because some of the things that you do to make an AI are ephemeral, they are
transient.
What matters more is that you've got an adequate description of how the AI acquired its knowledge,
that somebody else who is sufficiently experienced could take your recipe and do the same thing.
They may not need exactly the same data, but they do need the same recipe that you had
for how to train it on the health data of everyone in an emergency room for a month
with these inputs from the equipment and with these sign offs from the patients and so on.
An expert can take that description and produce the same transparent box.
They don't necessarily need all the exact same data to do that.
So that's a corner case.
As the general case, yes, indeed.
We don't want any black boxes.
We want to know what they were shown in order to be populated.
And I suppose that's sort of a hinge point here, right?
There are certain, medical is a really good example, right?
There are certain times where you would want an LLM that has been trained on medical data
and the idea of releasing all of that medical source data is just, it's a complete non-starter.
Like legally you just cannot do it.
But you would want that LLM to still be as open as possible and ideally be able to fall
under the open source definition of AI.
And so that's kind of the corner case that's been the sticking point maybe through all
of this.
Honestly, a lot of the corner cases that have been circulating, we must wait and see.
A lot of the conversations that we're having about these corner cases require new science
or they may become obsolete tomorrow.
A lot of the ideas that we had two or three years ago about the technology, specifically
LLMs, are starting to go away or are becoming less relevant.
So before we talk about corner cases, I would really love to see more work and more analysis
of the actual good examples that we have today of groups, research institutions, nonprofit
hackers that are really releasing datasets with full instructions on how to build them,
full code releases.
They're making attempts at creating platforms, including hardware descriptions of clusters,
training clusters, to build AI themselves.
All of these examples, the virtuous examples, are the ones that we are losing track of.
Everyone talks about LLMA.
And then on the other side, there is a lot of other groups that are releasing very, very
compelling technology with full access to all of the underlying components and pieces.
So respecting the concept of preferred form of making modifications to an AI system.
Have you gotten a decent bit of contact from the industry?
People saying, "We acknowledge the work that you've done and we would like to make changes
to make our license or model or whatever open source compliant."
Has there been some reach out?
Other than the industry, the most productive conversations we had and collaboration we
had, we had collaboration with industry, large corporations, small corporations, startups,
and research institutions, and nonprofit groups.
The nonprofit groups are the ones who have endorsed more happily the definition as it
came out, because it really supports that idea of creating a framework for collaboration,
a shared understanding of what are the principles of furthering the science, furthering the
knowledge on how systems have been built, how you train, and therefore how to improve
without having to reinvent the wheel.
But from the industry perspective, because of the technology, the way it is built, the
way of its complexity, the fact that it has to take into account multiple layers of the
companies themselves, like they go from the data scientists, but even on the legal departments,
just to give you an example, in the legal department for software, copyright experts
and maybe patent experts are sufficient.
All of a sudden for AI components and pieces, you end up having to involve the whole expertise
of the firm, plus consultants from outside, because you have to have export regulation,
the privacy regulation across multiple countries and worlds.
It becomes a lot more complex.
Companies generally haven't been very happy with the way the definition came out.
It's too restrictive for their point of view.
Yeah, and then you've got people on the other side that don't think it's restrictive enough,
I'm sure.
Right.
Yes, there are some groups who say, yes, we should be asking for more.
The thing that comes to mind with that is that there's nothing in this that would prevent
someone from writing a more restrictive license.
I would imagine that you could write a more restrictive license and it would still be
considered an open source AI license under these guidelines.
So someone could come along and try to bring the idea of copy left into this.
It's the open source AI definition.
Someone could come along and try to bring in a Fero genie public license to where if
anyone touches it, even on a website, they need to have a way to be able to get the source.
I would imagine that it would be possible to write these now.
They're not going to get a whole lot of uptake, but it would be possible to write these license
and to release something, to release an LLM under a less restrictive or a copy left license.
Right?
That's an option, isn't it?
It is an option and it's a conscious one.
I don't think it's a negative one, to be honest.
I don't classify the GNU GPL or the LGPL, the Fero GPL as restrictive licenses.
They're permissive.
They just add requirements that you may want or not.
They're not really restrictive.
So in the same vein, I do think that it's a good idea to have the possibility to have
legal frameworks, legal documents that would let someone like a user downstream to say,
"Hey, you're coming up with this system is spitting out this output.
I'm asking for a mortgage and it's consistently telling me that I'm not qualified to have
it.
But why?
Can I get access to all the instructions of how it's been built?
Can I have my experts review it?"
That kind of stuff is good for society.
And in general, let me put it also in the other way.
Think about the fact that we collectively have created a lot of content that has been
crawled and spidered and archived into repositories like Common Crawl or the Internet Archive
or our code is into Software Heritage and GitHub repositories.
That content is now can be used and is being used to train wonderful machines that create
images and spit out code.
Do we want as a society to have the possibility to say, "Hey, you're using my code.
I want the parameters to go back to me under the same conditions I gave the code to you
or my pictures."
I don't think it's wrong to think about it that way.
It's a choice that we need to allow.
Yeah.
And that actually kind of touches on a much bigger question with the way AI works right
now.
And there's this sort of legal theory that AI is putting data into a large language model.
It is so transformative that it pretty much removes the original copyright.
You put it in and the language model trains on it but does not inherit the copyright of
the training data.
That's essentially the way that it's being used.
You look at something like Copilot on GitHub.
It is trained on a whole bunch of GPL code.
But then you can say to Copilot, "Write me code," and there's no expectation that the
code that Copilot writes carries the GPL license.
So just as an example, that's the sort of thing that I mean.
And I know that there are some legal theories out there that that's not going to survive.
Now, we talked last week with a lawyer and his comment was, "The genie is out of the
bottle."
And I don't think we can ever put the genie back in the bottle.
But it is interesting to think that there is sort of this push for we should inherit
some of the copyright of the original training data.
I guess, what is your thought on that?
Do you think that's a reasonable thing to think about or is the genie just entirely
out of the bottle and there's no way to go back?
I don't have an easy answer.
It's a complicated and nuanced conversation.
And I have a dual approach to this.
On one hand, first of all, these theories, they are being proven in American courts.
And I'm saying American courts specifically because there are different laws.
The copyright law is fairly uniformly applied around the world, but some things are different
in the United States, in Europe, in Britain, China, etc.
So yes, the genie, I guess the lawyer may have been referring to the theory that has
been proven by Google Scholar, Google Books actually.
If you remember, was it 10 plus years ago, Google started scanning books and making them
available, search available through the content of the books.
They were buying the books on paper, scanning them, doing character recognition and offering
those as search engine products.
And Google got sued by the American Publisher Association and Google won that case because
the judge said basically that what Google was doing was not damaging the copyright holders
and also was transformative work.
And so I believe that Copilot and GitHub and Microsoft are building their cases, their
defenses against the lawsuits pretty much on similar theories.
We'll see if that survives the courts.
But there is a different, there is another angle that I keep on thinking, that the fact
that collectively we have created content, collectively the society has created content,
every blogger, every podcaster, we are creating content, we're making it available under permissive
licenses like Creative Commons licenses and others.
And we're telling the world, use it, do whatever you want with it.
And now if we start saying individually, like, you can use it, but not for training, or you
can use it not for training under these conditions, etc., then all of a sudden the larger copyright
holders, the larger corporations who can license content from content providers, large aggregators,
etc., they will have an edge.
They will have an advantage because they have the money and the resources to get access
to large quantities of data.
And groups like that are building their systems openly and freely and they want to have access
to freely available content, they will have to jump through hoops and license individually
for millions of people and copyright holders.
So it's a more complicated question in my mind than what it looks like at surface.
With some of those being more complicated questions and the way that all of this is
still being developed and changing so much, do you foresee the possibility of changing
the open source AI definition?
Do you think there's going to be some updates to it where you go back and you say, this
needed to be stronger or this doesn't need to be in there?
Absolutely.
I think we need to really pay attention to what's happening in the space, in the field.
What are not only the technologies, how they're evolving and changing, but also how the developers
and developers of AI, builders of AI, builders of datasets, how they're behaving, how they're
adjusting their tooling, their expectations, how they're releasing.
Where is the collaboration happening and how?
What's the potential for collaboration?
Where is the safety coming from?
All of these habits, we need to watch them.
Consider the fact that the open source definition appeared more than a decade, almost two decades
after the free software definition appeared.
And the free software definition was basically a statement of principles and a manifesto.
The open source definition is more like a checklist.
What we have today, a checklist that was based on 20 years of experience.
So we're basically watching the space as it evolves.
More systems are released, more datasets are released, more experience we gain, and we
can generalize from there.
What we have right now in the open source AI definition version one is a stake in the
ground.
It's basically like a conversation starter, if you want.
The place that we can use, like someone was saying, to have conversations with policymakers,
with researchers and developers, with corporations, to say, "These are the principles that came
out of a large conversation.
Where do you disagree?
What do you think is wrong?"
We keep collecting that information.
And we're also going to keep watching the data space because that's where I think that
we need to pay more attention to.
We have right now really been talking about open data as if it's the only and most important
thing that we have.
But the open data alone is not sufficient to describe the complexity of training datasets
and training data.
There's more than one to that.
>> Yeah, sure.
>> So I've got a kind of a reverse question.
We talked about this a little bit when Jonathan was talking about protecting creators' rights
or protecting the rights of the people whose data, whether it was images or whatever kind
of data that was used for training.
I'm reading through the definition now.
Because one of the nice things about open source licenses, and we've got to probably
also distinguish between the definition and the license, but the license does provide
protection at various levels, depending on which license you choose, for the creator
of the software in that case, to make sure that they get credit, for example, as the
code is copied by others or used in other projects, et cetera.
Is there also that same protection in the definition, or is that left up to the various
licenses that will come that meet the definition to provide that type of protection?
>> I think it will have to be coming from the legal terms as they get developed.
>> Yeah.
So keep in mind that the credit to the author is a license term.
It's one that's permitted by the open source definition, but it's not actually required.
Actually a little while ago, somebody, I think it was Jonathan, talked about restrictive
licenses.
There are no restrictive open source licenses.
>> I knew that was coming.
>> You knew it was coming.
>> Simon's had his bee in his bonnet ever since I said that.
I'm like, "Oh no, he's going to say it."
>> Yeah, yeah.
There are no restrictive open source licenses because a restriction is something that you
have to negotiate removal of.
And open source licenses do include conditions.
And so I say you can use this license if blah, but that's not a restriction, that's a condition.
A restriction is you guys who don't have white hair, you can't use this software.
That's a restriction.
And the only way you can get rid of that restriction is to go to the person who owns the copyright
and ask them to waive the restriction, probably in exchange for some money.
So all open source licenses are permissive because they contain no restrictions.
They only contain conditions.
And credit to the authors is a condition, and it's an optional condition.
There are open source licenses that don't include that condition.
And so if there are going to be those sorts of conditions placed on open source AIs, they
will have to be licensed terms because they're not predicated by the open source AI definition
itself.
>> That's a good point.
The other question I had as you guys were talking, was there ever any thought put into
this, or maybe it's just outside the bounds and it doesn't apply because it's too high
level of intelligence itself, right?
So what happens when we have an AI that, I don't want to go all the way to sentience,
but I mean, as these AI tools and things become more and more intelligent and able to do things
on their own, was there any thought in terms of the definition into we need to somehow
accommodate that or think about that, or do the rights change at that point when AIs become
or approach sentience?
>> That's got to be your question because I don't believe that can ever happen.
I'm a weak AI guy.
I read Marvin Minsky in the '80s, and I believe that society of mind does not lead to emergent
intelligence.
I believe that the evolution of machine learning only goes to just below that point.
But it's got to be his question.
>> My question?
>> Your question.
>> I'll take it.
We have this sticker that says, "Skynet won't be open source."
>> I love that.
>> But it's just a working theory right now.
>> Oh, Aaron, I think that is a great question, but I think that's probably also a great answer.
>> Yeah, that's pretty funny.
>> All right.
Let's see.
Where do we want to go from here?
Simon told me where one of the bodies was buried.
Do I want to dig around in that?
Simon's like, "I don't care.
I know, Simon."
There's this thought that in the ... There are exceptions for where sometimes all of
the data, for whatever reason, cannot be provided.
We talked about the medical exception, and there are some others.
Is it sort of a challenge to explain the open source definition because those exceptions
are so prominent?
Are we going to maybe see a version in the future that puts the exceptions sort of in
the back half of that section?
>> We might.
Okay, let me put it that way.
If I started today rewriting everything from scratch with the help of a few people without
having to go through the whole process and interviewing hundreds of people, et cetera,
and traveling the world, blah, blah, blah, probably the wording could change.
But honestly, I think that we are panicking a little bit, and we need to take a little
bit of a step back.
We're going to release next week a paper about data, specifically about the issue of data.
Because if you put things away ... Like I said, an open source AI is one that gives
you all the means to understand exactly how it's been built and be able to build something
that is working exactly like the one that you have received.
Knowing that software is ... We have decades of experience with, we have understood it
well enough that we have now reproducible builds, or at least a theory of it.
We can really take source code and rebuild a binary bit by bit exactly the same as, exactly
equivalent to the one that we have received.
It took us decades to get there.
With AI, with LLMs, with this sort of neural networks technology, we still don't have the
science to do the same thing.
You take ... I've been told by a notable AI developer that releases everything in open
source that they tried to take the same dataset, take one dataset, feed it through ... I had
an ambulance.
I live near a hospital, so ambulances every now and then.
I forgot about this issue.
No problem.
Okay.
They had this one dataset, and they were feeding the same dataset through two different pipelines
into the same cluster split into halves.
These two streams would produce two different models.
It's not easy.
It's not a solved problem on how to replicate a training so that you get an exact, identical
model, model weights.
So knowing that this is different than software, and this is a very young discipline, we need
to take a little bit of a step back.
We need to really understand the issue of data is that the issue of data is not going
to be solved quickly.
It requires much deeper understanding than what I was talking about.
Now thinking of open data versus not, and I give you a very quick example.
I was talking to a developer who's been thinking about building a dataset that is purely made
of copyright-free or unencumbered material, content, and they were adamant on using public
domain movies only.
They stepped into the public domain issue, which is in the United States, public domain
for a movie is 70 years after the death of the director.
In France, a movie goes into public domain 70 years after the last person who worked
on the movie dies.
It's impossible to calculate.
So a dataset that looks like it's built on public domain material in the United States
may not be in public domain in Europe or in France or in Germany.
Completely different story.
We need to get a little bit, take a step back and say, "Okay, this is different than source
code.
We need more.
We need to talk about changing policies, maybe have new laws or build new habits or change
the technology."
Right?
All of these questions are all open.
All of these possibilities are open.
One of the things as we get towards wrapping up, this is something that's kind of been
in the back of my mind the whole time.
When we talk about open source software, generally all it takes is a computer to be able to make
changes and compile.
But when it comes to open source AI, just the barrier to entry to really play with these
things is much higher.
In some cases you can do it on a CPU, in some cases a GPU, but these rather on the edge
AI models, multiple GPUs to be able to do anything interesting with it.
I guess that doesn't really change anything as far as what the open source definition
says for it.
But surely that changes things for how accessible, on a practical level, how accessible it is
to be able to actually get into and mess with some of these things.
Yeah.
There is definitely something that changed.
The scale of some of these training is prohibitive.
But again, in a couple of years, I've seen there's been some difference.
And small language models and other technologies, they seem to be making things more accessible.
Like if OpenAI, the company, trains on clusters that are worth billions of dollars, there
are smaller groups that are doing something on tens of thousands of dollars and getting
similar results.
I'm not saying that they can build something as powerful of OpenAI as GPT and being able
to respond that quickly.
But these models, like Mozilla is doing something extremely fascinating with smaller models
running inside the browser, even a mobile.
So training versus execution, that's another big conversation.
It's early.
It's really early.
We need to give it time.
Oh, yeah.
We are definitely in the...
Well, even faster than Moore's Law.
So there's this idea with early computing that every, what was it, 16 months, the computing
power would double, something like that.
And we're moving even faster than that with AI at this point.
So give it a year or two, and who knows where we'll be as far as the accessibility part
of it goes.
Yeah, it definitely speaks to the reason why something like this is needed, in my opinion.
Even though I'm an optimist, I'm not a skeptic.
I'm not saying we don't need any of these protections and definitions for things.
Speaking of definitions, I'm kind of curious, you've been saying it's early days.
This is 1.0, the definition, right, is what's out today.
By the way, if people are looking for it, it's on, I think it's opensource.org/ai if
they want to check it out.
So definitely go there and have a read, as I've been doing, as we've been talking here.
But it's still early days.
I'm kind of curious, for example, I only see really two definitions in version 1.0.
One is of an AI system, and the other one, and these are definitions in the definition,
but one is of an AI system, and then the other one is for machine learning.
And of course, AI is lots of different things, right, like LLMs and different types of things.
So I'm kind of curious, where do you go from here?
Will there be other definitions that you know you already have to add?
Are there things that, you know, what's the roadmap here of the definition?
Where do we go?
Yeah, very good point.
So why did we include the definition of an AI system in there is because we needed to
have an anchor to understand what we were talking about, what we were defining.
Three years ago, it wasn't really clear what we were talking about, like what's different
in here?
And so we used the definition of the OECD, the Organization for Economic Cooperation
and Development, which is what's been used also in the Artificial Intelligence Act, very
similar definition.
And why we're targeting machine learning specifically to talk about the preferred form to make modifications
is because the new LLMs, the ones that require training, they have the dependency of data,
etc., the ones that learn how to magically, those are machine learning systems.
So we said, okay, we don't want to define the preferred form for everything, forever,
at every time.
Let's focus on what we know today that needs clarifications.
And that's where we got it from.
Where do we go from here?
In the next year, year and a half, we will need to understand better how groups like
LLM360, Eleuther AI, the Allen Institute for AI, Falcon Foundation, TII, and other groups
like this are LLM France.
These groups that are releasing software parameters and datasets as much as possible to the
commons, into the open source communities, to understand how they operate and how they
work and what they need in terms of legal frameworks, legal documents, opinions, and
generalize from there.
How soon do you think we'll see the first license that is OSI approved specifically
for AI?
I know that the Linux Foundation is working on a new license specifically for that.
I would love to see even the current ones that would not pass definition, but I would
love to see the debate, like the ones, like the responsible AI license.
I would love to see one of those being submitted, but also would love to see submitted the data
licenses, for example, like the CDLA, I think it's called, from the Linux Foundation.
They have developed a couple of licenses that are suitable for datasets.
It would be a nice exercise to start getting the habits, but also understanding where the
open source definition terms require clarifications.
Yeah.
All right.
Very interesting.
Good stuff.
We have basically reached the bottom of the hour.
Aaron, was there anything that you desperately wanted to ask before we wrap?
Yeah, I've got two and they weren't immediately applicable to the discussion, but I'm curious
about their thoughts on this.
So I'm kind of curious if you have any thoughts on what other open source projects can do
besides getting more developers involved to incorporate some AI tools into other open
source programs or existing open source programs.
And the ones that come to mind for me, because I use them all the time, of course, are like
Inkscape and GIMP.
I find myself using Photoshop more than I want to these days because I just need a tool
that can quickly remove the background and generate a forest behind my image or something.
And they do that really well.
And I'm just concerned that people will stop using these great tools that have been in
the community for so long because now they're missing this AI functionality because they
don't have the development bench to go build it.
Any thoughts on that?
That's interesting.
Yeah.
I love to see Collabora and LibreOffice get some summarization stuff.
Mozilla is doing some very interesting work on that front.
I think it's just a matter of time to get, on the one hand, developers with skills and
understanding these tools and how to do things like reducing the size of a model, like something
that looks really gigantic that works only on a hardcore and high-level GPUs to make
it run on CPUs, for example, so that it can be distributed freely by Debian.
But also we need a little bit...
Speaking of Debian, I think that we need to understand a little bit better what the legal
frameworks are, because I don't think that Debian is going to be very happily distributing
Whisper, for example, or something based on Whisper.
So we will have to have more conversations about that.
This reluctance or maybe, let me put it that way, maybe we need to think about how we're
going to be solving that challenge between, "Oh my God, this thing is stealing my content.
It's stealing my stuff."
And, "Oh my God, this is useful.
I would use it."
Or, "My friends are using it."
So there's that tension in there that we need to resolve.
And you had one more, Aaron?
Yeah, one more quick one, and maybe this can be part of the wrap-up instead of our usual
questions, but I'm kind of curious what your favorite AI tool is that you're using at the
moment.
Oh, that's a really good one.
I really don't use them that much, but we do use Google Workspace at USI, and Gemini
is included in it.
So every now and then, the temptation is to go and check what Gemini does.
Simon?
I'm not knowingly using any AIs at the moment.
I do go and kick the tires on them every now and then.
So like Steph, I kick the tires on Gemini because you do that without needing to buy
tokens to put in the slot machine.
I'm going to be quite interested.
So to go back to Aaron's earlier question, the biggest challenges with doing that are
indeed the belief that the copyleft is carried into the statistical model.
And personally, I'm of the view that the courts are going to find that ridiculous.
They have done so far in each attempt in the US.
We've really not seen very much happening elsewhere.
But until we get over the idea that the copyleft has been carried into the model, we're not
going to see anybody then using the model in some software.
And I think that's a big obstacle to seeing AI ending up in open source tools.
I also think that we're going to see another generational change in AI coming about where
the technology is going to be made differently and deployed differently to the way that it
is now.
And I think that quite likely to wait for those cool things to make their way in to
open source tools is going to need to wait for that.
Having said that, there are already AI hooks in an awful lot of places.
I don't know if you've realized this.
You look in Home Assistant, for example.
So I do use Home Assistant.
There's a great big AI hook in the middle of Home Assistant so that it can do voice
recognition.
There are great big hooks in Mastodon for going and doing AI translation.
So actually, the question you asked, when are we going to see open source supporting
AI, it's already happening.
But the way it's happening at the moment is by providing hooks to go use external systems
rather than by building the capability into the product itself.
There's a lot of that already happening.
But as a community or a community of communities, we've got some very hard conversations to
have sometime soon if we're going to see freedom respecting software do AI rather than just
call out to freedom non-respecting software that does AI.
The agentic model, I guess, as it's known.
It seems like that's a big word that's thrown around a lot these days.
To your point, Simon, there about whether, and it's the same question that I asked about
the kind of the inherence of the copy left when it's part of the training data and how
that's gone in the courts.
I imagine what we're eventually going to see is essentially a test.
There's going to be a legal test that says, if, and I don't know for sure what it's going
to look like, but if you can create a prompt that gives you this many words in a row that
matches the input, then you have inherited the copyright from the input.
It may not be exactly that, but I have to assume that there's going to be some court
case that's going to give us a test that sort of everybody can agree on.
Because obviously you could just copy a file through a black box AI that doesn't do anything,
call it AI.
I mean, there was a cartoon to that effect, wasn't there?
Someone tried to do that with Beatles music years ago, and they ran the Beatles records
through their Sonic Maximizer.
And I don't know if they even use the AI buzzword or not, but they tried to make the point that,
"Oh, this transforms it so much, it's a completely new work."
And of course, the courts completely shot that down.
But there's got to be a happy medium in there somewhere.
So I expect that at some point there's going to be an agreed upon test of some sort, that
here's the guideline for where your AI is transformative enough that you're not inheriting
that copyright.
Yeah.
Well, I'm not going to second guess it.
But as an accident of what I do for a living, I know a lot of lawyers, and I have yet to
meet one that thinks that the statistical model is a derivative work of the source data.
Now maybe that's going to change sooner or later.
But at the moment, if you want to go make a court case that some AI has copied your
work, it's going to be a really tough case to even get legal counsel to defend you on.
And I draw your attention to the fact there's a lot of no win, no fee work going on in this
area.
But Steph disagrees.
I can see him waving.
No, I don't disagree.
I think that it's a less interesting question for me, because the more interesting question
is should it be considered a derivative or not?
And I think that we should be running that exercise a little bit more consciously and
think about the consequences of either way.
Like either way, what happens and what's the worst outcome possible in either path?
And maybe we can even influence courts.
But we should do it with consciousness.
It's not just the gut reaction, say, "Hey, that code is mine.
I should be getting something, remuneration for copilot's capabilities," for example.
Or DALI, the fact that it reproduces works that look like mine.
I need to get compensated.
All right?
Should you?
What happens if we do?
Yeah, there's a whole...
We do not have time to go down this rabbit hole, but there is an entire rabbit hole about
whether it's a good thing that we can have a machine produce an image and we're no longer
paying an artist to do it.
That's its own entire conversation that, yeah, I think is important to think about.
But as I said, we are not going down that rabbit hole today.
Maybe someday in the future.
I am required to get a couple of final questions in myself, and that is, what are each of your
favorite text editor and scripting language?
Stefano?
TISC.
Yeah, it's passed on the scripting language.
I really don't code anymore.
I played with Bash and Python, but right now I'd probably ask a copilot, a chat GPT or
something to do it for me.
Is there a text editor in there?
Text editors, VI, Vim is one that I usually fire up when I do some quick stuff, but I'm
not really a text editor guy.
And I'm very disloyal to my text editors.
I've been using different ones throughout my career.
The one I fire up most often at the moment is Nano.
But hey, when I was IBM, we were using E. I used to work on a word processor called
– I worked with WordStar and WordPerfect back in the day.
And I've got everything loaded on various computers around here.
Scripting language is more interesting, though.
I'm doing it all in YAML at the moment because I'm doing all this home assistant stuff.
Yeah.
You consider that a scripting language?
I'm not sure that yet another markup language really counts as a scripting language, but
– And yet I'm programming the whole of my home assistant deployment using YAML pages.
All right.
That's fair, I suppose.
Thank you guys both so much for being here.
We appreciate it.
And Andrew, a fascinating dive into some of the questions and some of the answers about
open source AI.
Appreciate it, man.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
All right.
Man, what do you think?
Yeah, I mean, it is – I'm glad it's being done.
I feel like with other areas in tech, we kind of missed the boat.
Open source hardware and some of those other things.
Social media, for example.
It feels like now there's all this concern around social media.
It's like, well, where were you five, ten years ago, right?
And people could see some of the problems that it was going to have.
And at least with AI moving so fast, I'm glad that somebody at least is thinking about
these things and coming up with these definitions because otherwise, you know, who knows what
could happen, right?
And like Stefano said, we need to have the discussion, right?
Even if you don't like 1.0 of the definition that's out today, talk about it.
Have the discussion.
It's what we've always done going back to early days of networking, for example.
Think of all the discussions and all the groups that were around to try to define how we're
going to make this thing work, right?
Without discussing it, you're just opening the door for not necessarily bad things to
happen but unwanted things to happen.
And so yeah, I'm glad it's taking place.
So I think it was Simon that told us something that absolutely terrifies me and that is that
in Europe, there are laws that refer to open source AI and they refer to that with there
being no definition for what open source AI is.
And it's like that encapsulates the central problem that many of us have with like overregulation
and just governments stepping into things that they really don't understand.
That's humorous.
And all of that to say, I'm glad that there are people working on this and, you know,
people that sort of have an idea what they're doing.
Exactly.
People that understand these things instead of politicians who don't, just coming up with
random things that they throw darts on the wall and come up with sometimes.
Yes.
All right.
You have anything-
Hey, we should talk about our favorite AI tools that were used.
What's your favorite, Jonathan?
What are you using?
So about the only one that I use these days is when you Google something, sometimes you'll
get like the AI, and I guess it's Gemini, right?
So you'll get like the AI answer to your question.
And that is getting to the point to where it's useful.
I do not consider it trustworthy, but it is useful.
And then I've done a little bit similar to what you did with like, here's a prompt, give
me an image that looks like this.
I've done some playing around with that with varying degrees of success.
Sometimes the prompts can be, if you're good at writing the prompts, sometimes you can
get really good results.
And then sometimes you ask for something a little esoteric or off the beaten path and
you just get weird results, which I guess is kind of fun too, but not really what you
were looking for.
Yeah.
What tool do you make most use of?
I've probably got to pick Jack GPT.
I mean, I do pay for the plus license and I use it multiple times a day for personal
and business use.
And it impresses me more than it disappoints me, that's for sure.
So I use it to summarize notes from meetings.
So I'll have like hour and a half long meetings, get the transcription, feed it into chat GPT,
say can you summarize this?
And it does a great job.
And there are other tools of course, that do that.
I use it as part of my YouTube channel for sometimes creating thumbnails, images.
If I just can't find anything that I'm allowed to use sometimes, I'll use it for that.
And of course I use it for, like I said, removing background on things, just things, shortcuts
that I can get it to do that would take me 10 times as long.
I can say, look, just like generating that image today, for example, of the guy coming
out of the garage with the open source tablets.
Right.
Yeah, that was pretty good.
Yeah.
So things like that, that you can do just as time savers really is the biggest way that
I use it today.
I think I'm a little gun shy on using AI because I write for Hackaday and I do not want there
to ever be even the appearance of crossing those streams.
So every word that I write for Hackaday always comes directly from me.
The most an AI is ever involved with is Google will tell me that I misspelled something and
that's it.
And we've had some conversations internally at Hackaday and that's pretty much the conclusion
we've come to as well.
I think there was once one of our writers used an AI image as like the headline image
and we kind of got shut down internally.
It's like, let's not do this unless we decide that we're going to be okay with this.
And so I'm pretty careful to not use much AI just kind of because of that.
Even as a research tool though for the background for the piece that you're writing?
About the only thing is if I Google something.
It'll come up with the Google summary of what it thinks the answer is.
And again, I've kind of found out that that's not necessarily always trustworthy.
Sometimes it'll tell you the exact, now it's getting better obviously, but sometimes it'll
tell you the exact opposite or it'll pull something from an article that's not really
about the thing that you asked about.
So even then I'm pretty careful to go in and try to find actual hard sources.
I use it for research and I tell it to give me sources and then I can go take a look at
the sources and validate.
Yeah.
And that's apparently a really useful hack.
You make your AI assistant way more accurate if you tell it.
It's kind of like with people.
You ask them, "Hey, what's the answer to this?" and give me your source.
Well, we're going to work a little bit harder to make sure we give you the right answer
if we also have to give you a source.
Apparently that works for AI too.
Exactly.
Yeah.
All right.
So where do you guys go?
Well, I mentioned the YouTube channel.
Check it out.
I've got two channels.
That's important because I've actually been publishing more on the second channel than
on the first.
So there's RetroHackShack of course, which is the main channel.
I do more history videos there, more big projects there, and they come out a little bit less
frequently and then there's also RetroHackShack After Hours.
And the last two videos I did there, one was a repair on a 1990s motherboard where the
keyboard didn't work.
I couldn't get any keyboards to work, so that was a short one.
And you can go watch that one and figure out what happened.
And then the one before that was, oh, I do a lot of e-waste stuff on the second channel.
I find stuff at e-waste and just bring it home and start the camera and I go through
and figure out on the fly what it is, what's working, what's not.
And so that's a lot of fun too.
So check out both channels and hopefully there's still people out there that like vintage
computers.
Oh, definitely.
I know I watched that last one about the keyboard not working and I won't give it away, but
I will say the component that you replaced, I would have looked at and probably just thought
it was a weird resistor.
So that's actually a pretty useful bit of knowledge for me to add to my own fix-it toolkit.
Right, right.
And I would say probably it wasn't long ago, 10 years ago, I would have been in the same
boat.
I would have been like, "Oh, what's that thing?"
But so yeah, it's fun and that's what's fun about it is you learn about what things are
and how they work and how they used to work.
Yes, absolutely.
Absolutely.
All right.
So next week, we've actually got something really interesting.
I believe, yeah, we're talking with, according to the calendar, hopefully it's right, we
have another Stefano.
We're talking with Stefano Zaccaroli about the Software Heritage Group and that's going
to be a lot of fun.
And then the week after that, hopefully we're going to have someone from CIQ to talk about
Rocky, which we've talked all Malinx.
I figure we might as well talk Rocky.
They were there at the very beginning as well.
And then the week after that, we're talking Thunderbird.
So all kinds of fun stuff coming up.
You don't want to miss it.
If you want to follow me and my work, of course, there is Hackaday.
We appreciate Hackaday being the home of Floss Weekly.
I've got the security column that goes live pretty much every Friday morning there and
you can check that out.
I've got a YouTube channel that you can find.
There's also the Untitled Linux Show still over at Twit.
That's twit.tv.
I think it's twit.tv/uls.
But we have a lot of fun there talking about what's going on with Linux and lots of open
source stuff, but more news of the week over there as opposed to the long interview forum
here.
Yeah, we appreciate everyone that watches, that get us both live and on the download,
and we will see you next week on Floss Weekly.